<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/guidelines/master/schema/tei-betamesaheftGL.rng" 
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/guidelines/master/schema/tei-betamesaheftGL.rng" 
type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Additional</title>
        <author>Pietro Liuzzo</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Produced by pandoc. Conversion from GIT flavoured markdown to TEI simple.</p>
        <p>transformed to TEI documentation with XSLT by Pietro Liuzzo</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="additionalInfo">
      <head>Additional</head>
      <p>This is used for any other information related to the manuscript. Note <gi>surrogates</gi>
        where for example microfilms or photographs should be recorded.</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <adminInfo>
          <recordHist>
            <source>
              <listBibl type="catalogue">
                <bibl>
                  <ptr target="EMML"/>
                  <citedRange unit="volume">V</citedRange>
                  <citedRange unit="page">354-356</citedRange>
                </bibl>
              </listBibl>
            </source>
          </recordHist>
          <custodialHist>
            <custEvent type="restoration" subtype="modern"/>
          </custodialHist>
        </adminInfo>
        <surrogates>
          <bibl corresp="EMML1234"/>
          <bibl corresp="ES4567"/>
        </surrogates>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>Ms. previously unknown</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </egXML>
      <p>For custodial history events use @subtype with one of the suggested values from the <ref
          target="https://github.com/SChAth/Authority-Files/blob/master/Restoration.xml"
          >corresponding taxonomy</ref>. oXygen should prompt them from the schema.</p>

      <p>Here the <gi>msDesc</gi> or <gi>msPart</gi> ends. Check that all is well nested and that
        all elements up to <gi>fileDesc</gi> are closed. *** ## Profile Description</p>
      <div type="level3">
        <head>People</head>
        <p>Important people related to the manuscript can be listed in <gi>particDesc</gi> with a
          list of pointers to names with a specific role. Allowed value of role here are * donor *
          scribe * other * ...</p>
        <p>Here it is enough to enumerate the scribe, owner, donor and patron, not everyone
          mentioned in the manuscript. If this information has already been stated elswhere in the
          description - which is preferable - it doesn't need to be repeated.</p>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <particDesc>
            <listPerson>
              <person>
                <persName ref="PRS2232AubertR" role="donor"/>
              </person>
              <person>
                <persName ref="PRS2233Audon" role="scribe"/>
              </person>
              <person>
                <persName ref="PRS2233Audon" role="other"/>
              </person>
            </listPerson>
          </particDesc>
        </egXML>
        <p>You can also be more precise and assign a @corresp to the <gi>persName</gi> if for
          example a person has commissioned only a specific part.</p>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <person>
            <persName role="patron" ref="PRS9170TaklaIy" corresp="#p1"/>
          </person>
        </egXML>

      </div>
      <div type="level3">
        <head>Keywords</head>
        <p>These keywords are used for the whole record. You can point use one or more of the values
          provided for <att>key</att>. You can assign as many keywords as needed. This means that it
          is not necessary to limit the keywords to the principal text, but keywords for any
          additional or minor texts contained in the manuscript should also be assigned. Always
          assign a period keyword, using the keywords referring to Ethiopian literary periods only
          in records actually belonging to the Ethiopian tradition. The keywords
          "ChristianLiterature", "IslamicLiterature" and "BetaEsraelLiterature" should be assigned
          to all records belonging to these traditions.</p>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <textClass>
            <keywords>
              <term key="ChristianLiterature"/>
              <term key="Gon"/>
              <term key="Liturgy"/>
            </keywords>
          </textClass>
        </egXML>

      </div>
      <div type="level3">
        <head>Languages</head>
        <p>within <gi>langUsage</gi> all languages used in the file should be defined. It is not a
          problem if one of these statements is not relevant to the current record, but if another
          language is used, it should be defined.</p>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">English</language>
            <language ident="it">Italian</language>
            <language ident="gez">Gəʿəz</language>
          </langUsage>
        </egXML>
        <p>If you add somewhere e.g.</p>
        <p>, there should be a <gi>language</gi> element in <gi>langUsage</gi> like the
          following</p>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <language ident="am">Amharic</language>
        </egXML>
        <p>the values of <att>ident</att> here are restricted, so you should not be able to add e.g.
          amh as value for <att>ident</att> and consequently use it in the file as value of
            <att>xml:lang</att>.</p>
        <p>Regardless of the validity of this transliteration, Gəʿəz is always referred to by
          "Gəʿəz" to ensure consistency.</p>

      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
