<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/guidelines/master/schema/out/tei-betamesaheftGL.rng"
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/guidelines/master/schema/out/tei-betamesaheftGL.rng"
type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Aligning transliteration and morphological annotations with Alpheios Alignment Tool</title>
            <author>Pietro Liuzzo</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>encoded in TEI</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>       <revisionDesc>       <change who="PL" when="2021-09-30">encoded as part of new release</change>     </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body xml:id="contributing">
        <p>The <ref target="https://alignment.alpheios.net/">Alpheios Alignment Tool</ref> is designed to align multiple versions of a text in different languages.
      We use it to align Fidal and the <ref target="transliteration-principles">transliteration</ref> so that morphological annotations can be made on the transliteraterated text.</p>
          <p>Instructions on how to do the alignment and annotation can be found in the <ref target="https://github.com/BetaMasaheft/alpheiosannotations/blob/main/README.md">GitHub repository</ref> where a video is screencast of an example is also available.</p>
<p>You can key in your texts, import them from files, from TEI or from the DTS API.</p>
        <p>Annotations produced in this way are entirely compatible with the TEI export of annotations made with the GETA tool during the TraCES project.</p>
        <p>This workflow, feeding directly the data to the morphological parser increments directly the available data for searches in Beta Masaheft as well. It is more suited for smaller
        parts of work and does not feature the text-length functionalities of a dedicated tool. This way of contributing morphological annotations is however much more flexible and straight forward and therefore particularly adequate for small tasks with immediate impact.</p>
        </body>
      </text>
    </TEI>
