<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/guidelines/master/schema/out/tei-betamesaheftGL.rng"
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/guidelines/master/schema/out/tei-betamesaheftGL.rng"
type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Catalogue Workflow</title>
        <author>Pietro Liuzzo</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Encoded natively in XML by Pietro Liuzzo</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>

      <change who="PL" when="2021-11-18">first version based on Dorothea, Denis, Mersha's works</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="catalogueworkflow">
      <div type="level1">
        <head>A Digital-first Collaborative Catalogue of Manuscripts</head>
<p>This is a strategic page, very similar to the one about the workflow for
  <ref target="editionworkflow">a digital-first collaborative critical edition</ref>. It is not meant to be
  comprehensive or tutorial-like, but to give you the right pointers in an organized fashion.</p>
        <p>There are many ways to do a digital-first catalogue or handlist which can then be the basis for a paper
          based product. Some tools are listed <ref target="https://doi.org/10.2307/j.ctvrnfr3q.14"
            >here</ref>, and can be found looking at the <ref target="trainingmaterials.xml"
            >training materials</ref> many more exist based on XML, LaTeX, etc.
            One example is <bibl>Nosnitsin and Reule 2021</bibl>, entirely based on data edited in the online research environment.

           Each workflow comes with its requirements and learning curve.
          Needless to say the best one is the one which works best for you and your needs. This page
          describes one possibility which benefits at several stages from the commonly edited data
          in Beta maṣāḥǝft (BM) and contributes in several citable and version-aware ways to it. It
          has never been used for a real project although it has been possible already for some
          years. By going through the hypothetical phases of the work involved for a catalogue of mansucripts
           we link to those resources and pages of documentation which are
          available. These do not need to be useded in the exact ways described. The page here will
          also try to clarify what can and what cannot be supported in such a process. The key idea
          is that what works for you and gets the result done tidily for you, does not necessarily
          mean it is the best thing to do for the future and for others, neither the smartest or
          more adequate to  state-of-the-art methodology. Taking a few steps towards a deeply
          collaborative way of working benefits you, the quality of your work and the direct impact
          of that on others, so, it is definitely worth it. </p>
        <p>The digital-first workflow presented here is based on the principle of separation of
          concerns, which is typical of the word of coding and programming. This methodological
          approach involves the splitting of as many different levels of concern as it is possible
          and useful. Instead of trying to do everything into one tool and with one method, each
          separate part of the work is done with a specifically designed method. The most common and
          basic separation of concerns is the separation between the concern about the semantic
          annotation of the text and that of its rendering on the printed page. Instead of saying
            <q>I make a footnote to indicate the list of variants for this passage, and I put it
            here because it looks nice</q>. we turn it around and think <q>I mark the variants as
            variants.</q> and then in a separate step <q>I want the variants to be listed in
            footnotes.</q> and in yet another independently-documented step <q>I want the footnotes
            to be arranged in this way because it looks nice.</q> Separating the steps also allows
          for much more control and consequently consistence. Mastering this concept is however not
          easy, because it requires a postponement of satisfaction, and thus a higher perceived
          risk. This page will try to persuade with evidence at each step of the falsity of this
          widely spread perception and serve as a reassurance that it is indeed the opposite which
          is true.</p>
        <p>With this in mind, within the Beta maṣāḥǝft Research Environment there are many things
          one can use, they will be linked in the different sections.</p>
        <p>This workflow is made possible by some set up and implementation choices made by the
          project, namely the TEI XML based data, the <ref
            target="https://distributed-text-services.github.io/specifications/">DTS API</ref> and
          the GitHub based collaborative workflow.</p>
        <div type="level2">
          <head>Requirements Identification</head>
          <p>To start with the right foot, one should be quite clear from the outset about the
            desired final output. In most cases if working at a catalogue this will involve
            the requirements of the editors of the article or book and the structure of the entry for one manuscript.
            Typically none of these requirements should prevent any
            of the following steps, that is to say, there is no such excuse as <quote>the editor
              does not let me</quote>.</p>
          <p>My suggestion: make a list or one, possibly complete, example of the input (XML) and output (your entry in the catalogue).
            If you did not do this before submitting your project
            and getting your funding, I suggest it is the first thing you do once you have been
            approved.</p>
          <div type="level3">
            <head>Benefits to you</head>
            <p>If you know what you are doing from the beginning, where it will land, everything
              will be easier. e.g. if the translation goes in a different book, then you will avoid
              wasting time with the alignment on facing pages, etc.</p>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div type="level2">
          <head>Start from the output...</head>
          <p>While in the other example for a critical edition we start from the data, here,
            let us start from the product setup.</p>
          <p>In the <ref target="https://github.com/BetaMasaheft/makepdf/tree/master"
              >GitHub Make PDF repository (Beta Masaheft)</ref> you can find all the details of a customizable
               package to allow you producing a PDF output from the data. It is the same used in the Catalogue of the manuscripts of Dayr as Suryan.
               It will include the full potential of the research environment collaborative work, that
            is, you do only the cataloguing, all the rest is done, which may not be always the case but
            is more and more so, since so many people contribute to the common good.</p>
          <p>If you open that package in Oxygen, open driver.xml and click play, the package will
            use BM to fetch resources from the research environment and print your book.</p>
          <p>The package is easily customizable with the <ref
              target="https://github.com/BetaMasaheft/makepdf/blob/master/settings.xml"
              >settings</ref> file not only for the layout features but also for the parts, their
            order, the contents and is all in TEI and XQuery, the standard languages of data for the
            humanities. The main functionalities are <ref
              target="https://github.com/BetaMasaheft/makepdf">documented here</ref> and the
            typesetting is done in Oxygen XML Editor using XSL-FO and Apache FOP.</p>
          <p>To use it, please fork (not branch) the repository to your own
            GitHub account.</p>
          <div type="level3">
            <head>Benefits to you</head>
            <p>Relying on your work file, which is included locally, so it can be on your branch
              only and not yet public, the script will use the data stored in BM as XML and the DTS
              API to fetch information to compile your book. For example, <list>
                <item>it will print out the parts that you want in the order that you chose always consistently</item>
                <item>it will collect bibliography and print it into a specific section using the
                  HLZ styles and the EthioStudies library pulling citations from the edition, the
                  driver file and the related manuscripts.</item>
                <item>it will format the text benefiting from the encoding</item>
                <item>it will collect all named entities and print the indexes (also selected in settings).</item>
                <item>it will attempt at listing plates, if you so desire.</item>
              </list>
            </p>
            <p>Of course, as you change your data, either the manuscripts or the edition running the
              transformation will update the output.</p>
            <p><emph>All </emph>can be customized, entirely changed, adapted, features can be added, etc. You can
              read the script or ask somebody who can read it for you, is one file only. For example, if a translation is provided it can be put in the facing page and kept aligned with its own apparata.</p>
            <p>Fine touches can be done in the XSL-FO, as this is also simply an XML file.</p>
          </div>
          <div type="level3">
            <head>Benefits to the community</head>
           <p>Any one could follow the same steps or some of them here to reproduce your work. Anyone will be able to find the exact point and layer of the information which can be criticized (or not), if they wanted to.</p> <p>Let us imagine that the same package is used by two scholars for two editions of texts which
              happen to share a witness. The description of the witness may be exactly the same in
              both. The authority files unequivocal, the data directly indexed and retrievable, the
              consistency ensured across different editions. Sure, there is much more that can be
              done...</p>
          </div>
          </div>
        <div type="level2">
          <head>Select the manuscripts</head>
          <p>Most likely if you are setting of on the journey to build a catalogue or a thematic list of manuscripts, you
            know where to find your manuscripts and probably already know which are where. Just in
            case you do not yet, or you are looking for more, <ref target="https://betamasaheft.eu/">Beta maṣāḥǝft</ref> may help
            you. Search for the title of your work, open the relevant work, and on the right, in
            red, you will find a list of manuscripts, sorted by type of content and eventually also
            telling you about other textual units related to the one you are looking for.</p>
          <p>This kind of search may not however bring you to the digital surrogates directly. <ref
              target="https://betamasaheft.eu/availableImages.html">The project also maintains a
              list of available images.</ref></p>

          <div type="level3">
            <head>Benefits to you</head>
            <p>Well, you may find in the research environment manuscript descriptions and images,
              curated by a team and peer reviewed. That does not sound bad, isn't it? Just add your bit, and make sure you correctly attribute the rest.</p>
          </div>
          <div type="level3">
            <head>Benefits to the community</head>
            <p>What about the others? Those which you know about and are not in the research
              environment? Those you went to inspect and catalogue yourself?
              Consider as a first step having a unified type of information, the TEI used by the project. Thus
              describing the manuscripts and linking the images and the text in the research
              environment will allow you to benefit from the exising information. <ref target="manuscripts">Catalogue descriptions</ref> can be long or
              short there are no requirement.</p>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div type="level2">
          <head>Encode, print, check, report, correct, repeat</head>
          <p>You are all set. Add the manuscripts, indexes will update at every run, add new information, change it, simply encode following this guidelines and
          look at the output. Chances are that the output will not look as you want. If it is not one of the customizable settings
           you can either try to read the Xquery or simply ask somebody who knows to help you.
           If you keep your project in GitHub help will come as easy as a commit to your repository.</p>
           <p>The clearer you explain what the source is and what the output is that you expect, the easier the fix.</p>
          </div>
        <div type="level2">
          <head>Deposit Your Dataset</head>
          <p>Working with the data in the research environment will provide you with<ref target="https://betamasaheft.eu/pid.html"> stable citable references</ref> for each committed and merged version of your files. But what about the entire group of resources you have used? To make the set really reproducible and your collected resources citable as a set, e.g. with your TEI edition, the files of the manuscript description has you have used them in the final version and eventually the script, you may deposit them in Zenodo or another similar repository.</p>
          <div type="level3">
            <head>Benefits to you</head>
            <p>Your dataset, as a group of resources will be citable. You may also submit a data paper to describe your dataset.</p>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div type="level2">
          <head>Copyright of remixed content</head>
          <p>As every single page of our website states, as well as each file in the Beta Masaheft dataset, the copyright of the data is of the Akademie der Wissenschaften in Hamburg, Hiob-Ludolf-Zentrum für Äthiopistik. Sharing and remixing are permitted under terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International License. Therefore books created remixing and reusing this data (catalogues, editions, etc.) should have the same copyright, or a formulation equally or more permissive adequately negotiated with the publisher.</p>
          <p>Publication products generated from BM data must respect this copyright and
            should contain appropriate attribution to all contributors. The above PDF producing script does some of this, not all that can be done!
Once all is ok, the book/article is ready the licensing of the data, with the agreement of the above copyright owners,
can be upgraded for commercial use as well, so that the publisher can print and sell (CC-BY-SA-NC —> CC-BY-SA).
This is possible and positive, as it allows even more reuse.
A Deposit of the source data, as descrbed above can be made and a DOI of the data deposit added to the book content.
Copyright of the book/article, product of the remix of data, can be silently or formally passed to the editor.
The statement in the book, in respect to the original copyright should state (C) editor name… CC-BY-SA, or an equally allowing licence
as the data on which it is based requires. Editors can commercialise it and sell the book no problem respecting this copyright.
As soon as possible and following agreement with the editor the data can additionally be made Open Access.
The DOI of the open access book is added to the deposit of the data with the proper relation so that the two DOI know about each other.

This example workflow yields the following distinct products, each of which is distinctly and separately citable, adding to each other over time:
<list>
    <item>publication of the source data NC until publication CC-BY-SA-NC (C) Akademie+HLCEES +  Open Access and versioned in GitHub</item>
    <item>publication of the source data after publication CC-BY-SA (C) Akademie+HLCEES + Open Access and versioned in GitHub</item>
<item>HTML versions of the data throughout CC-BY-SA-NC (C) Akademie+HLCEES + Openly available, with indepently generated Permanent Identifiers for reference and stable URIs for data relations.</item>
<item>Several additional data formats remixes with CC-BY-SA-NC (C) Akademie+HLCEES + Openly available</item>
<item>publication of the dataset for the publication  CC-BY-SA (C) Akademie+HLCEES + Open Access for the dataset with DOI</item>
<item>the print publication  CC-BY-SA (C) Editor</item>
<item>the digital publication  CC-BY-SA (C) Editor + Open Access for book with DOI.</item>
<item>An additional versions of the DOI of the deposit of the data, once this is updated with relation to the DOI of the book.</item>
</list>
This flow is, to the knowledge of the author of this page, consistent licencing-wise, protects the contents from commercialisation until necessary, allows sales, has no time impacts, no costs impacts, is ready for open access... is quite simple... enforces collaboration, so, is a win win win and win again. with no side effects!
</p>
        </div>
        <div type="level2">
          <head>Retrodigitizing</head>
          <p>You have done the work in all another way.
            Old school, as if none of this existed.
            But you want to contribute it to the community.
            You will need patience, a lot of it, becuase you are looking at doing the work twice.
            While getting an output from a semantically encoded set of files is possible,
            the other way around is tedious and error prone.
            </p>
          <div type="level3">
            <head>Benefits to you</head>
            <p>You will be doing the job a second time, it will be tedious. You will wish you had worked in another way from the beginning. By the way, nobody can actually help you much, but hey, your mess, you tidy it up...</p>
          </div>
          <div type="level3">
            <head>Benefits to the community</head>
            <p>Everyone will be glad to have one more digital resource so that the next edition can be based on that.</p>
          </div>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
