<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/guidelines/master/schema/out/tei-betamesaheftGL.rng"
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/guidelines/master/schema/out/tei-betamesaheftGL.rng"
type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Colophons, Titles and Supplications</title>
        <author>Pietro Liuzzo</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Originally written in XML TEI</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="PL" when="2019-06-28">first version from
        https://github.com/BetaMasaheft/Documentation/issues/946 and related issues, examples from
        document provided by Denis Nosnitsin and Dorothea Reule.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="ColophSupplTit">
      <head>Colophons, Titles and Supplications</head>
      <p>These three concepts are here treated together as they tend to overlap in discussion. We
        will try in this page to clarify our understanding and the way in which we encode each
        case.</p>
      <p>The elements used are <gi>title</gi> and <gi>div</gi> with <att>subtype</att>,
          <gi>colophon</gi>, <gi>incipit</gi>, <gi>explicit</gi>, <gi>seg</gi> with
        <att>type</att>. In <gi>title</gi> and <gi>div</gi> the attribute <att>type</att> is 
      used for a more general typology. Each of these elements can take as much text as available 
      and needed, from nothing to many thousands of words.</p>
      <p>Since some of these elements, can be used also for additions, it is possible with the same set 
        of tags and attributes also to encode for example a supplication and an extended title added at a moment later than the copy of the text. </p>
      <p>In either case the list of values which can be used for the attribute <att>type</att> or
          <att>subtype</att> is the same. More than one value can be used, up to six. </p>
      <!-- needs to find its place in the schema as well! -->
      <list>
        <item>"expanded" contains the title, tafaṣṣama/malʾa and further information</item>
        <item>"inscription" is used for a title occurring at the beginning of a work</item>
        <item>"subscription" for a title occurring at the end of a work</item>
        <item>"embedded" for a title copied together with the text</item>
        <item>"supplication" for a supplication</item>
        <item>"translation" to signal that the title is only of a translation</item>
      </list>
      <p> When used in <gi>div</gi> or <gi>seg</gi> other two values can be used</p>
      <list>
        <item>"title" contains the title as well as tafaṣṣama/malʾa or similar expression</item>
        <item>"desinit" to qualify expressions as tafaṣṣama/malʾa</item>
      </list>
      <p>types/subtypes should be combined to describe the exact situation as it presents itself in each work, 
        possibly in the form of, as in the following example from <ref type="bm" target="LIT5673AkkonuColl">LIT5673AkkonuColl</ref></p>
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="title inscriptio" xml:id="Title">
    <label>Title</label>
  </div>
</egXML>
      <p>Why so many ways to do this, which might seam one single topic? Because of the way
        information is entered. There are cases when we know there is a colophon and that is it, we
        do not know what its content is and we have no way to retrieve that information. Sometime we
        are working on a manuscript record and we do not know enough the textual unit, so we need to
        register as much as possible, but not overstate. Fortunately, all these different
        informations can be collected together, and the use of the same set of attributes can
        help. An additional reason for this is that these information can be joined to one 
        another, there might be a colophon which contains a title, and certainly a generic 
      incipit or explicit might contain, with other things also a title, but is generically the 
      beginning of a text part, which needs not to be a title or anything else, although it might be. 
      It is up to the encoder to make decisions for example if a long title before a text is all there is in a <gi>incipit</gi> given 
        by a cataloguer, the encoder might decide to have an <gi>incipit</gi> with a <att>type</att> <val>inscription</val>, 
        or copy the text in the title element of the <gi>msItem</gi>.</p>
      <p>A special note needs to be made for <gi>seg</gi> which can be used within <gi>colophon</gi>, <gi>incipit</gi>, <gi>explicit</gi>, <gi>div</gi> </p>
      <div type="level2">
        <head>Colophons</head>
        <p>For a definition of the colophons of a manuscript, see <ref target="colophon">the page on
            colophon</ref>.</p>
        <p>Titles (sometimes referred to as "colophon of the work") transmitted in all manuscripts
          will be encoded in the work record and titles particular to one manuscript in the
          manuscript record. Cases like the ones discussed for Coptic Biblical Titles <ref
            target="https://www.aai.uni-hamburg.de/en/comst/pdf/bulletin3/comst-bulletin3-1-05-22.pdf"
            >Buzi 2017, 5–6</ref> would need encoding in each manuscript without any doubt. The next
          section details a number of types of titles which can be encoded in a work, with examples
          of how to encode them.</p>
        <p>There is no need to add a <att>type</att> to every <gi>colophon</gi>, but the attribute and values should be used cautiously, 
          so that when one searches for a colophon with a certain type, will match that and not something simply copied over.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="level2">
        <head>Titles (colophon of the work)</head>
        <p>This can be encoded in the work record, but also in the manuscript description or
          transcription.</p>
        <p>While the best option is to encode them in the manuscript transcription, using an
          appropriate <gi>div</gi> with <att>subtype</att> using a combination of the values above,
          it is often the case that there is no transcription, and the encoder is left to decide if
          to put this within the <gi>msItem</gi> or directly in the work record.</p>
        <p>If adding a fixed text only in the work record, <gi>div</gi> with <att>subtype</att> or
            <gi>seg</gi> with <att>type</att> using a combination of the values above.</p>

        <p>This is an example in the transcription of a manuscript <ref type="bm" target="BNFet152"
            >BNFet152</ref>.</p>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <div type="textpart" subtype="title" xml:lang="gez" corresp="#ms_i1">
            <ab> ዝንቱ፡ መጽሐፈ፡ ትምህርት፡ ዘልሳነ፡ ግዕዝ፡ ዛይሳመይ፡ ከሌዳዊ፡ <gap reason="omitted" extent="unknown"
                resp="PRS10747Zotenbe"/>
            </ab>
          </div>
        </egXML>
        <p>This is an example in the edition of a work, where also <val>title</val> is used from
            <ref target="LIT1968Mashaf" type="bm">LIT1968Mashaf</ref>.</p>

        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <div type="textpart" subtype="title inscription expanded">
            <div type="textpart" subtype="paragraph" n="1">
              <ab> ዝንቱ፡ መጽሐፈ፡ ሥርዓት፡ ዘወፅአ፡ እመንበረ፡ ማርቆስ፡ ሐዋርያ፡ እመካነ፡ መዓልቃ፡ ዘምስር፡ </ab>
            </div> ... </div>
        </egXML>
        <div type="level3">
          <head>Title of the (entire) work</head>
          <p>See for example in the manuscripts with the <ref type="bm" target="LIT3179Revela"
              >Revelation of John</ref>, the wording like <foreign xml:lang="gez">ዝየ᎓ ተፈጸመ᎓ ራእየ᎓
              ዮሐንስ᎓ አቡቀለምሲስ᎓ ዘውእቱ᎓ በሕይወቱ᎓ ራእይ᎓ ብሂል᎓</foreign> e.g. <ref
              target="https://betamasaheft.eu/manuscripts/IVsuhtelen252/main#ms_i1.2">Saint
              Petersburg, Institut Vostočnyh Rukopisej Rossijskoj Akademii Nauk, IV Suhtelen 252,
              content item 1.2</ref>
          </p>
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.2">
              <locus from="66ra" to="99vb"/>
              <title type="complete" ref="LIT3179Revela" xml:lang="gez"/>
              <incipit xml:lang="gez">
                <hi rend="rubric">ዘዮሐንስ᎓ እጲስ᎓</hi> ቆጶስ᎓ ዘቍስጥንጥያ᎓ ምጥረ᎓ ጶሊስ᎓ አመ᎓ ሀለዎ᎓ ይሰደድ᎓ ራእዮ᎓
                ለዮሐንስ᎓ ዘከመ᎓ ርእዮ᎓ ለኢየሱስ᎓ ክርስቶስ᎓ ዘወሀቦ᎓ እግዚኣብሔር᎓ ከመ᎓ ያርእዩሙ᎓ ለአግብርቲሁ᎓ ዘሀሎ᎓ ይኩን᎓ ፍጡነ ። </incipit>
              <explicit xml:lang="gez"> ዝየ᎓ ተፈጸመ᎓ ራእየ᎓ ዮሐንስ᎓ አቡቀለምሲስ᎓ ዘውእቱ᎓ ብሂል᎓ ዘርእየ᎓ በሕይወቱ᎓ ራእየ፨
                ወእመቦ᎓ ዘገደፍኩ᎓ ወዘወሰኩ᎓ በኢያእምሮ᎓ ስረዩ᎓ ወባረኩ᎓ ላዕሌየ᎓ ወኢትርስዑኒ᎓ በሞትየ᎓ ወበሕይወትየ᎓ ሶበ᎓ አንበብክምዋ።
              </explicit>
            </msItem>
          </egXML>
          <p>This could have been added in a div in the transcription as well. Note that in this
            case the encode has added no <att>type</att> in <gi>incipit</gi> or <gi>explicit</gi>.
              <gi>seg</gi> or <gi>title</gi> may be used inside these elements to markup the exact
            portion of the incipit of explicit which is an inscription or subscription, for example,
            either here or in the transcription as in the example above.</p>
          <p> Other examples of short colophons can be found at the end of some of the Old Testament
            books (esp. Octateuch). Cp. <ref type="bm" target="ESaqg008">AQG-008</ref>, Octateuch:
              <foreign xml:lang="gez">ተፈጸመ᎓ ኦሪት᎓ ዘፀአት; ኦሪት᎓ ዘሌዋዊያን᎓ ተፈጸመ᎓</foreign>, etc. or at the
            end of Aksumite collection (<ref type="bm" target="ESum039">UM-039</ref>), <ref
              target="https://www.zotero.org/groups/358366/ethiostudies/items/tag/bm%3Abausi2016colof"
              >Bausi 2016, 240</ref>. Cp. <ref type="bm" target="ESdd042">DD-042</ref>, Zena Ayhud,
            f. 158r-v <foreign xml:lang="gez">ተፈጸመ፡ መጽሐፈ፡ ዮሴፍ፡ ወልደ፡ ከርዮን፡ ካህን፡ ዘያየድዕ፡ ዜና፡ አይሁድ፡ ውስተ፡
              ቤት፡ ዳግማዊ። ወዝክረ፡ ነገሥቶሙ፡ ወነገር፡ ዘኮነ፡ በመዋዕሊሆሙ፡ እም፡ አመ፡ ሕንጸተ፡ ቤት፡ ዳግማዊ፡ ወግአቶሙ፡ ኀቤሁ፡ እስከ፡
              ተነሥተ፡ ወተፄወው፡ እምኔሁ። ስብሐት፡ ወአኰቴት። ዝማሬ፡ ወዕበይ፡ ስጊድ፡ ወክብር። ግናይ፡ ወውዳሴ፡ ክብር: ለእግዚአብሔር፡ ክቡር፡
              ወልዑል። እስከ፡ ለዓለመ፡ ዓለም። ወለትውልደ፡ ትውልድ፡ ዘኢየሐልቅ፡ አሜን። ወአሜን፡ለይኩን፡ ለይኩ</foreign>
          </p>
          <figure>
            <graphic xml:id="g1"
              url="https://betamasaheft.eu/iiif/KAE/011/KAE-011__005.tif/info.json">
              <desc><ref type="bm" target="ESdd042">DD-042</ref>, Zena Ayhud, f. 158r</desc>
            </graphic>
            <graphic xml:id="g2"
              url="https://betamasaheft.eu/iiif/DD/042/DD-042_159.tif/info.json">
              <desc><ref type="bm" target="ESdd042">DD-042</ref>, Zena Ayhud, f. 158v </desc>
            </graphic>
          </figure>
          <p>This could be reproduced in the manuscript transcription using a <gi>div</gi> with
              <gi>subtype</gi> having the values title, embedded and subscription, but would need to
            be in the manuscript transcription, not in the work because the fact it is embedded
            hints at the fact that it is not a constant of the tradition of this text.</p>

          <p>In a few cases the colophon of the work is extensive, e.g., in the <ref
              target="LIT3973GadlaT" type="bm">Vita of Takla Hāymānot</ref>.</p>
        </div>
        


        <div type="level3">
          <head>Title of a work which is part of a collection</head>
          <p>The identification of this type of title depends on how the structure of the work in
            question is understood. However this level of interpretation will be encoded as well, so that the position of the information will be enough to provide the information about the fact that a 
          title regards only a part: it will be nested into it, either as a <gi>div</gi> or a <gi>msItem</gi>.</p>
          <p>An example of this can be <ref target="ESum018" type="bm">UM-018</ref>, f. 18vb, 
            followed by a supplication; f. 37rb; possibly with a date, f. 56rb; 77vb, followed by a subscription; 
            possibly f. 88va; f. 123va; possibly f. 241b; f. 252vb.
            
            In <ref target="ESmgm013" type="bm">MGM-013</ref>, the Vita of Gabra Manfas Qeddus
            and the Miracles each has a colophon, f. 52va <foreign xml:lang="gez">ተፈጸመ፡ በዝየ፡ ገድለ፡ አቡነ፡</foreign>…; f. 68va, 
            <foreign xml:lang="gez">ተፈጸመ፡ በዝየ፡ ተአምረ፡ አቡነ፡ ገብረ፡</foreign>….
            <ref
              target="https://www.zotero.org/groups/358366/ethiostudies/items/tag/bm%3Abausi2016colof"
              >Bausi 2016, 253–54</ref>, for the Ethiopic Apocalypse of Peter (The last two lines<foreign xml:lang="gez"> ለዛቲ᎓ መጽሐፍ᎓ ዘአጽሐፋ᎓</foreign>… 
            can be considered also as a separate unit, a commissioner note or supplication for the commissioner).</p>
          
        </div>
       
       
        
        
        <div type="level3">
          <head>Title of  a part of the work</head>
          <p>The identification of this type of title depends on how the structure of the work in
            question is understood. However this level of interpretation will be encoded as well, so that the position of the information will be enough to provide the information about the fact that a 
            title regards only a part: it will be nested into a <gi>div</gi>.</p>
          <p><ref target="ESam002" type="bm">AM-002</ref>, Sinodos, f. 40vb ተፈጸመ᎓ ተፈሥሑ᎓ ቀዳሜ᎓ ብሔር᎓; f. 68rb: ተፈጸመ᎓ ኃምስ᎓ ብሔር᎓ etc.
            Aksumite collection (<ref target="ESmum039" type="bm">UM-039</ref>),
            e.g., f. 117/46rb ተፈጸመ᎓ ሥርዓተ᎓ ጥምቀት᎓; f. 61/134 ተፈጸመት᎓ እንተ᎓ በከልቂዶን᎓ etc.
            Nearly all copies of the Synaxarion have these colophons, always at the end of the part for each month.
            Cp. <ref target="ESsdm008" type="bm">SDM-008</ref>.
          </p>
        </div>
        
        <div type="level3">
          <head>Title of the translation of the entire work</head>
          <p>The identification of this type of title depends on how the structure of the work in
            question is understood.</p>
          <p>Nearly all copies of Maṣḥafa krǝstǝnnā (sometimes it is preceded by the colophon of the work), 
            see, e.g., <ref target="ESdz011" type="bm">DZ-011</ref>, f. 47rb; <ref target="ESmr039" type="bm">MR-039</ref>, f. 36rb.
            Nearly all copies of Aragāwi manfasāwi (sometimes followed by the colophon of the manuscript), 
            cp. <ref target="ESmakm012" type="bm">MAKM-012</ref>, <ref target="ESgkm011" type="bm">GKM-001</ref>.
            <ref target="ESdd015" type="bm">DD-015</ref>, Maṣḥafa ḥāwi, f. 12r, refers to the beginning and the end of the translation.
            <ref
              target="https://www.zotero.org/groups/358366/ethiostudies/items/tag/bm%3Abausi2016colof"
              >Bausi 2016, 249–50</ref>: the colophon of the Kebra nagast.
            <ref target="ESdd012" type="bm">DD-012</ref>, Commentaries on the Epistle of John, f. 315vb:  
            <foreign xml:lang="gez">ተፈጸመ፡ በረድኤተ፡ እግዚአብሔር፡ ልዑል፡ ወሀብተ፡ ጸገሁ፡ ወስብሀቲሁ፡ ትርጓሜ፡ አቡነ፡ ዓቢይ፡ በውስተ፡ ቅዱሳን፡ ዮሐንስ፡ አፈ፡ ወርቅ፡ 
            መልእክተ፡ ጳውሎስ፡ ሐዋርያ፡ ኀበ፡ ሰብአ፡ ዕብራውያን፡ ጸሎቶሙ፡ ወበረከቶሙ፡ ወሀብተ፡ ረድኤቶሙ፡ የሀሉ፡ ምስለ፡ ገብሮሙ፡ ዝክረ፡ ማርያም። 
            ተተርጐመት፡ እምልሳነ፡ ዓረብ፡ ለግዕዝ፡ በአፈ፡ ዕንባቆም፡ ወሚካኤል፡ በ፸፻፲ወ፭ዓመተ፡ ምሕረት። ወእምልደተ፡ ክርስቶስ፡ እግዚእነ፡ ወመድኃኒነ፡ 
            በ፲፻ወ፭፻ዓመት። ወእምዓመተ፡ ሰማዕታትኒ፡ በ፲፻ወ፪፻፴ወ፱ዓመት፡ ወፍፃሜኒ፡ ኮነ፡ በዕለተ፡ ሰኑይ፡ በወርኃ፡ ነሐሴ፡ አሜን። </foreign>
          </p>
          
        </div>
        
        
        <div type="level3">
          <head>Title of the translation of a work which is part of a
            collection</head>
          <p>Examples of titles of the translation of a part </p>
            <list>
              <item><ref target="ESum018" type="bm">UM-018</ref>, f. 115rb 
            <foreign xml:lang="gez">ወአዕለውነ᎓ ዘንተ᎓ ገድለ᎓ በመዋዕለ᎓ መፍቀሬ᎓ እግዚአብሔር᎓ ንጉሥ᎓ ገብረ᎓ መስቀል᎓ 
              ወዘተረጐሞ᎓ ቀሲስ᎓ ግብጻዊ᎓ ወስሙ᎓ ሚካኤል᎓ ወመካኑ᎓ ብሔረ᎓ ግብጽ᎓ ደብረ᎓ አባ᎓ ሲኖዳ</foreign>; f. 132r, etc.</item>
              <item><ref
                target="https://www.zotero.org/groups/358366/ethiostudies/items/tag/bm%3Abausi2016colof"
                >Bausi 2016, 243</ref>, colophon for the Vita of Bsoy (<ref target="BLorient692" type="bm">BritLib Orient 692</ref>, 
                <ref target="EMML7602" type="bm">EMML 7602</ref> Gadla  samāʿtāt).</item>
              <item><ref
              target="https://www.zotero.org/groups/358366/ethiostudies/items/tag/bm%3Abausi2016colof"
              >Bausi 2016, 243–244</ref>, Vat. Et. 264, for the Vita of Nob.</item>
              <item><ref
              target="https://www.zotero.org/groups/358366/ethiostudies/items/tag/bm%3Abausi2016colof"
              >Bausi 2016, 244</ref>, colophon with the date 678 in the <ref target="LIT2358Sirach" type="bm">Mashafa Sirak</ref> 
            (<ref type="bm" target="BNFet27">BN éth. 6</ref>).</item>
              <item><ref
              target="https://www.zotero.org/groups/358366/ethiostudies/items/tag/bm%3Abausi2016colof"
              >Bausi 2016, 246</ref>, colophon of the Acts of Kaleb from the Gadla  samāʿtāt of Zway (
            may be considered as composed of two units: colophon of the work, colophon of the translation).</item>
            </list>
        </div>
      
      </div>
      <div type="level2">
        <head>Supplications</head>
        <p>It is important to mark up supplications (or eulogy, or final blessing formula)
          wherever in a manuscript they can occur (beginning, end, within the text)</p>
        <p> In individual cases, it might be difficult to distinguish the colophon 
          from other material surrounding it, such as supplications.  
          Supplications, which are often not part of colophons or titles, are usually encoded 
          as <tag>explicit type="supplication"</tag> or <tag>incipit type="supplication"</tag> 
          as in this example from <ref type="bm" target="BDLpoc6">BDLpoc6</ref>. </p>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <incipit type="supplication" xml:lang="gez">
            ጸሎቱ፡ ወበረከቱ፡ የሀሉ፡ ምስለ፡
            <persName ref="PRS11601EdaM">እደ፡ ማርያም።</persName>
          </incipit>
        </egXML>
        <p>or this case from <ref type="bm" target="Parm3852">Parm3852</ref></p>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <explicit xml:lang="gez" type="supplication">
          <locus from="138rb" to="138va"/>
          ወለነኒ፡ ይጸግወነ፡ በረከቶ፡ ወይክፍለነ፡ ርስቶ፡ ወመክፈልቶ። ወምስለ፡ ኵሎሙ፡ ...
        </explicit>
        </egXML>
<p>        
          However, a supplication can be immediately followed or preceded by a colophon or be seamlessly contained in it. 
          In such cases it might be desirable to encode the supplication as part of the colophon, using <gi>seg</gi> inside it.</p>
        <p>The same can value for <att>subtype</att> can be used for a <gi>div</gi> in the 
          manuscript transcription or edition of a work as in the following example from <ref type="bm" target="LIT5061TaammeraA">LIT5061TaammeraA</ref>.</p>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <div type="textpart" subtype="supplication" xml:id="SupplicationTM" xml:lang="gez">
            <label>Supplication</label>
            <ab>
              ጸሎቱ፡ ትኵኖ፡ ወበረከተ፡ አምላኩ፡ ወትንብናሃ፡ ለእግዝእትነ፡ ማርያም፡ ጸሎታ፡ ወበረከታ፡ የሃሉ።
            </ab>
          </div>
        </egXML>
        <p>Supplications  in transcribed text that are integrated into the text and 
          cannot logically be encoded in <gi>incipit</gi> or <gi>explicit</gi> must be encoded in 
        either the manuscript transcription or the edition of the text, or both, using a 
          <tag>div subtype="supplication"</tag> or <tag>seg type="supplication"</tag> with </p>
        
        <p>Where the supplication is present only in one manuscript, 
          clearly separated from the other textparts, it can be marked there, using either <gi>incipit</gi>, <gi>explicit</gi>, <gi>colophon</gi> or <gi>seg</gi>
        as in the previous example, only in the manuscript where it occurs.</p>
        <p>Where the supplication is present only in one manuscript but seamlessly integrated into a 
          <gi>title</gi>, <gi>seg</gi> can be used or a portion of transcription be encoded with a <gi>div</gi> with the correct subtype.
        </p>
        <p>Where the supplication can be said to be part of the work 
          as it is transmitted in all manuscripts in the same place, but with varying names, the encoder my consider the option to use a narrative
          unit, and assign a narrative unit id to its supplication, and the using it in the edition, as a value for <att>corresp</att> on the dedicated 
          <gi>div</gi>. However, if the names are changing, then ideally it would be even nicer to have this encoded in each manuscript.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div type="level2">
        <head>Redundancy</head>
        <p>Given these many options it is possible to be redundant. Consider the following example.</p>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.8">
            <locus from="108va" to="110ra"/>
            <title type="complete" ref="LITREFERENCE"/>
            <title type="complete" subtype="inscription" ref="LITREFERENCE">
              <locus target="#108va"/>
            </title>
            <incipit>
              <locus target="#108va"/>
              text
            </incipit>
            <explicit xml:lang="gez">
              <locus from="109va" to="109vb"/>
             text
            </explicit>
          </msItem>
        </egXML>
        <p>In here the encoder is declaring the relation between the <gi>msItem</gi> and a textual unit twice, 
          once declaring an incipit, once not, and then also adding the incipit, which may contain the title again. There is no need to do all this, 
        it is enough to either
        <list><item>add the type <val>inscription</val> to the <gi>title</gi></item>
          <item>add the type <val>inscription</val> to the <gi>incipit</gi></item>
          <item>add the type <val>inscription</val> to a <gi>seg</gi> 
            inside the text copied either inside <gi>title</gi> or <gi>incipit</gi></item>
          <item>if this is fixed and is encoded in the work record, nothing really needs to be done here unless deviating from what is in the work record.</item>
        </list>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div type="level2">
        <head>Examples or queries to this information</head>
        <div type="level2">
          <head>Only bare titles of a work given in its text or in manuscript descriptions</head>
          <p>In the files of the work and of related manuscripts and parts or container of that work, with the manuscripts where those are contained,
            look for <gi>titles</gi>, <gi>explicit</gi>, <gi>incipit</gi>, <gi>colophon</gi>, <gi>div</gi> and <gi>seg</gi> which do NOT have the value <val>extended</val> for <att>type</att> or <att>subtype</att>.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="level2">
          <head> All types of colophons/titles referring to a work </head>
          <p>In the files of the work and of  manuscripts where it is contained look for any of the element discussed with at least one of the values discussed, (eventually could be expanded to include all).</p>
        </div>
        <div type="level2">
          <head> All translation colophons/titles</head>
          <p>Take any of the above elements with <att>type</att> or <att>subtype</att> with value 'translation'</p>
        </div>
        <div type="level2">
          <head> All translation colophons/titles in a subscription</head>
          <p>Take any of the above elements with <att>type</att> or <att>subtype</att> with value 'translation' and value 'subscription'.</p>
          <p>In the case of <gi>explicit</gi> take it also if it does not have <att>subtype</att> equal to subscription.</p>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
