<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/guidelines/master/schema/out/tei-betamesaheftGL.rng"
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/guidelines/master/schema/out/tei-betamesaheftGL.rng"
type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Create a new file, delete existing, deal with doublets</title>
            <author>Pietro Liuzzo</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
          </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>       <revisionDesc>
        <change who="PL" when="2019-11-20">Created file</change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body xml:id="create">
<div type="level1">
   <head>Create</head>
        <p>If you have editors' rights, you can create a file once logged in the application from the relevant page.</p>
        <p>If you are not, ask to be added.</p>
        <p>You can always check the data and add in the folder called "new" correct and validating files which adhere to these guidelines, with one exception:
          <ref target="Works">Work</ref> records can only be created in the application, because their IDs become CAe identifiers.</p>
        <p>Please follow the instructions given on the application after the creation of a new file with that procedure. After downloading and before committing
         the new file, always open it in your editor to make sure that it is valid and, if necessary (which it nearly always is!), edit it.</p>
</div>
         <div type="level1">
            <head>Example workflow</head>
            <p>It is not rare that a single unit of work will involve several commits to several branches of different repositories. Here is an example</p>
            <list rend="ordered">
               <item>The contributor starts to edit a manuscript record,</item>
               <item>she thinks an identifier for a new Textual Unit is needed,</item>
            <item> she      opens an issue, labeled Textual Unit Identification, ping relevant people and 
               make sure it is the case 
               (this helps also contributors who do not have enough permissions to 
               create Textual Units in the app). In the while, there is no need to add a <att>ref</att> to
            <gi>title</gi> in <gi>msItem</gi>, for example, and a comment can be left that there is a pending issue about the identification of the Textual Unit.</item>
              <item> 
                 If the result of the discussion is positive and a new records is needed,
                 the editor or some other collaborator creates it in the app (it needs to, is a textual unit!),</item>
              <item> 
                 Because the Textual Unit record has been created in the app, it needs to be synced.
                 Make a PR to Works repository and make sure it is promptly reviewed, corrected and merged. 
                 Planning this 
                 in the issue where you discussed the creation is a good idea.
                 Please note that it really needs to be merged quickly, to keep the app in sync.
              </item> 
               <item>Anyone can now use the newly created 
                  Textual Unit ID in  manuscript records.
              </item> 
               <item>Once she is ready, a PR for the manuscript can be done to Manuscript.
               </item>
               <item>During review it turns out it was not necessary to create a Textual Unit, alas. A collaborator reviewing this PR did not see the discussion and could not intervene before.
               </item>
               <item>The editor or any other collaborator can now delete the 
                  record in the Works repository and make a PR justified by the
                  review of the manuscript, and eventually needs no review if linked to that.
                  By doing this also the app, where the record was created, gets to know and stays in sync.
             </item>
            </list>
            <p>A record creation in the app should always be promptly followed by a 
               commit and a PR to align to the database in any case. If the discussion about this 
               operation has already happened, review only needs to focus on typos and contents of the record.
              The app will have learned about the new files because they were created in there 
              in the first place, but if you do not merge them into master, as a result of a PR and delete them
              the app will never get to know that the record was deleted, 
              because you deleted it somewhere else. 
              That is why we need a commit and a PR, so that repository and database stay in sync.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="level1">
            <head>Doublets</head>
            <p>It can happen that doublets are identified. This happens especially when Textual Units are created without enough disambiguation information
            or when one same manuscript is entered in the system from different sources without prior knowledge 
            and due diligence to identify the already existing record. It is however normal and will always happen.</p>
            <p>If you identify a doublet, it is wise to deal with it in some way or another 
            and it is often advisable to consult with other editors and collaborators about this, exactly 
            because there may be reasons to have those different records.</p>
            <p>
               If it is clear that a record is superfluous, 
               delete it, properly document this in the commit, make sure the deleted identifier is
               not used elsewhere, update existing references,
               but also add a relation in the record which survives, like the following.
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <relation 
                     name="betmas:formerlyAlsoListedAs" 
                     active="IDofthesurvivedrecord"
                     passive="IDofthedeletedrecord"/>
               </egXML>
               If you delete more than one, the same can be said for each. If the deleted ID is requested
               a redirect will fetch the surviving record.
            </p>
            <p>It may be also that in cases of doubt or for other reasons that the editors and collaborators will discuss
            you want to keep the double record. In this case you can always use a <gi>relation</gi>
               with <att>name</att> <code>skos:exactMatch</code>,  <code>skos:broadMatch</code> 
               or <code>skos:closeMatch</code>. It will be even more useful than usual to give a <gi>desc</gi>
               in your <gi>relation</gi>. No redirect will be produced in this case when one of the two is requested, 
               the relations will be visualized, and in case of <code>skos:exactMatch</code> this will be with the header.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="level1">
            <head>Delete</head>
            <p>If you make a mistake, or find a doublet 
               which needs to be cleaned up, or need 
               to <ref target="definitionWorks">reorganize Textual Units</ref> by making one formerly independent 
               part of another, you will delete a record. 
            Doing so as you do normally, with a commit to the 
            public repositories in GitHub, 
            will add a value to a list of deleted records and if a 
               <gi>relation</gi> with <att>name</att> 
               <code>betmas:formerlyAlsoListedAs</code> 
               is present in another record of which
            the deleted one was a double, then requesting 
            the deleted item will redirect to that record.
            </p>
         </div>
        </body>
        </text>
        </TEI>
