<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/guidelines/master/schema/out/tei-betamesaheftGL.rng" 
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/guidelines/master/schema/out/tei-betamesaheftGL.rng" 
type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Definition of Works, Textparts and Narrative Units</title>
            <author>Pietro Liuzzo</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
          </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Produced by pandoc. Conversion from GIT flavoured markdown to TEI simple.</p>
            <p>transformed to TEI documentation with XSLT by Pietro Liuzzo</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body xml:id="definitionWorks">
         <div type="level1">
            <head>Definition of works and Assignment of IDs</head>
         
            <p>We consider a <hi rendition="simple:bold">work</hi> any text with an
independent circulation. This does not mean it has to be alone in a
manuscript. A text which sometimes is added to another is also an
independent work. So <hi rendition="simple:italic">Genesis</hi> is a
work as <hi rendition="simple:italic">Pentateuch</hi> is a work which
contains it. But <hi rendition="simple:italic">Chapter 1 of Genesis</hi>
is not a work, it is a part of the work
<hi rendition="simple:italic">Genesis</hi>.</p>
            <p>Works should not be confused with  <ref target="narrativeUnits">Narrative Units</ref>. To
               decide whether the text you are dealing with is a work or a
               narrative unit, consider  Orlandi 2010, <hi rendition="simple:italic">A
                  Terminology for the identification of Coptic Literary Documents</hi>.
               A work "only refers to fixed contents and a precise
               sequence", see
               <ref target="https://www.zotero.org/groups/ethiostudies/items/itemKey/NWT4X3K9/q/corpus-organizers">Bausi
                  2010, 34 n3</ref>
               </p>
            
          <p>Works, textparts and Narrative Units:</p>
            
         <list type="unordered">
            <item>
               <p>Texts with independent circulation get an individual record with a first-level ID (such as LIT1931Mashaf), all
    other are textparts. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>If a text is at the same time part of another text and circulates independently, it gets
                  an independent first-level ID/record.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>For these texts (both circulating independently and part of another work), a <gi>div</gi> should also be created, with a
                  <att>corresp</att> giving the individual ID, in order to show the full content of a collection in
                  correct order.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>If a textpart has an individual circulation in other traditions, but not in the Ethiopian tradition,
    all information on this text should be given in the <gi>div</gi>: multiple titles can be
    inserted, with bibliography linking to the IDs of these titles,
    relations for the authors of the titles, etc.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>For text portions (paragraphs, chapters, miracles, etc.) which are extant as different versions in multiple recensions of the same work or even in different works, 
                  create a <ref target="narrativeUnits">Narrative Unit</ref>.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>The existing records inherited from the EAe index that do not
    have an independent circulation in Ethiopic should be deleted.</p>
            </item>
         </list>
            
         <p>See as example
            <ref target="LIT1931Mashaf" type="bm">LIT1931Mashaf</ref>.
         </p>
            
         <p>Often the first problem to face is which records and how many to
make. We accept as a principle to create <hi rendition="simple:bold">the
maximum number of record as it is sensible</hi> and to state
<hi rendition="simple:bold">the minimum number of relations needed among
them</hi> with a view on expanding them potentially to all what is not
essential, in order to clarify their relation with each other. It might
happen that different researchers have different opinions on the
relation between the versions and the manuscripts and in this we will be
able to host them all.</p>
            
         <p>For example. If the Work A has four versions 1, 2, 3 and 4, 1 being a
short version of 2 and 3 a later version of 4 while 2 and 4 differ from
one another only in the order in which the content is organized, there
will be 5 records, one for the abstract work, one for each version.
While the abstract work will point to each of the 4 version with
relations and might contain a general description of the work, each of
the version will have clearly defined relations with the others and the
abstract Work.</p>
            
         <p>A further example: a text which is made of parts which can occur in
different orders within different manuscripts. This will have 1 Work
record, describing the ideal or majoritarian, or standard sequence,
while each witness (Manuscript) will contain the specific order of the
parts in it.</p>
            
         <p>Create a new record for every different version, recensions, etc. and
then express the diverse relations between the records with relation
elements. This should be clearer and leave space for more differing
opinions than to try to express the relations within one single
record.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
