<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/guidelines/master/schema/out/tei-betamesaheftGL.rng"
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/guidelines/master/schema/out/tei-betamesaheftGL.rng"
type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Documentary Texts</title>
                <author>Pietro Liuzzo</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Encoded in XML</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
          <change who="PL" when="2018-07-20">first version of guidelines from Wiki</change>
            <change who="PL" when="2019-02-28">updated with examples</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body xml:id="Documents">
    <head>Documentary texts</head>
<p>Texts which are not <ref target="definitionWorks">textual units</ref>
occur often in manuscripts as <ref target="additionsVaria">additions</ref>.
That is why the list of types for these texts is in the
<ref target="http://betamasaheft.eu/authority-files/list">Taxonomy</ref> under 'Additions'.</p>
            <p>Please, make sure you encode these texts correctly according to their actual
  status in the manuscript.</p>
<p>If you want to provide an ID for a given text of this type, you can do
  so and create a Work record for it, where the same keywords used in <tag>desc type</tag>
  are added as keywords to the record.
</p>
<p>You need not by any means to always assign an ID to each of these texts, they
  already have one within the manuscript they belong to, which is unique and
  precise enough and you can reference anywhere.</p>
<p>You might find more appropriate to associate a document to
  a <ref target="narratives">narrative unit</ref>,
if the formalization is such, using a <gi>title</gi> as discussed also in
 the page about <ref target="additionsVaria">additions</ref>. The following example is from
<ref type="BM" target="BMLor70">Florence, Biblioteca Medicea Laurenziana, BML Or. 70</ref>
</p>
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
  <list>
    <item xml:id="a1">
        <locus target="#201v #203 #204" facs="211"/>
        <desc  type="GuestText"><title ref="NAR0015ListForSingleFeasts"/></desc>
    </item>
    <item xml:id="a2">
        <locus target="#204r" facs="214"/>
        <desc><title ref="NAR0006monast"/> Rules on the relationship of the monks to the monastery when they leave.</desc>
    </item>
  </list>
</egXML>
<p>You do not have to always give a value to <att>type</att> in <gi>desc</gi>, neither
you have to give a <gi>title</gi>, this depends on what is
known and you wish to encode.</p>
<p>There will be cases when it is only worth adding a value to <att>type</att> in <gi>desc</gi>,
cases in which
an association to a Narrative Unit is all that can be done, and cases in which the two
might be very similar.</p>
<p>While the value of <att>type</att> in <gi>desc</gi> is only providing a useful
grouping keyword from the taxonomy,
the identification with a Textual Unit or Narrative Unit specifies that the current text is an <!--what?--></p>
<p>In the same way in which a document in a quaternary stratum
   can be associated with a Narrative Unit, a quaternary stratum content
  which can be identified with a stable content
  can be referenced in this same way,
  like in <ref type="BM" target="BLorient481">London, British Library, BL Orient 481</ref></p>
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
  <item xml:id="a15">
    <locus target="#92r"/>
      <desc type="Letter">A <title ref="LIT2665SD">letter</title>...
      ...</desc>
  </item>
</egXML>
<p>Here you will notice also how assigning a value to <att>type</att> in <gi>desc</gi>
is different from identifying it with a Textual or Narrative Unit</p>
<p>If a document is the main content of a manuscript,
  it can be encoded in the same way as other main contents in <gi>msContents</gi>. If it
  is not an identifiable Textual Unit,
it might also be assigned a <ref target="narrativeUnits">Narrative Unit</ref> identifier in the same way.</p>
<p>For meaningful groups of documents you can also use the document <ref target="corpora">corpus</ref> grouping</p>
<p>In case your text is in an <gi>additions</gi> <gi>item</gi> and it is composed of different sections,
you can use <gi>seg</gi> with <att>ana</att> as specified in the above page.</p>
<div></div>

        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
