<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/guidelines/master/schema/out/tei-betamesaheftGL.rng" 
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/guidelines/master/schema/out/tei-betamesaheftGL.rng" 
type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Editing these Guidelines</title>
                <author>Pietro Liuzzo</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Encoded in TEI.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body xml:id="editingGuidelines">
            <head>Editing these Guidelines</head>
            <div type="level3">
                <head>How it works</head>
                <p>These guidelines are fed by a Github webhook pushing into the web application at
                        <ref target="Guidelines" type="bm">http://betamasaheft.eu/Guidelines/</ref>
                    data from the<ref target="https://github.com/BetaMasaheft/guidelines">
                        guidelines repository</ref>, the <ref
                        target="https://github.com/BetaMasaheft/guidelines">Beta maṣāḥǝft schema
                        repository</ref> and the <ref target="https://github.com/BetaMasaheft/RDF"
                        >Beta maṣāḥǝft ontology (this is not via webhook)</ref>.</p>
                <p>If you edit and push (or make a PR) to the above repos, the XML files will be
                    sent to the application and go live so that you can see them, search, browse,
                    read, etc.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="level3">
                <head>Editing the TEI</head>
                <p>You can use any editor you like to edit the XML files. We are going to deal here
                    only with the guidelines files, not with the editing of the schema.</p>
                <p>There is indeed a Beta maṣāḥǝft Guidelines Schema which validates the files you
                    are pushing to the app and will notify you if anything goes wrong. Actually,
                    there are processing instructions in every single file that should allow your
                    editor to validate your XML BEFORE you push it to the repo. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="level3">
                <head>Principles</head>
                <p>In principle, given that the information is displayed together, what is already
                    specified in the schema should not need further clarification, so, e.g. there is
                    no need to repeat a list of values for an attribute if this is in the
                    schema.</p>
                <p>There are Pages, Table of Contents and Elements beside the schema folder (which
                    is the Beta maṣāḥǝft Guidelines Schema). </p>
                <list>
                    <item>Pages are descriptive pieces like this one, trying to explain how to
                        encode something.</item>
                    <item>Table of Contents (toc) are simply lists, organizing pages in meaningful
                        ways based on type of user, kind of task, etc.</item>
                    <item>Elements describe one element, will fetch from the schema any
                        specification further to those in TEI and link back to pages mentioning
                        it.</item>
                </list>

            </div>
            <div type="level3">
                <head>Documentation Tags</head>
                <p>We use the <ref
                        target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/de/html/TD.html#TDphrase"
                        >TEI Documentation Elements</ref>.</p>
                <p>The application will use the <att>xml:id</att> in <gi>body</gi> to identify the
                    pages and elements, so, please take care not to duplicate this if you are
                    creating a new page. The application will use the <gi>title</gi> inside
                        <gi>titleStmt</gi> as a label for that resource. This means that you can
                    have a page and an element called "person" but these will need to different
                        <att>xml:id</att> in <gi>body</gi></p>
                <p>We use <gi>div</gi> elements to structure the contents. These should have <list>
                        <item>A <att>type</att> with <val>level2</val> where the digit is a number
                            from 2 to whatever the deepness of sections required is. </item>
                        <item> A child <gi>head</gi> with the title of the subsection.</item>
                    </list></p>
                <p>You can use <gi>table</gi> and <gi>list</gi> and their children as specified in
                    TEI.</p>
                <p><gi>ref</gi> is used with <att>target</att>. The app will do some job for you in
                    this case: <list>
                        <item>You can enter in <att>target</att> simply the ID of any of the pages
                            in the guidelines.</item>
                        <item>You can add a <att>type</att> with <val>bm</val> and your
                                <att>target</att> can simply be the ID of any of the entities in
                            Beta maṣāḥǝft. This is useful to link to examples.</item>
                        <item>If you enter a URL, this will become an external link.</item>
                    </list></p>
                <p>Please always use <gi>gi</gi>, <gi>tag</gi>, <gi>att</gi> and <gi>val</gi> to
                    mark up respectively element names, tags, attributes names and values. You do
                    not need to type angle brackets and escape them or to add @ in front of every
                    attribute, this will be done during the visualization. For elements a link will
                    also be given to the page for that element.</p>
                <p>To add examples of XML markup, use the <gi>egXML</gi> element, always with its
                    namespace so, <tag>egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"</tag>. This
                    allows the validation to skip the contents (i.e. do not add again the TEI
                    namespace in the examples).</p>
                <p>You can use <gi>cit</gi> and <gi>quote</gi> for quotations.</p>
                <p>If you really want to make something bold or italics use <tag>hi
                        rendition="simple:bold"</tag> and <tag>hi
                    rendition="simple:italic"</tag></p>
                <p>In a Table of contents file, please only use <gi>list</gi> and enter as content of the <gi>item</gi>s only the id of the page you want the ToC to point to.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
