<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/guidelines/master/schema/out/tei-betamesaheftGL.rng" 
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/guidelines/master/schema/out/tei-betamesaheftGL.rng" 
type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>from template</title>
            <author>Pietro Liuzzo</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Produced by pandoc. Conversion from GIT flavoured markdown to TEI simple.</p>
            <p>transformed to TEI documentation with XSLT by Pietro Liuzzo</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body xml:id="from-template">
         <head>from template</head>
         <p>Cataloguers may use one of the
    <ref target="https://github.com/BetaMasaheft/schema">annotated
    templates</ref> to create new data. ### in the preview app You shall
    now find a new "create new entity" function in the list
    view of the app. You only need to enter the name of the file, for
    manuscripts this is the full filename, for the other entities just
    the last part of the id . For LIT1234iliad, you would enter only
    "iliad". For a manuscript, simply enter the full name, the
    small print will indicate you what is needed. As you start typing
    the button will become active and you can create the file. This is
    stored in the app, not in git! As the confirmation page tells you,
    you need to 1. download the file 2. save it in a folder called
    "new" into the proper folder 3. commit and sync to git</p>
         <p>Once you have done this git and our server will be again in sync,
    which means you can now move your file if you need to (especially
    for manuscripts) and then commit and sync this change again. If you
    omit the first step, we will have two identical files in two
    locations and thus the id lookup of the app will fail not showing
    you your file. On leaving the page you will get a warning every
    time, intended to make you stop before you carry on without syncing.
    The generated file will have a consistent new id and will insert it
    in the appropriate place in the file. This should avoid the really
    frequent problem of ids not being updated after copy-pasting a
    master file. it remains entirely possible to create your files in
    oXygen as previously, but this method is recommended as it makes
    sure your id is unique. The file will also have the correct type and
    a change element with your initials and current date, nothing
    else.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
