<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/guidelines/master/schema/out/tei-betamesaheftGL.rng"
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/guidelines/master/schema/out/tei-betamesaheftGL.rng"
type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letters</title>
            <author>Pietro Liuzzo</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Produced by pandoc. Conversion from GIT flavoured markdown to TEI simple.</p>
            <p>transformed to TEI documentation with XSLT by Pietro Liuzzo</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>       <revisionDesc>       <change who="PL" when="2018-10-26">Created page</change>     </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body xml:id="letters">
          <div>
            <p>
              Encoding letters on parchment or paper or whatever,
              written in ink or typed with a machine follows the same guidelines available
              for other <ref target="manuscripts">manuscripts</ref>.
              It is suggested that the keyword Letter is used to mark these record as well
              as those which contain letters as part of the
              <ref target="manuscriptContents">main or secondary contents</ref>.

<ref type="bm" target="IVEf921">Saint Petersburg, Institut Vostočnyh Rukopisej Rossijskoj Akademii Nauk, IV Ef.92.1</ref> is an example of such a letter being recorded in the database.
  Another case is a letter which is copied into a manuscript, which has no independent support, and is thus a secondary or main content according to the criteria to decide on that.
  In this case, the criteria for contents apply,
  and you might or not want to create a work record.
  If you do so, then give to that work record the keyword <q>Letter</q> to facilitate retrieval.
</p><p>
  There might be cases where you need to split a work and a manuscript record,
  if, for example, a letter of which we do have the original is mentioned
  somewhere for its text and a work record has been created for it to point it.
  This is fine, and if and when we might end up having a record for the actual
  manuscript letter then we will have it and point to the work record as usual.
  If, for example, one of these letters is mentioned in a manuscript (another of the same letters?)
  and you want to refer to it, then you could do that directly to the manuscript record,
  with no need to create a work record.
</p>
<p>
  This has NOTHING to do with Letters as a literary genre.
</p>
<p>The transcription of the letter can be done following the normal

              <ref target="text-encoding">Text encoding</ref>
              Guidelines.
            </p>
      </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
