<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/guidelines/master/schema/out/tei-betamesaheftGL.rng"
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/guidelines/master/schema/out/tei-betamesaheftGL.rng"
type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Manuscripts</title>
            <author>Pietro Liuzzo</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Produced by pandoc. Conversion from GIT flavoured markdown to TEI simple.</p>
            <p>transformed to TEI documentation with XSLT by Pietro Liuzzo</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="PL" when="2018-04-30">first version of guidelines from Wiki</change>
         <change who="DR" when="2018-12-07">Updated issue link, added link to TEI
            guidelines</change>
         <change who="DR" when="2019-04-09">Added before creating a manuscript record
            paragraph</change>
         <change who="NV" when="2024-12-13">added a paragraph about "Differenciating between various
            levels of description"</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body xml:id="manuscripts">
         <p>Any manuscripts referenced in our records should have at least a minimal record. To
            create such a minimal record for referencing use the form to <ref target="newEntry"
               >create new items</ref> in the Beta maṣāḥǝft website.</p>

         <div type="level2">
            <head>Before creating a manuscript record</head>
            <p>Before creating a manuscript record, as for all entities, it is important to check
               whether it already exists! It is better not to check only the repository folder in
               which you would expect it in GitHub, but to <ref
                  target="https://betamasaheft.eu/as.html">search</ref> for the manuscript's
               shelfmark or other identifiers on the app as well. Remember that particularly records
               for EMML and EMIP manuscripts might have already been created within their actual
               repository and vice versa.</p>
         </div>


         <div type="level2">
            <head>Manuscript Structure: Use of <gi>msDesc</gi>, <gi>msPart</gi> and
               <gi>msFrag</gi></head>
            <p>Reading of the <ref
                  target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/MS.html">TEI
                  guidelines for manuscript description</ref> is highly recommended. Regarding the
               structure of simple and composite manuscripts, they also state in <ref
                  target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/MS.html#mspt"
                  >Manuscript Parts</ref>
               <cit>
                  <quote>Since each component of such a composite manuscript will in all likelihood
                     have its content, physical description, history, and so on, the structure of
                     msPart is in the main identical to that of msDesc, allowing one to retain the
                     top level of identity (msIdentifier), but to branch out thereafter into as many
                     parts, or even subparts, as necessary.</quote>
               </cit></p>
            <p>This means that for manuscripts made of only one part we will use only
                  <gi>msDesc</gi>, but in any case, where a structure in codicological units occurs,
               we will use <gi>msPart</gi>. <gi>msPart</gi> can contain other <gi>msPart</gi>s.
                  <gi>msFrag</gi> can be used when there are at least two parts of one manuscript
               kept in different repositories and our schema this is allowed also beside
                  <gi>msPart</gi> for special cases like <ref target="BNFet45" type="bm"
                  >BNFet45</ref>.</p>
            <p>As for <ref target="https://github.com/BetaMasaheft/Documentation/issues/368">issue
                  368</ref> we have decided to use <gi>msFrag</gi> and <gi>msPart</gi> as follows in
               cases where leaves or quires have been moved. The Ms containing currently the unit
               will have a <gi>msPart</gi> with it, with an appropriate description and pointer to
               the manuscript where the unit comes from. The Ms which has lost a unit will instead
               have a <gi>msFrag</gi> pointing to the Ms where the unit is now. Please, do not
               confuse this with cases where leaves or quires are lost.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="level2">
            <head>Double records</head>
            <p>It can be that you find out the same manuscript is present under 2 identifiers.</p>
            <p>You can fix this by merging the two records in one and deleting the one with less
               information. Remember when doing this to check for references to the id which will go
               missing, and update them to point to the other identifier.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="level2">
            <head>Differenciating between various levels of description</head>
            <p>To mark a rudimentary description as "stub" (if the cataloguer wants others consider
               it as "stub"), one needs to write the word "stub" anywhere in the change history.
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <revisionDesc>
                     <change who="ES" when="2024-04-10">created stub</change>
                  </revisionDesc></egXML> When the record has stopped being a stub as it has been
               developed further then in the first change line the word stub must replaced with
               something like "initial version" or anything else. After the description is
               completed, the above example can be changed into something like the example below.
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <revisionDesc>
                     <change who="ES" when="2024-04-10">created an initial version</change>
                     <change who="NV" when="2024-12-13">completed the description, change the first
                        line above</change>
                  </revisionDesc>
               </egXML>
            </p>
            <p> In cases of enriching a historical catalogue description, such as verifying images
               or adding new information, one can acknowledge this using <ptr target="bm:BmWebsite"
               />, see the respective paragraph in <ref target="bibliographic-references"
                  >Bibliographic References</ref></p>
         </div>
         <div type="level2">
            <head>Manuscript Encoding: Overview</head>
            <list>
               <item><ref target="structure">General structure of the Manuscript record</ref></item>
               <item><ref target="identifiersStructure">Structure of the Identifiers in a Manuscript
                     record</ref></item>
               <item><ref target="manuscriptDescription">Description of the Manuscript</ref></item>
               <item><ref target="text-encoding">Text encoding</ref></item>
               <item><ref target="references">References</ref></item>
               <item><ref target="syntaxe">Stratigraphic description (La Syntaxe du
                  Codex)</ref></item>
               <item><ref target="images">Images</ref></item>
            </list>
            <p>Some more specific types of written artefacts, </p>
            <list>
               <item><ref target="inscriptions">Inscriptions</ref></item>
               <item><ref target="scrolls">Scrolls</ref></item>
               <item><ref target="letters">Letters</ref></item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
