<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/guidelines/master/schema/out/tei-betamesaheftGL.rng"
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/guidelines/master/schema/out/tei-betamesaheftGL.rng"
type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Manuscripts</title>
            <author>Pietro Liuzzo</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Produced by pandoc. Conversion from GIT flavoured markdown to TEI simple.</p>
            <p>transformed to TEI documentation with XSLT by Pietro Liuzzo</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="PL" when="2018-04-30">first version of guidelines from Wiki</change>
         <change who="DR" when="2018-12-07">Updated issue link, added link to TEI
            guidelines</change>
         <change who="DR" when="2019-04-09">Added before creating a manuscript record
            paragraph</change>
         <change who="NV" when="2024-12-13">added a paragraph about "Differentiating between various
            levels of description"; introduced English corrections suggested by ChatGPT.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body xml:id="manuscripts">
         <p>Any manuscripts referenced in our records should have at least a minimal record. To create such a minimal record for referencing, use the form to <ref target="newEntry">create new items</ref> on the Beta maṣāḥǝft website.</p>
         
         <div type="level2">
            <head>Before Creating a Manuscript Record</head>
            <p>Before creating a manuscript record, as with all entities, it is important to check whether it already exists! Avoid relying solely on the repository folder in GitHub where you expect it to be; instead, <ref target="https://betamasaheft.eu/as.html">search</ref> for the manuscript's shelfmark or other identifiers on the app. Remember that records for EMML and EMIP manuscripts may already exist in their respective repositories or vice versa.</p>
         </div>
         
         <div type="level2">
            <head>Manuscript Structure: Use of <gi>msDesc</gi>, <gi>msPart</gi>, and <gi>msFrag</gi></head>
            <p>It is highly recommended to consult the <ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/MS.html">TEI guidelines for manuscript description</ref>. Regarding the structure of simple and composite manuscripts, the guidelines state in <ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/MS.html#mspt">Manuscript Parts</ref>:
               <cit>
                  <quote>Since each component of such a composite manuscript will in all likelihood
                     have its content, physical description, history, and so on, the structure of
                     msPart is in the main identical to that of msDesc, allowing one to retain the
                     top level of identity (msIdentifier), but to branch out thereafter into as many
                     parts, or even subparts, as necessary.</quote></cit>
            </p>
            <p>For manuscripts consisting of only one part, we use <gi>msDesc</gi> exclusively. However, when a structure with codicological units occurs, we use <gi>msPart</gi>. Note that <gi>msPart</gi> can contain other <gi>msPart</gi>s. The <gi>msFrag</gi> element is used when parts of a manuscript are kept in different repositories. In our schema, <gi>msFrag</gi> can also be used alongside <gi>msPart</gi> for special cases, such as <ref target="BNFet45" type="bm">BNFet45</ref>.</p>
            <p>As per <ref target="https://github.com/BetaMasaheft/Documentation/issues/368">issue 368</ref>, the following approach is adopted for cases where leaves or quires have been moved. The manuscript currently containing the unit will have a <gi>msPart</gi> with a description and a pointer to the manuscript where the unit originated. The manuscript that has lost the unit will instead have a <gi>msFrag</gi> pointing to the manuscript where the unit is now located. Please do not confuse this with cases where leaves or quires are lost.</p>
         </div>
         
         <div type="level2">
            <head>Double Records</head>
            <p>In some cases, you may find that the same manuscript is present under two identifiers.</p>
            <p>This can be resolved by merging the two records into one and deleting the record with less information. When doing so, ensure that any references to the deleted identifier are updated to point to the retained identifier.</p>
         </div>
         
         <div type="level2">
            <head>Differentiating Between Various Levels of Description</head>
            <p>To mark a rudimentary description as a "stub" (indicating that the cataloguer wants others to consider it as such), include the word "stub" in the change history:
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <revisionDesc>
                     <change who="ES" when="2024-04-10">Created stub.</change>
                  </revisionDesc>
               </egXML>
               Once the record has been developed further, the word "stub" anywhere in the <gi>change</gi> element under <gi>revisionDesc</gi> should be replaced:
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <revisionDesc>
                     <change who="ES" when="2024-04-10">Created an initial version.</change>
                     <change who="NV" when="2024-12-13">Completed the description.</change>
                  </revisionDesc>
               </egXML>
            </p>
            <p>When enriching a historical catalogue description, such as verifying images or adding new information, this can be acknowledged using <ptr target="bm:BmWebsite" />, as outlined in the paragraph on <ref target="bibliographic-references">Bibliographic References</ref>.</p>
         </div>
         
         <div type="level2">
            <head>Manuscript Encoding: Overview</head>
            <list>
               <item><ref target="structure">General structure of the Manuscript record</ref></item>
               <item><ref target="identifiersStructure">Structure of the Identifiers in a Manuscript record</ref></item>
               <item><ref target="manuscriptDescription">Description of the Manuscript</ref></item>
               <item><ref target="text-encoding">Text encoding</ref></item>
               <item><ref target="references">References</ref></item>
               <item><ref target="syntaxe">Stratigraphic description (La Syntaxe du Codex)</ref></item>
               <item><ref target="images">Images</ref></item>
            </list>
            <p>Specific types of written artefacts include:</p>
            <list>
               <item><ref target="inscriptions">Inscriptions</ref></item>
               <item><ref target="scrolls">Scrolls</ref></item>
               <item><ref target="letters">Letters</ref></item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
