<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/guidelines/master/schema/out/tei-betamesaheftGL.rng"
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/guidelines/master/schema/out/tei-betamesaheftGL.rng"
type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Narrative Units</title>
                <author>Pietro Liuzzo</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Produced by pandoc. Conversion from GIT flavoured markdown to TEI simple.</p>
                <p>transformed to TEI documentation with XSLT by Pietro Liuzzo</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
        <change who="PL" when="2018-04-30">first version of guidelines from Wiki</change>
        <change who="PL" when="2019-02-28">added links, split in three parts to define most common uses of the Narrative Unit</change>
      </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body xml:id="narrativeUnits">
            <div type="level1">
    <head>Narrative Units</head>
                <p>The model file for a <ref target="definitionWorks">Narrative Unit</ref> is much
                  simpler than a <ref target="works">work file</ref>. Just assign a
        title to your file and add in the <gi>body</gi> a short
        description. You can mark up content as in any other entity.
        Recommended but not compulsory are a bibliography and a
        <gi>listRelation</gi>.</p>
        <p>A narrative unit can be pointed to in any place where you can point to a <ref target="definitionWorks">Textual Unit</ref>.
          The following are some examples of the main types of use</p>
        <div type="level2">
          <head>Narrative Units in the main content</head>
          <p>
            In the following example from
            <ref type="BM" target="BLadd16217">London, British Library, BL Add. 16,217</ref>
            a main content of the manuscript could not be identified with a Textual Unit. It has been associted with a Narrative Unit
          instead.
          </p>
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <msItem xml:id="ms_i3">
              <locus from="19" to="21"/>
              <title ref="NAR0009history" xml:lang="gez">ሐሳበ፡ ዓለም፡</title>
                ...
            </msItem>
          </egXML>
          <p>This is exactly the same which you would do for a Textual Unit (see page on <ref target="manuscriptContents">manuscript contents</ref>).</p>
          </div>
          <div type="level2">
            <head>Narrative Units in quaternary strata</head>
            <p>
              <ref target="documents">The page about documents</ref>
              gives some examples of how to use Narrative Units and Textual Units to identify a content.
              This will happen basically in the same way as in the above example, with a <gi>title</gi> element.
            </p>
            </div>
        <div type="level2">
          <head>Narrative Units to associate different parts of a text</head>
    <p>Narrative units can also be created for text portions (paragraphs,
        chapters, miracles, etc.) which are extant as different versions in
        multiple recensions of the same work or even in different works.
        Creating these narrative units allows displaying in the app all the
        existing interrelated versions of that text. See, e.g.,
        <ref target="NAR0013pelican" type="bm">NAR0013pelican</ref>, i.e.,
        the chapter on the pelican in the different versions (see <ref target="work-teiHeader">section Versions in the page about work description</ref>) of the
        <ref target="LIT1401Physio" type="BM">Physiologus</ref>.
        Once a single narrative unit ID is provided as
        <gi>div</gi> with <att>corresp</att> in correspondence of the text
        edition in the Work records of the different recensions (e.g.,
        <tag>div type="textpart" subtype="chapter"
          xml:id="ch4" n="4"  corresp="NAR0013pelican"</tag>),
        all the existing versions of that narrative unit will be visualized in
        the app by clicking the Versions button in the Text page of the work
        record.</p>
        </div>
</div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
