<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/guidelines/master/schema/out/tei-betamesaheftGL.rng" 
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/guidelines/master/schema/out/tei-betamesaheftGL.rng" 
type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Narrative Units</title>
                <author>Pietro Liuzzo</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Produced by pandoc. Conversion from GIT flavoured markdown to TEI simple.</p>
                <p>transformed to TEI documentation with XSLT by Pietro Liuzzo</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body xml:id="narrativeUnits">
            <div type="level1">
    <head>Narrative Units</head>
                <p>The model file for a Narrative Unit is much simpler then a <ref target="works">work file</ref>. Just assign a
        title to your file and add in the <gi>body</gi> a short
        description. You can mark up content as in any other entity.
        Recommended but not compulsory are a bibliography and a
        <tag>listRelation</tag>.</p>
    <p>Narrative units can also be created for text portions (paragraphs,
        chapters, miracles, etc.) which are extant as different versions in
        multiple recensions of the same work or even in different works.
        Creating these narrative units allows displaying in the app all the
        existing interrelated versions of that text. See, e.g.,
        <ref target="NAR0013pelican" type="bm">NAR0013pelican</ref>, i.e., the chapter on the pelican in the Physiologus.
        Once a single narrative unit ID is provided as
        <gi>div</gi> with <att>corresp</att> in correspondence of the text
        edition in the Work records of the different recensions (e.g.,
        <tag>div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" xml:id="ch4" n="4"  corresp="NAR0013pelican"</tag>),
        all the existing versions of that narrative unit will be visualized in
        the app by clicking the Versions button in the Text page of the work
        record.</p>
</div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>