<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/guidelines/master/schema/out/tei-betamesaheftGL.rng"
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/guidelines/master/schema/out/tei-betamesaheftGL.rng"
type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Person</title>
            <author>Pietro Liuzzo</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
          </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Produced by pandoc. Conversion from GIT flavoured markdown to TEI simple.</p>
            <p>transformed to TEI documentation with XSLT by Pietro Liuzzo</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>       <revisionDesc>       <change who="PL" when="2018-04-30">first version of guidelines from Wiki</change>
         <change who="DR" when="2018-05-23">Added title priorities</change>
         <change who="DR" when="2018-07-06">Added use of floruit</change>
         <change who="DR" when="2019-03-20">Split groups, added information on person types</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body xml:id="persons">
         <p>This page contains information about how to encode information about a single individual, including
names, occupation, nationality, birth, death, residence, etc.</p>
         <p>It can be expanded with much more information, following TEI
guidelines for
<ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/de/html/ref-person.html">
               person
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>For the encoding of groups of persons see, <ref target="groups">groups</ref>.</p>
         <p>The elements of a person's record constitute in their entirety a brief biographical sketch of the record's subject. It is therefore not necessary to
         limit the description of the person's life to a single element. Instead, all information should be encoded at the appropriate place in the record,
         for example, <gi>birth</gi>, <gi>death</gi> or <gi>floruit</gi>.</p>
         <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<text>
      <body>
         <listPerson>
            <person sex="1">
               <persName xml:lang="gez" xml:id="n1">አበከራዙን</persName>
               <persName xml:lang="gez" type="normalized" corresp="#n1">ʾAbakarazun</persName>
               <persName type="alt"><roleName type="title">ʾabbā</roleName> ʾAbakǝrazun</persName>
               <nationality>Christian Ethiopia</nationality>
               <faith>EOTC</faith>

               <occupation type="ecclesiastic">monk</occupation>
               <death>1471</death>
               <floruit notBefore="1390" notAfter="1471">1390-1471</floruit>
               <residence>
                  <placeName ref="LOC2331DabraQ">Dabra Qaʿat</placeName>
               </residence>
            </person>

         <listRelation>
               <relation name="bm:fatherOf" active="PRS1009Abakaraz" passive="PRS1000Abakaraz PRS1020Abakaraz"/>
               <relation name="bm:husbandOf" active="PRS1009Abakaraz" passive="PRS1030Abakaraz">
                    <desc>It is always a nice idea to provide a description of this relations with a sentence or two.
                   </desc>
            </relation>
</listRelation>

         </listPerson>


      </body>
   </text>
</egXML>

<p>Within <gi>birth</gi> you can use other elements, for example <gi>placeName</gi> for a place of birth.</p>
         <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <birth when="1419">
               He was born at
               <placeName ref="LOC6569Tegray">Tǝgrāy</placeName>
               in <date>1419</date>.
            </birth>
         </egXML>

         <div type="level1">
            <head>Names and roles</head>

            <div type="level2">
               <head>Encoding of personal names</head>

               <p>We usually assign <val>n1</val> to the standard name in Fidal and point with <att>corresp</att> to that for transliteration and translations of the same.</p>
               <p>Other <gi>persName</gi>s will have other IDs, which can be anything which is a valid <att>xml:id</att> but better if they are in the format 'n\d+'.</p>
               <p>If you want to add a typical spelling which is used to search a name,
                  like in https://github.com/BetaMasaheft/Documentation/issues/506, the safest place
                  to add it so that it is indexed without affecting the actual content of
                  the entry is in a new teiHeader//titleStmt/title</p>
               <p>You can also use <att>type</att> with value <val>main</val> to further specify what the label name of the person should be.</p>
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <persName xml:id="n1" xml:lang="gez">ማርያም፡</persName>
                  <persName xml:lang="gez" corresp="#n1" type="normalized">Māryām</persName>
                  <persName xml:lang="en" corresp="#n1" type="main">Mary</persName>

               </egXML>
<p>Do not add <att>xml:lang</att> if you do not know the language in which the name is attested, 
   prefer not to say anything instead of defaulting on a possibly untrue value.</p>
               <p>So, any proper name reported in Geez should receive the attribute xml:lang="gez", 
                  though it might be of Arabic, Amharic, Oromo, or whatever origin. Etymology can be discussed in the record.</p>
               <p>
                  This is of course redundant when the <gi>persName</gi> you assign this attribute would be already the one picked by the titles rules, which are in order of
                  priority:
                  <list>
                     <item><tag>persName[@type = 'main']</tag></item>
                     <item><tag>persName[@corresp = '#n1'][@xml:lang = 'gez']</tag></item>
                     <item><tag>persName[@corresp = '#n1'][@xml:lang = 'en'][@type = 'normalized']</tag></item>
                     <item><tag>persName[@corresp = '#n1'][@xml:lang[not(. = 'en')][not(. = 'gez')]]</tag></item>
                     <item><tag>persName[1]</tag></item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Changing the IDs to arrive at a certain visualization is deceptory as in the following example, where </p>
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <person sex="1" sameAs="wd:Q671055">
                     <persName xml:lang="en" xml:id="n1" type="main">Cyprian of Antioch</persName>
                     <persName xml:lang="gez" xml:id="n2">ቆጵርያኖስ፡</persName>
                     <persName xml:lang="gez" corresp="#n2" type="normalized">Qoṗrǝyānos</persName>
                  </person>
               </egXML>

               <p>The correct way to do this is</p>
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <person sex="1" sameAs="wd:Q671055">
                     <persName xml:lang="gez" xml:id="n1">ቆጵርያኖስ፡</persName>
                     <persName xml:lang="gez" corresp="#n1" type="normalized">Qoṗrǝyānos</persName>
                     <persName xml:lang="en" xml:id="n2" type="main">Cyprian of Antioch</persName>
                  </person>
               </egXML>
               <p>which will print in the application 'Cyprian of Antioch' instead of the usual first candidate 'Qoṗrǝyānos', the normalized transcription of the name in Fidal.</p>

               <p>
                  Sometimes it is difficult to distinguish between the birth name and given name.
                  The name given at the time of birth, is encoded as a <gi>persName</gi> with an attribute <att>type</att> with value <val>birth</val>.
                  However, there are exceptions where a person has been forced to change his or her birth name to another name for various reasons.
                  In this case, a new name should be given to a person  with <att>type</att>=<val>given</val>.
                  In our person records some persons  have both a birth name and a given name.
                  Here a typical example is a woman named  <ref target="PRS2170AsterGa" type="bm">Aster Gānnoo</ref>, who was an Oromo pioneer working
                   on the translation of the Bible into Oromo. Her Oromo name,
                  which she had got from her parents, was called ሰልባን፡ but later she changed her name to አስቴር፡. In this case, we mark ሰልባን፡ as birth name whereas አስቴር፡ as a given name.
                  Please note that in cases where the name type is not known for certain, it not necessary to specify it.</p>
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <persName xml:lang="gez" xml:id="n1" type="given">አስቴር፡ ጋኖ፡</persName>
                  <persName xml:lang="gez" corresp="#n1" type="normalized">ʾAster Gānnoo</persName>
                  <persName xml:lang="gez" xml:id="n2" type="given">አስቴር፡ ገኖ፡</persName>
                  <persName xml:lang="gez" corresp="#n2" type="normalized">ʾAster Gano</persName>
                  <persName xml:lang="gez" xml:id="n3" type="birth">ሰልባን፡ ጋኖ፡</persName>
                  <persName xml:lang="gez" corresp="#n3" type="normalized">Salbāān Gānnoo</persName>

               </egXML>

            </div>

         <div type="level2">
            <head>Surname and Forename</head>
            <p>Use <gi>surname</gi> and <gi>forename</gi> only for European names. For other names,
  you can use <gi>addName</gi>
               <gi>genName</gi> (e.g. for the ordinal in the name of a
  king) or simply <gi>name</gi>. To
  <gi>persName</gi> you can give a
  <att>type</att> </p>
            <p>For international saints and biblical figures, the English name
  should be used. "Saint" as a title should be spelt with a
  capital and can be abbreviated St (without the dot)</p>
         </div>

         <div type="level2">
            <head>Role</head>
            <p>If the name contains a role, please tag it as
  <gi>roleName</gi> and add a <att>type</att>.</p>
  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
    <persName xml:lang="gez" xml:id="n1" type="birth">ሚናስ፡</persName>
    <persName xml:lang="gez" corresp="#n1" type="normalized">Minās</persName>
    <persName><roleName type="title">ʾaṣe</roleName></persName>
  </egXML>
  <p>Also the  encoding in the first example above is correct, although this second method has been preferred.</p>

            <p>Please note that <gi>roleName</gi> always has to be
  encoded within <gi>persName</gi> for indexing and consistency purposes.</p>
         </div>

         <div type="level2">
            <head>Epithet</head>
            <p>Epithets should be recorded as
  <tag>addName type='epithet'</tag> and should have their
  <att>xml:id</att> with a chosen value. Assuming the
  <att>xml:id</att> is, in this case, "SaviourOfTheWorld" ID to be copied
  there will be the like 'PRS5684JesusCh#SaviourOfTheWorld'</p>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<persName xml:lang="gez" xml:id="n1">ኢየሱስ፡ ክርስቶስ፡</persName>
<persName xml:lang="gez" type="normalized" corresp="#n1">ʾIyasus Krǝstos</persName>
<persName xml:lang="gez" type="alt" xml:id="n2">ክርስቶስ፡</persName>
<persName xml:lang="gez" corresp="#n2">Krǝstos</persName>
<persName xml:lang="gez" xml:id="MadhaneAlam"><addName type="epithet">መድኃኔ፡ ዓለም</addName> </persName>
<persName xml:lang="gez" corresp="#MadhaneAlam">Madḫāne ʿĀlam</persName>
</egXML>
         </div>

         <div type="level2">
            <head>Unknown or incomplete names</head>
            <p>If the name of a person is only partly attested in a manuscript,
  the <gi>persName</gi> in the person record
  should only contain the attested part of the name or be normalized. It
  should not be marked-up in any way. Mark up should instead be carried
  out in the text of the manuscript which contains this name. Note that
  it is not necessary to create a record if there is not enough
  information available on the person to ensure the record's
  correctness.</p>
         </div>
         </div>

         <div type="level1">
            <head>Commemoration</head>
            <p>For Saints, you might wish to record the commemoration dates. Please
               follow the following example. Please always include the source for the date (Sǝnkǝssār, Dǝggwā, EAe...).</p>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
               <note type="commemoration"><date type="diesNatalis">5 Maskaram</date></note>
            </egXML>
         </div>

         <div type="level1">
            <head>Further information about the person</head>

            <div type="level2">
               <head>Period of activity</head>
            <p><gi>floruit</gi> contains the date of the major active years of the record's subject. The paragraphical information given in <gi>floruit</gi> does not aim at describing
               the whole life of the person in question but focusses on what they have done in their active years. In this case, for Ethiopian kings (for most of them) 
               we have conventionally known years of reigns which are considered as a period of activity that we should 
               encode <att>from</att> (indicates the starting point of the period) and <att>to</att> (indicates the ending point). And also for metropolitans it would usually encompass the years from
               their appointment to death or replacement. See, for example, <ref target="PRS6229LebnaDe" type="bm">Lǝbna Dǝngǝl</ref>:</p>
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <birth when="1496">1496</birth>
                  <floruit from="1508" to="1540">He sat on Solomonic throne, when he succeeded his father King <persName ref="PRS7481NaodA">Nāʿod</persName> and ruled the kingdom until <date>1540</date>. 
                     During his minority, however, the kingom was effectively governed by a group of leading court figures and nobels among whom his step grand mother, <persName ref="PRS3706eleni"/> was paramount. 
                     Next importance came <persName ref="PRS10077WasanS"><roleName type="title">rās</roleName>Wasan Sagad</persName> and his mother <persName ref="PRS7482NaodMo"/>. 
                     The years before the wars with <persName ref="PRS1522Ahmadb"/> were mostly peaceful for the Christian kingdom, and it was a time of economic and cultural prosperity.
                     Lǝbna Dǝngǝl was defeated by <persName ref="PRS1522Ahmadb"/> forces in the battle of <placeName ref="LOC5667Sember"/>, in <date>1529</date>, which made him fugitive in his own realm.
                     Being chased from <placeName ref="LOC5597Sawa"/> to <placeName ref="LOC2488Damot"/> to <placeName ref="LOC6135Wag"/> to
                     <placeName ref="LOC6568Amhara"/> to <placeName ref="LOC2481Dambey"/> and finally he found a refugee in the 
                     monastery of <placeName ref="LOC2255DabraD"/>, where he died in <date>1540</date>. 
                  </floruit>
                  <death when="1540"></death>
                  
                    </egXML>
               
               <p>However, when we are not sure of the exact date of <gi>floruit</gi>,
                  period of the person's activity, but we have supporting evidence to claim the approximate period of <gi>floruit</gi>,  
                  we should use <att>notBefore</att> (specifies the earliest possible date for the event) and <att>notAfter</att> (specifies the latest possible date for the event). 
                  See, for example, <ref target="PRS1083AbbayHa" type="bm">ʾAbbāy Habta Ṣǝyon</ref>:</p>
                  
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
               <birth when="1869"/>
            <floruit notBefore="1889" notAfter="1914">He was among the last notables of
               <placeName ref="LOC3764Hamase"/>
               to hold the office of <persName ref="PRS1083AbbayHa"><roleName type="title">baḥǝra nagāš</roleName></persName>.
               He was officially promoted by the Italians, he inherited the office from his uncle
               <persName ref="PRS4907Gwerade"/>. The decline of this office lead to the loss of effective executive power, but ʾAbbāy  became the spokesperson and the head
               of the indigenous population of  <placeName ref="LOC1579Asmara"/>, concentrated in its old quarters.
               It seems that thanks to his services the relationships with the
               Italian colonial administration, tense from time to time, stayed harmonious on the whole.</floruit>
            <death when="1914">He died at <placeName ref="LOC1579Asmara"/> in <date>1914</date>. </death>
            </egXML>
            </div>

            <div type="level2">
               <head>Faith</head>
            <p>For <gi>faith</gi>, the values
               for <att>type</att> can be used, considering their definition. If the faith of a person is not known, it is preferable not to encode it.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="level2">
               <head>Occupation</head>
            <p>
               <gi>occupation</gi> can take
  <att>type</att> attribute.</p>
                  <p>You can also use multiple
      <gi>occupation</gi> elements and add <att>from</att> and/or <att>to</att>
       to assign the occupation to a period. The use of
      <tag>occupation type="academic"</tag>
      should be restricted to scholars involved in the study of
      Ethiopian manuscripts. All persons whose records contain
      <tag>occupation type="academic"</tag>
                     are displayed on <ref target="https://betamasaheft.eu/academics.html">this page</ref>.
                  </p>
               <p>Similarly, <tag>occupation type="ruler"</tag> refers specifically to a head of state or government (queen, king, president, prime minister etc.).
                  Therefore,  <tag>occupation type="ruler"</tag> is used for all Ethiopian kings, while <tag>occupation type="political"</tag>
                  refers to persons whose occupation belongs to the category of politics, whether they are rulers
                  (e.g., governor of a province), courtiers or occupy other political posts.
                  <tag>occupation type="political"</tag> therefore also includes the various occupations of civil offices of the Christian kingdom of Ethiopia.
               </p>

               <p>Try to limit the use of
      <gi>occupation</gi> to actual occupations, otherwise use person types keywords.
      If you are unsure about whether some information on a person
      should be added in <gi>occupation</gi>, please open
      a new issue.
      </p>
               </div>

            <div type="level2">
               <head>Person types</head>
               <p>Generic information about types of persons which are not occupations, such as "saint" or "angel" is encoded with keywords.
                  If you would like to add new person type keywords, or are unsure about whether to
                  encode information as a person type keyword or occupation, please open a new issue.</p>

            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term key="angel"/>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</egXML>
            </div>


         </div>
         <div type="level1">
            <head>Wikidata</head>
            <p>Use <att>sameAs</att> inside <gi>person</gi> to declare the authority file. Prefer
  Wikidata if an item is present, otherways use VIAF.</p>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<person sex="1" sameAs="wd:Q302">
<persName xml:lang="gez" xml:id="n1">ኢየሱስ፡ ክርስቶስ፡</persName>
</person>
</egXML>
         </div>
         <div type="level1">
            <head>Dates</head>
            <p>If you want to give extremes of the date also in
  <att>when</att>
               <att>notBefore</att>
               <att>notAfter</att> please follow
  <ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/CO.html#CONADA">TEI
  guidelines for date</ref>. When the date is given as a value and no
  further information is provided, it is not necessary to repeat the
  dating in the content of the element:
  <tag>death when="1636" evidence="internal"</tag>
  is sufficient. However, if the element contains text, the value will
  not be visualized. The date should, therefore, be included explicitly in
  the content as in this example from <ref target="PRS10233Yamana" type="bm">Yamāna Krǝstos</ref>:</p>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
              <floruit when="1605" evidence="internal">
              He was an important military and political figure, who was involved in several episodes related to
              <persName ref="PRS9038Susenyos"/>
              during the latter's years as šǝftā and pretender to the throne. He refused to side with his brother
              <persName ref="PRS9038Susenyos">
              <roleName type="title">ʾaṣe</roleName>
              Susǝnyos
              </persName>
              in a struggle against the young
              <persName ref="PRS10198Yaeqob">
              <roleName type="title">ʾaṣe</roleName>
              Yāʿqob
              </persName>
              in
              <date>1605</date>
              .
              </floruit>
</egXML>
         </div>
         <div type="level1">
            <head>Relationships</head>
            <p>Each relationship should be listed separately in a
  <gi>relation</gi>, even if the same relationship exists
  between this and more than one other entity.
  <att>name</att> contains the name of the relation.
  Allowed values are those in the
  <ref target="http://snap.dighum.kcl.ac.uk/ontology/">SNAP
  Ontology</ref>. you can filter them out in Oxygen typing snap: in the
  value list.</p>
            <p>
               <att>active</att> should contain the <att>xml:id</att> of the
  current person. <att>passive</att> should contain the IDs
  of the related persons, separated by a space</p>
            <p>As usual all elements can take a
  <att>xml:lang</att>.</p>
            <p>The relationship between a work and its subject is expressed in the
  person record:</p>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<relation name="ecrm:P129i_is_subject_of"
active="PRS4585Georgeo"
passive="LIT1455GadlaG"/>
</egXML>
         </div>

      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
