<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/guidelines/master/schema/out/tei-betamesaheftGL.rng"
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/guidelines/master/schema/out/tei-betamesaheftGL.rng"
type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Place or Repository</title>
                <author>Pietro Liuzzo</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Produced by pandoc. Conversion from GIT flavoured markdown to TEI simple.</p>
                <p>transformed to TEI documentation with XSLT by Pietro Liuzzo</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>       <revisionDesc>       <change who="PL" when="2018-04-30">first version of guidelines from Wiki</change> 
        <change who="ES" when="2019-11-26">added example</change></revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body xml:id="placeOrInstitution"><div type="level1">
    <head>Creating a new record or deciding between repository entity and
        place entity</head>
    <p>All Monasteries and Churches in PLACES have also a parallel 
        Repository record in the institutions repo. The two lists have different origins, PLACES comes from
        EA indexes, while the INSTITUTIONS list is an export of the records in
        EthioSPaRe for repositories.</p>
            <p>In principle, all geographical locations should have a PLACE-type record, with co-ordinates and administrative division provided wherever possible, and all repositories (places where manuscripts are preserved) should have a REPOSITORY-type record. 
                In case of "doublets" the records must be disambiguated. </p>
                <p>Please, proceed as follows in case of doubt:</p>
    <list type="ordered:arabic">
        <item>
            <p>if the repository record for the repository you need does not
                exist, create one and assign an ID.</p>
        </item>
        <item>
            <p>leave the place record there, check the already existing
                references to this place. This can be done either with xpath in
                Oxygen or on the website looking at related entities.</p>
        </item>
        <item>
            <p>modify those references that actually point to a repository
                and not to a place, if any.</p>
        </item>
        <item>
            <p>you can link the place and repository by adding a relation of the skos:exactMatch type as e.g. in <ref  type="bm" target="INS0017UM">ʿUra Qirqos</ref>
                <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                <listRelation>
                    <relation name="skos:exactMatch" active="INS0017UM" passive="LOC6063UraMas"/>
                </listRelation>
                </egXML>
            </p>
        </item>
    </list>
            <p>See also <ref target="places">Places</ref> <ref target="institution">Repositories</ref>.</p>
</div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
