<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/guidelines/master/schema/out/tei-betamesaheftGL.rng" 
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/guidelines/master/schema/out/tei-betamesaheftGL.rng" 
type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Place or Institution</title>
                <author>Pietro Liuzzo</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Produced by pandoc. Conversion from GIT flavoured markdown to TEI simple.</p>
                <p>transformed to TEI documentation with XSLT by Pietro Liuzzo</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>       <revisionDesc>       <change who="PL" when="2018-04-30">first version of guidelines from Wiki</change>     </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body xml:id="placeOrInstitution"><div type="level1">
    <head>creating a new record or deciding between institution and
        place</head>
    <p>All Monasteries and Churches in PLACES have also a parallel in
        Institutions. The two lists have different origins, PLACES comes from
        EA indexes, while the INSTITUTIONS list is an export of the records in
        EthioSPaRe for institutions.</p>
    <p>Please, proceed as follows in case of doubt:</p>
    <list type="ordered:arabic">
        <item>
            <p>if the institution record for the institution you need does not
                exist, create one and assign an id.</p>
        </item>
        <item>
            <p>leave the place record there, check the already existing
                references to this place. This can be done either with xpath in
                Oxygen or on the website looking at related entities.</p>
        </item>
        <item>
            <p>modify those references that actually point to an institution
                and not to a place, if any.</p>
        </item>
    </list>
    <p>with regard to automatically creating an institution record for all
        churches and monastries in Places: is it true that all those with no
        exception are also institutions holding manuscripts?</p>
    <p>Please, markup entities referred to in the text of the fields into
        <gi>note</gi> as described in the
        <ref target="guidelines">guidelines</ref> A template with comments for
        a place description is available
        <ref target="https://github.com/BetaMasaheft/schema/blob/master/modelfilePlace.xml">here</ref>
    </p>
    <p>A template with comments for an Institution description is
        available
        <ref target="https://github.com/BetaMasaheft/schema/blob/master/modelfileInstitution.xml">here</ref>
    </p>
</div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>