<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/guidelines/master/schema/out/tei-betamesaheftGL.rng"
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/guidelines/master/schema/out/tei-betamesaheftGL.rng"
type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Place or Repository</title>
                <author>Pietro Liuzzo</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Produced by pandoc. Conversion from GIT flavoured markdown to TEI simple.</p>
                <p>transformed to TEI documentation with XSLT by Pietro Liuzzo</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>       <revisionDesc>       <change who="PL" when="2018-04-30">first version of guidelines from Wiki</change> 
        <change who="ES" when="2019-11-26">added example</change></revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body xml:id="placeOrInstitution"><div type="level1">
    
    
            <p>All geographical locations should have a <ref target="places">PLACE</ref>-type record (prefixed LOC and stored in the Places repository), with co-ordinates and administrative division provided wherever possible.</p>
            <p>At the same time, all repositories (libraries/archives/collections where manuscripts are preserved, including private collections, churches, monasteries, etc.) should have an <ref target="institution">INSTITUTION</ref>-type record (prefixed INS and stored in the Institutions repository).</p>
            <p>If you need to mark up a locality mentioned in a work, or relevant for a manuscript, a person or a place place refer to a record of <ref target="places">PLACE</ref>-type (creating one if necessary).</p>
            <p>If you need to refer to a manuscript repository, in particular to link <gi>repository</gi> within the <gi>msIdentifier</gi> of a manuscript description, please refer to a record of <ref target="institution">INSTITUTION</ref>-type (creating one if necessary).</p>
            <p>If you need to refer to a manuscript repository which is a church or a monastery already present among the Places (either because it has been inherited from the initial list of authority files, or created in another context) but not among the Institutions please proceed as follows :</p>
    <list type="ordered:arabic">
        <item>
            <p>create a new <ref target="institution">repository record</ref> and assign an ID (prefixed INS).</p>
        </item>
        <item>
            <p>leave the place record there, check the already existing
                references to this place. This can be done either with xpath in
                Oxygen or on the website looking at related entities.</p>
        </item>
        <item>
            <p>modify those references that point to a repository
                and not to a place, if any.</p>
        </item>
        <item>
            <p>link the place and repository by adding a relation of the skos:exactMatch type as e.g. in <ref  type="bm" target="INS0017UM">ʿUra Qirqos</ref>
                <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                <listRelation>
                    <relation name="skos:exactMatch" active="INS0017UM" passive="LOC6063UraMas"/>
                </listRelation>
                </egXML>
            </p>
        </item>
    </list>
            <p>See also the Guidelines for <ref target="places">Places</ref> and <ref target="institution">Repositories/Institutions</ref>.</p>
</div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
