<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/guidelines/master/schema/out/tei-betamesaheftGL.rng"
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/guidelines/master/schema/out/tei-betamesaheftGL.rng"
type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>References</title>
            <author>Pietro Liuzzo</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Produced by pandoc. Conversion from GIT flavoured markdown to TEI simple.</p>
            <p>transformed to TEI documentation with XSLT by Pietro Liuzzo</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="PL" when="2018-04-30">first version of guidelines from Wiki</change> 
         <change who="PL" when="2020-06-16">introduced text and example for referencing 
         based on DTS navigation and document support</change>     
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body xml:id="references">
         <div type="level2">
            <head>Internal References</head>
         <p>Any <att>xml:id</att> within the file can be pointed
    to with an element <gi>ref</gi> with a
    <att>target</att> attribute. oXygen will not let you
    enter a double ID, and will pull up a list of
    <att>xml:id</att> when you attempt to enter
    <att>target</att> or
    <att>corresp</att>.
         </p>
         <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<ref target="#p1"/>
</egXML>
         <p>This example will point to the <tag>msPart xml:id="p1"</tag>.
         You can also use this with content, especially where the text of the link is different from the standard label of the node you want to link to, e.g.</p>
         <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<p>this happens also in <ref target="#q14">the final quire</ref></p>
</egXML>
         <p>This second method preserves your text and creates a link. However, please note that multiple
    references will be split in several links, so having something
    like</p>
         <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<p>this happens also in <ref target="#q14 #q15">the final quires</ref></p>
</egXML>
         <p>will not return the text in the element, but the values of the
    targets. You can split that reference like</p>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<p>this happens also in <ref target="#q14 #q15"/>, the final quires</p>
</egXML>
         </div>

         <div  type="level2">
            <head>References to other entities in BM</head>
         <p>If you are adding a reference, please simply mark it up using
    <gi>placeName</gi>, <gi>persName</gi>, etc. If you want to refer to another entity in
    the project but you don’t want to mark up the entity you can use
    <gi>ref</gi> with <att>corresp</att> as
    follows (see also the <ref target="summary-on-the-use-of-ref-and-corresp">summary
    on ref and corresp</ref>). This is intended to be useful especially for pointing
    directly to a particular part of a manuscript description, e.g. a
    hand or a quire or a part. This should also be used to refer to
    specific works.</p>
         <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<ref type="mss" corresp="ESap001">AP-001</ref>
<ref type="work" corresp="LIT4018Mashafa"/>
</egXML>
         <p>In <att>corresp</att>, don’t start with a
    # but use it if you are referring to a
    specific part of the quoted manuscript:</p>
         <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
This manuscript is in the same hand as <ref type="hand" corresp="ESap002#h2"/>
</egXML>
         <p>Please specify the <att>type</att> for each
    reference. Allowed values are encoded in the schema.</p>
</div>
         
         <div type="level2">
            <head>References to text passages</head>
            <p>In manuscript and work records, you 
               may use references to parts of a text, like <gi>locus</gi>, 
               also when we do not yet have
               this text transcription at all. These references are 
               valuable information connecting to a real word artefact. You do not need to have somewhere 
               a <gi>div</gi> or any other element, you are actually adding a structured string which refers to
               the actual real life object, as you would do in any text.
               However, for these references to be resolvable  to a fragment of text 
               (i.e. for you to be able to let the machine retrieve that piece of text you are referring to), 
               this text needs to be present
               and for all the cases in which a reference can be constructed 
               but there is no text, at least the text's 
               structure must be declared by encoding it. So, if you change 
               the structure of a text edition, translation or transcription which have made up (that is, it cannot have 
               a real word resolution allowing you to go to folio 1 recto column b line 4 of the real object), 
               please make sure that any pointer to that is still valid. 
               For example, you
               decide to add a <gi>div</gi> in between your <gi>div</gi> with <att>type</att> 
               edition and a series of previously existing <gi>div</gi>s. You are
               also now making any reference to this invalid, and you need to fix it.
            </p>
            <div type="level3">
               <head>General Structure of references</head>
               
               <p><code>ID_(ED|TR)_(@xml:id).1.2.3</code></p>
               <p>This is made of three main parts.
                  The first part (ID) is separated from the second ((ED|TR)_(@xml:id)) by <q>_</q> .
                  The second part is separated from the third (1.2.3) by <q>.</q>. 
               The first part is also the main ID of the record. The second part is mapped to
               a parameter "edition", which is implementation specific. The last part is mapped to
                  <ref target="https://distributed-text-services.github.io/specifications/">Distributed Text Services</ref> 
                  navigation and document parameters <code>ref</code>, 
                  <code>start</code> and <code>end</code> and are 
                  resolved in the application (i.e. if you point your browser there, 
                  it will return that passage precisely if available) based on our implementation 
                  of the specification, which is surfaced in the text view.</p>
               <p>You can have the first part of the reference alone, to point to the entire text,
               or you can have a pointer to an edition (first and second part, e.g. TUid123text_TR_translation) 
               or to a passage without specifying the edition
               (first and third part, e.g. TUid123text.1.2.3) which will return as 
               many versions as the editions (most of the time, one) 
               or a reference to text, edition and passage with all three parts (e.g. TUid123text_TR_translation.1.2.3).</p>
               <p>The following section provides details on each part of these references.</p>
               <div type="level4">
                  <head>First part (identifier)</head>
               <p><code>ID</code></p>
                  <p>This is the ID of the manuscript or textual unit, <ref target="entities-id-structure">as normally used</ref>.
               Anchors are inconsistent with the aim of this structured referencing system and alternative to it. 
               The following example is what is discussed here, as a pointer to a specific passage in the text TUid123 at a subdivision named 1 which is 
               child of another subdivision named 1.
             It could be a verse in a chapter or a chapter in a book.</p>
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><ref type="work" corresp="TUid123.1.1"/></egXML>
                     
                  <p>Please note the difference between this reference, and the more generic reference as discussed above
                  to an anchor (the <att>xml:id</att> on an element which is unique in that file).</p>
                     
               </div>
               
               <div type="level4">
                  <head>Second part (editions transcriptions and translations)</head>
              <p><code> _(ED|TR)_(@xml:id)</code></p>
              <p>This second, optional part of a reference 
                 identifies the translation or edition, with its type, 
                 which is ED for edition and TR for translation and finally, 
                 after the second underscore
               the @xml:id of the edition/translation, which is especially important if there are more than one edition or translation.
               If this section of the reference is not provided, the default is <tag>div[@type='edition']</tag>.</p>
                  <p>For example, at the time of writing 
                     <ref target="LIT1758Lefafa" type="BM">Lǝfāfa ṣǝdǝq</ref> has two <tag>div[@type='edition']</tag>,
                     one with and one without <att>xml:id</att>.
               <code>LIT1758Lefafa_ED_</code> can be used for the edition in 
                  the <tag>div[@type='edition']</tag> without <att>xml:id</att>
               <code>LIT1758Lefafa_ED_editionBudge</code> for the edition in 
                     the <gi>div</gi> with a <att>xml:id</att>.</p>
              <p>It is important that there are not 
               two or more <gi>div</gi> of the same type without 
                     an <att>xml:id</att> to distinguish them.
               </p>
                  <p>If I want to point to the translation of the
                     <ref target="LIT2170Peripl" type="BM">Periplus of the 
                        Erythraean Sea</ref>, even if it had an <att>xml:id</att>, 
                     I can use <code>LIT2170Peripl_TR_</code>.</p>
               <p>For these records, if no edition is specified, 
                  all available references (i.e. double or triple)
               will be valid references and will be returned.</p>
               </div>
              
               <div type="level4">
                  <head>Third part (reference)</head>
               
               <p>This part, introduced by a <q>.</q> is a 
               reference to a specific passage or range within the selected text and edition/translation.
               Each level is separated by a dot. 
               Levels of the citations depend on the encoded text, they are not fixed, each position
               in the reference is only relevant to that text and how it is encoded and accordingly
               structured. <gi>div</gi>, <gi>l</gi>, <gi>pb</gi>, <gi>cb</gi> and <gi>lb</gi>
                  are the structuring elements. <gi>div</gi>s can be nested and
                  each nested level  will be a citation level. <gi>pb</gi>, <gi>cb</gi> and <gi>lb</gi>
                  are all empty elements whose hierarchy is only dependent on their position, i.e. a column of a page
                  starts at the <gi>cb</gi> which occurs after that <gi>pb</gi>.</p>
               
               <p>The levels in this text reference 
                  can be constructed as a series of sub references. Each
                level is separated by a dot, e.g. 1.1. The value for each level is extracted from
               <list>
                  <item>a <att>n</att></item>
                  <item>a <att>xml:id</att></item>
                  <item>a <att>corresp</att></item>
                  <item>a concatenation of <att>subtype</att> and <att>n</att>.
               </item></list>
               </p>
                  <p>The total number of levels cannot be greater than the citation depth, that is the
                     number of nested countable structures. If there is a <gi>div</gi> with <gi>lb</gi>s in it only,
                     I will only have 2 levels, I cannot point to 1.1.1, because the last level of my reference will not match anything.
             </p>
                  <p>
                     Support for <gi>pb</gi> for multiple citations structures exists, like in
                     the following example from <ref target="LIT2170Peripl" type="BM">Periplus of the 
                        Erythraean Sea</ref>:
                     <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                        <pb n="1" corresp="#frisk"/>
                        <pb n="51" corresp="#casson"/>
                        <pb n="257" corresp="#mueller"/>
                        <pb n="9r" corresp="#L"/>
                     </egXML>
                     Each reference can be pointed to and 
                     retrieved as <code>1.1[frisk]</code>, <code>1.51[casson]</code>, 
                     <code>1.257[mueller]</code>, <code>1.9r[L]</code>
                     as far as the nodes are there and there is a corresponding 
                     bibliography item with <att>xml:id</att>. 
                    </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="level3">
               <p>More detailed information and examples are available in the following two pages.</p>
             <list>
               <item><ref target="referencing-the-manuscript">Adding precise references to places in the manuscript transcription</ref></item>
               <item><ref target="referencing-the-text"/>Adding precise references to places in text editions</item>
            </list>
            <p>A note on the way in which the Beta maṣāḥǝft application uses these references, 
            which is entirely application dependent. The structure described above is mapped to 
            parameters, so that your request for https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT1758Lefafa_ED_editionBudge.2 
            is actually redirected to https://betamasaheft.eu/works/LIT1758Lefafa/text?edition=_ED_editionBudge&amp;ref=2
            </p>
            </div>
         </div>
<div  type="level2">
  <head>External links</head>
    <p>You can also use <att>target</att> to point to
external resources. In this case, please enter the full URL,
starting with http.</p>
         <p>To link to a manuscript in vHMML, please, use the provided
    permalink in the metadata.</p>
         <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
 <ref type="mss" target="https://w3id.org/vhmml/readingRoom/view/133001"/>
</egXML>
</div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
