<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/guidelines/master/schema/out/tei-betamesaheftGL.rng"
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/guidelines/master/schema/out/tei-betamesaheftGL.rng"
type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Referencing parts of the manuscript</title>
            <author>Pietro Liuzzo</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Produced by pandoc. Conversion from GIT flavoured markdown to TEI simple.</p>
            <p>transformed to TEI documentation with XSLT by Pietro Liuzzo</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="PL" when="2018-04-30">first version of guidelines from Wiki</change>
         <change who="PL" when="2020-06-16">introduced text and example for referencing based on DTS
            navigation and document support</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body xml:id="referencing-the-manuscript">
         <head>Referencing parts of the text</head>
         <p> A <gi>locus</gi> element can be used almost everywhere (see content model) to indicate
            the physical location of a content item or other unit of interest which can be delimited
            with reference to a defined portion of text. <gi>locus</gi> contains always either two
            attributes <att>from</att> and <gi>to</gi> or the attribute <att>target</att> with one or
            more references listed which are not a range. Please do not use other numbering systems
            or spaces within these attributes.</p>


         <p>Beside the basic referencing structures (<gi>div</gi>) you may refer to parts of the
            text of the manuscript using references to <gi>pb</gi>, <gi>cb</gi> and <gi>lb</gi>.
            Although for these to be resolvable the text needs to be present and encoded, their
            semantic value with reference to the selected passage remains even when the actual
            elements (<gi>pb</gi>, <gi>cb</gi> and <gi>lb</gi>) and text are not present and the reference is intended to the material object.
            The following are possible references: <list type="ordered">
               <item>a folio, e.g. <code>1</code> (<tag>div[@type='folio'][@n]</tag>)</item>
               <item>a page, e.g. <code>1r </code>(<tag>pb[@n]</tag>)</item>
               <item>a column, e.g. <code>1va</code> (<tag>pb[@n]</tag>,<tag>cb[@n]</tag>)</item>
               <item>a line, e.g. <code>2.1</code>
                     (<tag>div[@type='folio'][@n]</tag>,<tag>lb[@n]</tag>). Note that this is the
                  same very generic referencing system of any numbered division declared in the
                  document, it can refer to a line in a folio, but also to a chapter in a book or a
                  day in a month, depending on what is declared in the file.</item>
               <item>A line, e.g. <code>2</code> (<tag>lb[@n]</tag>), if the folio structure is not
                  present.</item>
               <item>A line, eventually in a specific page and column, e.g. <code>2ra1</code>
                     (<tag>pb[@n]</tag>,<tag>cb[@n]</tag>, <tag>lb[@n]</tag>)</item>
            </list> This assumes consistent numbering.</p>
         <p> It is possible to use the same syntax for a reference to a page in one of more defined
            paging systems, e.g. based on different editions. e.g. <code>1[frisk]</code>
               (<tag>pb[@n][@corresp]</tag>). </p>

         <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <locus from="1v1" to="2ra6">the text begins on 1v in line 1 and ends on 2ra in line 6
            </locus>
         </egXML>
         <p>A list of individual references at page level (without line indication) can be given in
               <att>target</att>
         </p>
         <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <locus target="#28v #33r #49r #50v #55v #82r #82v #83r #83v #84v #85r"/>
         </egXML>
         <p>Please DO NOT use unknown as a value for any of these attributes. Simply do not enter
            the attribute if its value is not known.</p>
         <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <locus from="20r"/>
         </egXML>
         <p>NOT <tag>locus from="20r" to="unknown"</tag>
         </p>
         <p>A manuscript's existing foliation should not be shifted - it is possible to point to
            folia not included in the foliation by assigning individual leaf numbers. This will
            lead to the inability to calculate the foliation, but the semantic will be valid and if
            encoded the reference may be resolvable.</p>
         <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"> Two folios between <locus target="#66"/>
            and <locus target="#67"/>, <locus target="#66i"/> and <locus target="#66ii"/>, are so
            badly mutilated that only small corners - each not containing more than fragments of 4
            letters - are preserved which have not been taken into account for the foliation of the
            manuscript. </egXML>


         <p>While <gi>l</gi>, <gi>lb</gi>, <gi>pb</gi> and <gi>cb</gi> all need to have
            <att>n</att>, <gi>div</gi>s not always have this attribute and sometimes have
               <att>corresp</att>, sometimes <att>subtype</att> or an <att>xml:id</att> or a
            combination of these. For canonical referencing of structures in the text encoded with
               <gi>div</gi>s, any of the basic values or combinations detailed in <ref
               target="references">referencing</ref> can be used.</p>

         <p>This simply means, for example in the Beta maṣāḥǝft web application and related services
            that the text view when listing available references to passages for EMIP01859, e.g. at
            the third level of depth, will show <code>1.1.1</code> but you can use to refer to that
            same passage a number or alternative references e.g.
               <code>EMIP01859.month1.day1.NAR0019SBarkisos</code>, <code>EMIP01859.1.day1.1</code>,
            etc. <code>BLorient718.1.1</code> can be used as an alternative to
               <code>BLorient718.1ra1</code> or <code>BLorient718.1.1ra1</code>, but note the
            different semantic flavouring.</p>
         <p>In real life daily encoding fun, you need to either use the existing references as
            offered in the text view or in the DTS Navigation API, or know the structure of the XML
            to build one option which you like more and is valid according to the guidance offered
            here. The canonical reference displayed in the text view will be the better one
            available at the time of loading the page. Here are some more examples of these
            references:<list>
               <item><code>BLorient718.1</code> gives the folio 1.</item>
               <item><code>BLorient718.1r</code> gives the recto of folio 1.</item>
               <item><code>BLorient718.1ra</code> gives column a on the recto of folio 1.</item>
               <item><code>BLorient718.1ra1</code> gives the first line of column a on the recto of folio
                  1.</item>
               <item><code>BLorient718.1ra1-1ra3</code> gives line 1 to 3 of column a on the recto of folio
                  1.</item>
               <item><code>BLorient718.1ra1-2vb6</code> gives from line 1 of column a on the recto of folio 1 to
                  line 6 of column b on the verso of folio 2. <code>BLorient718.1.1</code> can be used to point
                  to a line, if this is uniquely identified with <att>n</att>.</item>
               <item><code>EMIP01859.month1.day1</code> is also a valid reference and will fetch the element in
                  the manuscript transcription associated with the specified structure of type and
                  names. </item>
               <item><code>EMIP01859.1.1.1</code> is also a valid reference and will fetch the nested structured
                  marked with n. </item>
               <item><code>EMIP01859.month1.day1.NAR0019SBarkisos</code> 
                  is also a valid reference and will fetch
                  the element in the manuscript transcription associated with the specified
                  narrative unit. If you want to fetch passages connected to a narrative unit
                  without specifying the manuscript, add the narrative unit ID instead. </item>
               <item><code>EMIP01859.NAR0019SBarkisos</code> is also a valid reference and will fetch the element
                  in the manuscript transcription associated with the specified narrative unit. If
                  you want to fetch passages connected to a narrative unit without specifying the
                  manuscript, add the narrative unit ID instead. </item>
               <item><code>IVEf921</code> is a letter only encoded into a <tag>div type="edition"</tag>. You can still point to a line in it
                  by saying IVEf921.1 but this will not be resolvable. 
                  The moment you add a <gi>pb</gi> or a <gi>lb</gi>,
                  this will become resolvable and a request for that part of text will return that part of text.
                  
               </item>
               <item><code>RIE193</code> is an inscription with <gi>div</gi>s. you can point to specific ones.</item>
            </list></p>
         <p>It is not possible to canonically reference a part of text transcribed e.g. in an <gi>incipit</gi> inside
         <gi>msContents</gi>, but don't panic, you still have your <att>xml:id</att>! Anchors, 
            informally referred to as "sub-IDs" are a perfectly valid, standard way of referring to an element with an
         <att>xml:id</att>, but they are not canonical citation of the structure of the text in one of its
         manifestations. With a canonical reference you are referring to the text in one of its abstractions
         using a canonical model, which you may have encoded; with an anchor pointing to an 
            <att>xml:id</att> you are referring to that specific element node in an XML tree.</p>
         <p> Inside locus these can be used to refer internally to a piece of text transcription.
            this use in <att>from</att> <att>to</att> and <att>target</att> follows the 
            usual conventions, 
            i.e. does not need the
            manuscript ID.</p> 
         <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
               <locus from="1r" to="2ra" facs="004"/>
               <locus from="1ra1" to="34vb4"/>
               <locus target="#1ra1 #34vb4"/>
               <locus from="1r" to="2ra" corresp="#fol1"/>
            </egXML> 
            
           <p>You may still wish to use your own text for a reference</p>

         <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <locus from="1ra1" to="34vb4">1ra up until the fourth line of column b on the verso of
               folio 34</locus>
            <locus from="1r11" to="1r18">f. 1r lines 11-18</locus>
         </egXML>

         <p>If <gi>locus</gi> is not for you, 
            or you do not want to use a folio/page/column/line reference
            string, for example because you have an inscription or a scroll or a shred of pottery,
            you may opt for a simple <gi>ref</gi>, where you use the 
            reference in full according to the
            structure you have encoded in the file. 
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
               <ref type="mss" corresp="MSid123.section1.column2.text3.4-5"/>
            </egXML> 
            For a formal citation of a passage, you may use a  canonical reference in <att>cRef</att> .
            <egXML
               xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
               <ref cRef="betmas:MSid123.section1.column2.text3.4-5"/>
            </egXML>
         </p>

         <p>Some manuscripts are paginated instead of being foliated. You will have in such cases
            most probably to be consistent and provide inside <gi>extent</gi> a <tag>measure
               unit="page"</tag>. This will then alter the behaviour of the visualization and use p.
            and pp. instead of f. and ff.. However, the values you may enter inside <att>from</att>,
               <att>to</att> or <att>target</att> are still the foliation references, so, 1v, not 2,
            2v, not 4.</p>
         <p>The markup in <gi>locus</gi> of a paginated manuscript will look like in the following
            example</p>
         <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <locus from="1ra" to="6vb">1-12</locus>
         </egXML>
         <p>However, you may use the equivalent markup for a generic reference 
            instead (see also <ref target="referencing-the-text">references to text passages</ref>).</p>
         <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <ref corresp="PaginatedMSid123.1-12">1-12</ref>
         </egXML>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
