<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/guidelines/master/schema/out/tei-betamesaheftGL.rng"
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/guidelines/master/schema/out/tei-betamesaheftGL.rng"
type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Editing the Schema</title>
                <author>Pietro Liuzzo</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Encoded in TEI.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>       <revisionDesc>       <change who="PL" when="2018-04-30">first version of guidelines from Wiki</change>     </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body xml:id="editingSchema">
            <head>Editing the ODD (i.e. the Schema)</head>
          <p>  In the Schema repository there should be five files and the README.md</p>

<p>The .xml files are the ODD (One Document Does it all) and the .rng are the actual RelaxNG schema files used for validation.</p>

<p>To update the schema start always from the ODD (tei-betamesaheft.xml).</p>




            <p>There is very good tutorial to <ref
                    target="http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/Customization/odds.xml">edit ODD (One
                    Document Does it all)</ref> among the TEI resources.</p>
            <p>In most cases, you
                will be simply adding a value to an existing list.
                But to add rules it is safer to ask somebody who has done it.</p>
            <p>Please, try to discuss any schema update in a issue before editing the schema.</p>
            <p>After editing the ODD, use the Oxygen transformation for TEI ODD to RelaxNG which is
                already available in the software and will save a .rng file in a "out" directory
                relative to the place where your schema is stored. You can also do the same using the TEI Roma web application.</p>
            <p>Before committing the edited schema, test it locally validating a file against that
                new version of the rng schema.</p>
            <p>Move then the new version in the main schema repository (not in the out subdirectory) and commit it. This will update the schema used by all the applications.</p>
            <p>If you are not sure of what you are doing please ask.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
