<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/guidelines/master/schema/out/tei-betamesaheftGL.rng"
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/guidelines/master/schema/out/tei-betamesaheftGL.rng"
type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Setup</title>
            <author>Pietro Liuzzo</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
          </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Produced by pandoc. Conversion from GIT flavoured markdown to TEI simple.</p>
            <p>transformed to TEI documentation with XSLT by Pietro Liuzzo</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>       <revisionDesc>       <change who="PL" when="2018-04-30">first version of guidelines from Wiki</change>
        <change who="DR" when="2019-06-24">Corrected typos</change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body xml:id="setup">
<p>This page is intended to guide team members to a stable setting to
work for the project</p>
<p>You will need:
<list><item>an account in GIT (github.com)</item>
<item>Atom (or oXygen
with a licence for it)</item>
<item>an account in Zotero</item></list>
</p>
<div type="level2">
  <head>GITHUB</head>
  <p>Git is a shared repository, public on the web, where we keep our project
  files and code. <ref target="https://github.com/BetaMasaheft">Our organization</ref> in GitHub.com contains several repositories, which are just like
  folders from a user perspective. Here are the files we work on and the documentation, such as
  guidelines and issue tracking. You will use this to:</p>
  <list type="ordered:arabic">
    <item>
      <p>Keep your files in sync with others</p>
    </item>
    <item>
      <p>Point out issues, problems requests</p>
    </item>
  </list>
  <p>You will want to be always up to date. Here is what to do:</p>
<!--  <list type="unordered">
    <item>
      <p>After you created and verified your account, you will need to
      be added to the group; email Pietro to get this done.</p>
    </item>
    <item>
      <p>Install <ref target="https://desktop.github.com/">GitHub
      Desktop</ref></p>
    </item>
    <item>
      <p>Prepare in your computer, in a location of your choice, a
      folder called <hi rendition="simple:bold">BetMas</hi></p>
    </item>
    <item>
      <p>Open GitHub Desktop</p>
    </item>
    <item>
      <p>Login with your GitHub user name and password</p>
    </item>
    <item>
      <p>Clone repositories from the application, if you are logged in and have accepted the invitation to the group, the software will know that you are part of the Beta maṣāḥǝft organization
        and offer that among your possibilities. </p>
    </item>
    <item>
      <p>Select the group Beta maṣāḥǝft organization</p>
    </item>
    <item>
      <p>Select the schema repository</p>
    </item>
    <item>
      <p>Click CLONE below</p>
    </item>
    <item>
      <p>Select the folder BetMas on your computer as target location and say ok</p>
    </item>
    <item>
      <p>This will create a folder called schema in your BetMas folder
      which is identical to that in GitHub and can be synced with it if you
      are online</p>
    </item>
    <item>
      <p>Repeat the same operation for the repositories with the data that you need, most typically
      Manuscript, Persons, Places, Repositories and Works</p>
    </item>
  </list>-->
  <p>If you use the new version GitHub beta:</p>
  <list type="unordered">
    <item>
      <p>After you created and verified your account, you will need to
      be added to the group. Email Pietro to get this done.</p>
    </item>
    <item>
      <p>Install GitHub Desktop</p>
    </item>
    <item>
      <p>Prepare in your computer in a location of your choice a folder
      called BetMas</p>
    </item>
    <item>
      <p>Open GitHub Desktop</p>
    </item>
    <item>
      <p>Login if you aren't automatically logged in</p>
    </item>
    <item>
      <p>Click &quot;file&quot; on the top left corner</p>
    </item>
    <item>
      <p>Select &quot;clone repository&quot;</p>
    </item>
    <item>
      <p>In your browser, go to https://github.com/BetaMasaheft</p>
    </item>
    <item>
      <p>Click on &quot;Schema&quot;</p>
    </item>
    <item>
      <p>Add the URL (https://github.com/BetaMasaheft/Manuscripts) to
      GitHub Desktop</p>
    </item>
    <item>
      <p>In &quot;Local path&quot;, select the folder BetMas</p>
    </item>
    <item>
      <p>Click CLONE below</p>
    </item>
    <item>
      <p>This will create a folder called schema in your BetMas folder
      which is identical to that in GitHub and can be synced with it if you
      are online.</p>
    </item>
    <item>
      <p>repeat the same operation for all other BetaMasaheft
        repositories you might need, most typically
      Authority-Files, Manuscripts, Persons, Places, Repositories and Works</p>
    </item>
  </list>

  <p>Let's say you have edited a manuscript file from the newly cloned Manuscripts repository or created a new manuscript file. To add a new file to the Manuscripts
  folder, create a new file in your XML editor and save it to the Manuscripts folder which you have in your BetMas folder.</p>
  <list type="unordered">
    <item>
      <p>Open GitHub Desktop and select the Manuscripts repository on the left</p>
    </item>
    <item>
      <p>Before you commit your changes, make sure that you are synced: click on "fetch origin" in the upper right corner, and, if there are new commits by others, click on "pull"</p>
    </item>
    <item>
      <p>Click the CHANGE tab and you will see that it has recorded the
      fact that you have added a new file to the folder or modified an existing one</p>
    </item>
    <item>
      <p>Below the list of changes there is a Commit field, where you can enter a name
      such as &quot;new manuscript ready for review&quot; and a
      description about what you have done e.g. &quot;entered catalogue
      entry 1234 from Catalogue X&quot; Please see also this page on <ref target="revisions">revisions</ref> history.</p>
    </item>
    <item>
      <p>Click commit</p>
    </item>
    <item>
      <p>Once it has committed the changes on the top right corner, click
      SYNC (old version of GitHub Desktop) or PUSH. This will look for anything that has changed online and
      update your files locally, then will upload your file or update
      the online version from yours.</p>
    </item>
    <item>
      <p>N.B. THERE IS NO RISK of data to be overwritten or lost.</p>
    </item>
  </list>
  <p>It is always
  advisable to Sync/fetch all your repositories before you begin a work session.</p>
  <p>The Documentation repo contains two other important parts, beside some
  code used locally for the project, the Wiki and the Issues</p>


</div>
<div type="level2">
  <head>Issues</head>
  <p>Let's say something goes wrong. e.g. I cannot see anymore the
  values from the schema! or the text displayed is the wrong one!.
  <ref target="https://github.com/BetaMasaheft/Documentation/issues/new">Open an
  issue for that here</ref> and give as much detail as possible.</p>
  <p>There are templates provided to guide you in writing a nice and understandable issue.</p>

</div>
<div type="level2">
  <head>Atom</head>
  <p>You can use <ref target="https://atom.io/">Atom</ref> to edit
  files, but to validate and get schema related support (like
  autocompletion) you will need to install a package.</p>
  <p><ref target="https://atom.io/packages/linter-autocomplete-jing">linter-autocomplete-jing</ref> Normally, Atom will install dependencies for you, if it fails to do so, at the moment, the current version of this package needs Java to be installed on your machine, and the following additional packages: busy-signal, intentions, linter, linter-ui-default.</p>
  <p>once you have Atom installed, inside Atom, go to settings (or
  preferences on mac), then click on + install on the left and search
  the above string.</p>
  <p>It will find the package. Click on install and say yes to
  dependencies installation requests.</p>
  <p>You will then see errors messages and will get the autocompletion.
  it works very well!</p>
  <p>Note also that if you open a folder as project in atom, which is a git repository, you will be able to pull and push directly in ATOM, using the Github package which is shipped with it. It is awesome.</p>
  <p>Just click on the arrows pointing up and down in the bottom right corner and you will have really all in one place.</p>
</div>
<div type="level1">
  <head>oXygen</head>
  <p>oXygen is a text editor which is very smart with XML.
  oXygen is designed to help you write XML and it does it in a wonderful
  way, with all possible tools to help you in your workflow. Very often
  you will only use a few of the options provided. Some things you might
  find useful to know:</p>
  <p>You can create a project and add to it your folders, so you can
  open files from oXygen directly.
<list>
  <item>click on PROJECT, then on NEW
  project. Call the file BetMas and save it to your BetMas folder,
  where you cloned the repositories from GIT.</item>
  <item>Once created, the project
  will open in oXygen in a side bar on the left (if it doesn't, click on "Project" and "project view" in the upper menu bar). </item>
  <item>click with the
  secondary button on the icon of the project and select &quot;add
  Folder&quot;</item>
  <item>select the folders in the BetMas folder and add them
  all.</item>
  <item>They will appear under the Project icon. Open the
  manuscripts folder and click on a file to open it.</item>
  </list>
  </p>

  <p>While editing your file you might start from one existing file, taking it as a model, and always reading and comparing other files.
    oXygen has several helpful features that will facilitate your work:

    <list>
<item>Once you start typing a name of an element, oXygen will suggest you
which elements can be used there.</item>
<item>You can also use the elements and
attributes view to select from a sidebar the element to add.</item>
<item>Once you
have an element and you want to add an attribute, type the space
separating the element name from the future attribute and oXygen will
pull up a list of attributes from which you can select. If an
attribute is compulsory, it is bold.</item>
<item>Values for attributes are also
suggested by oXygen based on the schema.</item>
<item>To enter an element, you can
either start typing it, or you can select a portion of text to tag and
click CTRL+E which will open a small window where you can type the
first letters of an element's name and select. </item>
<item>You might need to
repeatedly enter the same element. You can do the repeat with
CTRL+/</item>
    </list>
    </p>
  <p>You will often have to enter the current date, for example when
  you describe your work in <gi>change</gi>. To
  facilitate this you can use the Code Templates function in oXygen. Set
  a Code Template for the XML Editor and assign it the current date
  value. Then, while editing to enter today's date open Document/Content
  Completion, start the assistant and enter the date.</p>
  <p>There is a green light on top right corner of your document. If it
  is red, it means something is not valid. Click on the small red bar
  on the side of the document to go to that point and read the
  message. Often this is enough, if you don't understand where the
  problem is, ask Pietro.</p>

  <div type="level2">
    <head>Special Characters and letters with diacritics</head>
    <p>You might need to type one of the following</p>
    <list type="unordered">
      <item>
        <p>Ā ā (long a)</p>
      </item>
      <item>
        <p>Ē ē (long e)</p>
      </item>
      <item>
        <p>Ī ī (long i)</p>
      </item>
      <item>
        <p>Ō ō (long o)</p>
      </item>
      <item>
        <p>Ū ū (long u)</p>
      </item>
      <item>
        <p>Ǝ ǝ (schwa)</p>
      </item>
      <item>
        <p>ʾ (glottal stop)</p>
      </item>
      <item>
        <p>ʿ (ʿayn)</p>
      </item>
      <item>
        <p>Š š (sh)</p>
      </item>
      <item>
        <p>Ś ś (lateral s)</p>
      </item>
      <item>
        <p>Ṣ ṣ (emphatic s)</p>
      </item>
      <item>
        <p>Ḍ ḍ (emphatic d)</p>
      </item>
      <item>
        <p>Ḏ ḏ (dh, Arabic)</p>
      </item>
      <item>
        <p>Ṭ ṭ (emphatic t)</p>
      </item>
      <item>
        <p>Ṯ ṯ (th, Arabic)</p>
      </item>
      <item>
        <p>Ṗ ṗ (emphatic p)</p>
      </item>
      <item>
        <p>Ḥ ḥ (pharyngeal h)</p>
      </item>
      <item>
        <p>Ḫ ḫ (kh)</p>
      </item>
      <item>
        <p>Ž ž (zh, Amharic)</p>
      </item>
      <item>
        <p>Ẓ ẓ (emphatic z, Arabic)</p>
      </item>
      <item>
        <p>Ǧ ǧ (dj)</p>
      </item>
      <item>
        <p>Ġ ġ (gh, Arabic)</p>
      </item>
      <item>
        <p>Č č (ch)</p>
      </item>
      <item>
        <p>Č̣ č̣ (emphatic ch)</p>
      </item>
      <item>
        <p>Ḵ ḵ (kh, Tigrinya)</p>
      </item>
      <item>
        <p>Q̲ q̲ (qh (Tigrinya)</p>
      </item>
      <item>
        <p>Ḳ ḳ (emphatic k)</p>
      </item>
      <item>
        <p>Ñ ñ (gn, Amharic)</p>
      </item>
    </list>
    <p>You can use oXygen Content Completion. To do this, make sure you
    sync the "Documentation" repository. In the folder codetemplates there is all you need.
    Open oXygen, go to Preferences and search &quot;Code
    Templates&quot;. Click on it on the menu list on the left. Once the
    list on the right appears, click IMPORT in the lower right corner.
    select the codetemplates.xml file from the codetemplates folder.
    Apply and close.</p>
    <p>To use this code templates while editing click Document/ Content
    Completion, then &quot;show content completion&quot; and then select
    from the list what you need to type.</p>
  </div>
</div>
<div type="level1">
  <head>Zotero</head>
  <p>Please check the
  <ref target="zotero">Zotero
  guidelines</ref> for working with the group bibliography.</p>
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
