<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/guidelines/master/schema/out/tei-betamesaheftGL.rng"
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/guidelines/master/schema/out/tei-betamesaheftGL.rng"
type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>La Syntaxe du Codex</title>
            <author>Pietro Liuzzo</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Produced by pandoc. Conversion from GIT flavoured markdown to TEI simple.</p>
            <p>transformed to TEI documentation with XSLT by Pietro Liuzzo</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>       <revisionDesc>       <change who="PL" when="2019-03-07">Example extraced from article for issue #35</change>     </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body xml:id="syntaxe">
         <p>Describing the stratigrapy
           following <hi rendition="simple:italic">La Syntaxe du Codex.
             Essai de codicologie structurale</hi>
             <ref target="https://www.zotero.org/groups/358366/ethiostudies/items/itemKey/86TDDASU/">Andrist,
               Canart, and Maniaci 2013</ref> requires reading the methodology outlined in the book.
               It is not just an extraordinary book, it is also well
               written and made clear by examples fully spelled out.</p>
               <p>The Beta maṣāḥǝft application tries to support this
                 methodology with tabular visualizations based also on RDF data which are
                 exemplified by <ref type="bm" target="BAVcerulli37">Vatican City,
                   Biblioteca Apostolica Vaticana, Biblioteca Apostolica Vaticana
                   Cerulli 37</ref> and especially in its <ref target="https://betamasaheft.eu/manuscripts/BAVcerulli37/graph">syntaxe view</ref>.
                 The workings of these are out of the scope of these guidelines and
                 here only the way in which the information is encoded in the TEI will be described. An article by Pietro Liuzzo, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Linked Open Data based
                   on La Syntaxe du Codex for Manuscripts in Beta maṣāḥǝft</hi>, has
                   been submitted for the forthcoming <hi rendition="simple:italic">Linked
                     Ancient Word Data Cookbook</hi>, ed. by Paul Dilley, Sarah Bond e
                     Ryan Horne (ISAW papers).</p>
              <p>The ontology used in the encoding can be
                found <ref target="https://w3id.org/sdc/ontology">here</ref> and can
                be viewed clicking on the ontology button in these guidelines.</p>
                <p>Some of the values, especially properties, are also reproduced for convenience in the Schema.</p>
              <p>The tabular visualizations are based on two aspects of the encoding. The first is the assignation of identifiers to
              the relevant parts of the TEI description. The schema enforces the presence of <att>xml:id</att>. The second part is the use of <gi>relation</gi>
              to make statements which work like stand off annotations about the stratigraphy.</p>
              <p>Both these practices are documented in these guidelines
                elsewhere and here we will focus on how to encode a statement about
                the stratigraphy using <gi>relation</gi>.</p>
                <div type="level2">
                  <head>Production units added later</head>
                  <p>In this example, from <ref target="BDLaethe8" type="bm">Oxford, Bodleian Library, Bodleian Aeth. e. 8</ref>,
                  we want to say that <gi>msPart</gi>s p1 and p2 where added later to the manuscript. From the catalogue information we can deduce that
                  this can be a transformation (this is the term used in the book, which I will not define here)
                  of type A1 (Andrist, Canart, and Maniaci 2013, 63).</p>

                  <p>We can then rely on the <att>xml:id</att>s of the description to describe this sitution in a series of <gi>relation</gi> elements.</p>
                <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<listRelation>
          <relation active="BDLaethe8#p3" name="SdC:constituteUnit" passive="BDLaethe8#UniCirc1"/>
            <relation active="BDLaethe8#UniCirc1" name="SdC:undergoesTransformation" passive="BDLaethe8#tr1"/>
            <relation active="BDLaethe8#tr1" name="SdC:hasTransformationModel" passive="SdC:A1"/>
            <relation active="BDLaethe8#tr1" name="SdC:produces" passive="BDLaethe8#p1"/>
            <relation active="BDLaethe8#tr1" name="SdC:produces" passive="BDLaethe8#p2"/>
            <relation active="BDLaethe8#tr1" name="SdC:resultsIn" passive="BDLaethe8#UniCirc2"/>
            <relation active="BDLaethe8#p1" name="SdC:constituteUnit" passive="BDLaethe8#UniCirc2"/>
            <relation active="BDLaethe8#p2" name="SdC:constituteUnit" passive="BDLaethe8#UniCirc2"/>
            <relation active="BDLaethe8#UniCirc2" name="dcterms:hasPart" passive="BDLaethe8#p1"/>
            <relation active="BDLaethe8#UniCirc2" name="dcterms:hasPart" passive="BDLaethe8#p2"/>
            <relation active="BDLaethe8#UniCirc2" name="dcterms:hasPart" passive="BDLaethe8#p3"/>
            <relation active="BDLaethe8#UniCirc1" name="dcterms:hasPart" passive="BDLaethe8#p3"/>
            <relation active="BDLaethe8#UniCirc2" name="skos:exactMatch" passive="BDLaethe8"/>
</listRelation>

                    </egXML>
                  <p>Here we start defining only the part 3 as UniCirc,
                    by assigning to it the ID ‘UniCirc1’
                    using the property SdC:constituteUnit
                    from the ontology.
                    We continue saying that part 3 (UniCirc1)
                    has undergone a transformation
                    (property SdC:undergoesTransformation).
                    We are actually defining a
                    transformation with ID ‘tr1’ and we want to say that
                    we know that this transformation is an addition
                    of material and content, thus
                    a transformation of type A1, and we do so
                    using the property SdC:hasTransformationModel. </p>
<p>
                    During this process of transformation
                    part 1 and part 2 were produced
                    (SdC:produces) by this transformation,
                    which resulted (SdC:resultsIn) the UniCirc2.
                    Now that the two parts have come into the game,
                    we can also explicitly assign them to the UniCirc2
                    with the property SdC:constituteUnit.
                    We can then also repeat the dcterms:hasPart
                    nodes for each UniCirc.
                    </p>
<p>
The order of the encoded elements is irrelevant, we are just following the logic in the argument.
We can additionally say that it is this one UniCirc with ID ‘UniCirc2’ which actually corresponds to the manuscript we have in our hands.
We cannot make any further statement about UniProd or about the pertinence of the parts 1 and 2 to another UniCirc and we do not do so.
</p>



      </div>

      <div type="level2">
        <head>Added text in another hand</head>
        <p>In <ref target="IVorlov20" type="bm">Saint Petersburg,
                          Institut Vostočnyh Rukopisej Rossijskoj Akademii Nauk,
                          Orlov20</ref>
                          there are two cases, where according to
                              Turaev’s description,
                              some text was presumably added later in another hand.
                              These added portions should be regarded as additions,
                              because they are written in another hand, presumably later.
                              And these texts might also be regarded as
                              complete without these added information, so it was not about the completion of the text,
                              rather adding new information. (this paragraph is an adaptation
                              of the explanation given by Daria Elagina <ref target="https://github.com/BetaMasaheft/Documentation/issues/927">here</ref>)

                      </p>

                      <p>In the following example I reproduce the encoding I have made of this. (<gi>listRelation</gi> is allowed anywhere in the Beta Masaheft schema).</p>
                      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<msItem xml:id="p1_i14">
    <locus target="#9v"/>
    <title ref="LIT4952History" cert="medium"/>
    <textLang mainLang="gez"/>
    <msItem xml:id="p1_i14.1">
        <title type="incomplete" ref="LIT4952History"/>
        <note>Extends till <persName ref="PRS5616IyasuI"/></note>
    </msItem>
    <msItem xml:id="p1_i14.2" corresp="#h5">
        <title type="incomplete" ref="LIT4952History"/>
        <note>Starting from <persName ref="PRS10303Yekunno"/> till
        <persName ref="PRS5616IyasuI"/> the text is written in another hand.
        </note>
    </msItem>
    <listRelation>
         <relation
          active="IVorlov20#UniProd1"
          name="SdC:undergoesTransformation"
          passive="IVorlov20#tr2"/>
         <relation
          active="IVorlov20#tr2"
          name="SdC:produces"
          passive="IVorlov20#UniProd3"/>
         <relation
          active="IVorlov20#tr2"
          name="SdC:resultsIn"
          passive="IVorlov20#UniCirc2"/>
         <relation
          active="IVorlov20#tr2"
          name="SdC:hasTransformationModel"
          passive="SdC:A2"/>
         <relation
          active="IVorlov20#UniProd3"
          name="skos:exactMatch"
          passive="IVorlov20#p1_i14.2"/>
         <relation
          active="IVorlov20#UniProd3"
          name="SdC:constituteUnit"
          passive="IVorlov20#UniCont5"/>
         <relation
          active="IVorlov20#UniProd3"
          name="SdC:constituteUnit"
          passive="IVorlov20#UniMain5"/>
    </listRelation>
</msItem>
                      </egXML>
<p>The encoder had already structured the information about the content of the manuscript in
  a series of nested <gi>msItem</gi>s and the information given by the cataloguer
  is in a <gi>note</gi>. This would be already sufficient and serve well enough the users.
  </p
  ><p>In this example, since we do not know the order
  in which the two additions of contents without material support
  of which the cataloguer and the encoder speak, occurred,
  I have not stated an explicit equation with the main identifier of
  the manuscript, as we would normally do, to say that the
  final UniCirc (circulation unit) corresponds to that final stage.
  This is to say that we know that the manuscript being described is the
      latest available unit of circulation, but
      we do not know in which relation it
      is with the units of circulation resulting
      from each transformation. We also
      do not know if the two additions in question are part
      of a same action, so we have to consider them distinct for the moment.
     </p>
  <p>
      I made instead two statements about the resulting UniCirc with
      each addition, one of which can be seen in the example above at line 23.
      The URI of the manuscript, as well as the UniCirc2 and UniCirc1 URIs
      defined in these sets of triples will be all in the class of
      circulation units, but we are not stating
      which one come first and which one come after since we do not yet know.
The numeric part of the UniCirc identifier has no
 sequential value and is totally arbitrary, although it should be of course unique.
 In the same way the UniProd anchors are set there and will become <term>URI</term>s
in the RDF, but are here defined for the first time.</p>

        </div>
                <div type="level2">
                  <p>Now that most probably nothing of
                    this made sense to you, go read the book (that is really important!),
                  then you can probably figure out much better who the ontology does not
                  change much compared to that and you canuse its values here.</p>
                  <p>Once you have an idea of the stratigraphy of your manuscript than it can most certainly be translated
                    in a series of statements of the kind above and be formally described in this way.</p>
                  <p>In this case the visualizations in the website are supposed
                    to help you also in the process, by offering the table visualization and some graphs.</p>
                    <p>So, try it out! and if you are not sure, drop an issue in the repo and we will be all happy to help.</p>

                </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
