<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/guidelines/master/schema/out/tei-betamesaheftGL.rng" 
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/guidelines/master/schema/out/tei-betamesaheftGL.rng" 
type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Transformation</title>
            <author>Pietro Liuzzo</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
          </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Produced by pandoc. Conversion from GIT flavoured markdown to TEI simple.</p>
            <p>transformed to TEI documentation with XSLT by Pietro Liuzzo</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>       <revisionDesc>       <change who="PL" when="2018-04-30">first version of guidelines from Wiki</change>     </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body xml:id="transformation">
         <p>Once you have your XML file nice and complete and you have validated
it and all is fine, you might wish to test what you have done and
see without tags. We have a test HTML view which you can use for this.
it can be useful to check for white spaces, for information missing of
mistyped, etc. This assumes you have set up your machine to have all the
project repositories in one folder called BetMes as described in the
<ref target="Project-Workplace-Setup#github">GitHub setup</ref> and that
you have checked out and updated you BetaMasaheft repository.</p>
         <p>Here is what you need to do to set up the transformation</p>
         <list type="ordered:arabic">
            <item>
               <p>Open in Oxygen the file you want to see in HTML</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Click the little tool icon on the top which says Configure
    Transformation scenario.
               </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Now click on NEW and select "XML Transformation with
    XSLT" .
               </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>First thing, select from the Transformer menu the highest version
    of SAXON available.
               </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Now name your preview transformation.
               </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>You need now to tell Oxygen where to find the XSLT to start the
    transformation. Click on the browse icon and navigate into your
    local BetaMasaheft repository.
               </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>You will find there a preview folder with several XSLT files,
    select only <gi>preview.xslt</gi>.
               </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>You should be back to the previous window, then click the Output
    tab on top and lets set where the results of your transformation
    will be saved. 
               </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Save it to an appropriate location .
               </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Leave a random name, we will then change it. 
               </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Once you have selected the folder and given a mock name, we will
    substitute that name with a function which will give the same name
    as your original file. click on the little green arrow pointing down
    and select ${cfn} current file name. We want to change the
    extension, so, after entering that type .html .
               </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>I would suggest also to open directly in your browser the saved
    file, ticking the option right there. 
               </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>All set! Apply and enjoy! 
               </p>
            </item>
         </list>
         <p>Attention!</p>
         <list type="unordered">
            <item>
               <p>if Oxygen says the file ended prematurely, it is highly likely
    that something is wrong with your pointers to Zotero, as this is the
    only live API call being done.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>To correctly see bibliography citations and maps you need to be
    online when you transform.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>There are a series of tests embedded in this transformation, to
    help check your contents. For example, if a person ID does not exist,
    you will see a bold red sentence telling you about it. Fix the issue
    and the transform will be fine.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>The Transformation will first check the type of file and will
    return a slightly different view for each different entity type.
    Note that THE HTML IS SCHOOL BASIC as this serves only the purpose
    of testing contents.</p>
            </item>
         </list>
         <p>
            <ref target="guidelines">guidelines</ref>
         </p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
