<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/guidelines/master/schema/out/tei-betamesaheftGL.rng" 
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/guidelines/master/schema/out/tei-betamesaheftGL.rng" 
type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Works</title>
            <author>Pietro Liuzzo</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
          </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Produced by pandoc. Conversion from GIT flavoured markdown to TEI simple.</p>
            <p>transformed to TEI documentation with XSLT by Pietro Liuzzo</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body xml:id="works">
         <div type="level1">
            <head>Definition and Assignment of IDs</head>
         
            <p>We consider a <hi rendition="simple:bold">work</hi> any text with an
independent circulation. This does not mean it should be alone in a
manuscript. A text which sometimes is added to another is also an
independent work. So <hi rendition="simple:italic">Genesis</hi> is a
work as <hi rendition="simple:italic">Pentateuch</hi> is a work which
contains it. But <hi rendition="simple:italic">Chapter 1 of Genesis</hi>
is not a work, it is a part of the work
<hi rendition="simple:italic">Genesis</hi>.</p>
            <p>Works should not be confused with  <ref target="narrativeUnits">Narrative Units</ref>. To
               decide whether the text you are dealing with is a work or a
               narrative unit, consider  Orlandi 2010, <hi rendition="simple:italic">A
                  Terminology for the identification of Coptic Literary Documents</hi>.
               A work "only refers to fixed contents and a precise
               sequence", see
               <ref target="https://www.zotero.org/groups/ethiostudies/items/itemKey/NWT4X3K9/q/corpus-organizers">Bausi
                  2010, 34 n3</ref>
               </p>
            
          <p>Works and textparts:</p>
            
         <list type="unordered">
            <item>
               <p>Texts with independent circulation get an individual record with a first-level ID (such as LIT1931Mashaf), all
    other are textparts. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>If a text is at the same time part of another text and circulates independently, it gets
                  an independent first-level ID/record.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>For these texts (both circulating independently and part of another work), a <gi>div</gi> should also be created, with a
                  <att>corresp</att> giving the individual ID, in order to show the full content of a collection in
                  correct order.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>If a textpart has an individual circulation in other traditions, but not in the Ethiopian tradition,
    all information on this text should be given in the <gi>div</gi>: multiple titles can be
    inserted, with bibliography linking to the IDs of these titles,
    relations for the authors of the titles, etc.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>For text portions (paragraphs, chapters, miracles, etc.) which are extant as different versions in multiple recensions of the same work or even in different works, 
                  create a <ref target="narrativeUnits">Narrative Unit</ref>.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>The existing records inherited from the EAe index that do not
    have an independent circulation in Ethiopic should be deleted.</p>
            </item>
         </list>
            
         <p>See as example
            <ref target="LIT1931Mashaf" type="bm">LIT1931Mashaf</ref>.
         </p>
            
         <p>Often the first problem to face is which records and how many to
make. We accept as a principle to create <hi rendition="simple:bold">the
maximum number of record as it is sensible</hi> and to state
<hi rendition="simple:bold">the minimum number of relations needed among
them</hi> with a view on expanding them potentially to all what is not
essential, in order to clarify their relation with each other. It might
happen that different researchers have different opinions on the
relation between the versions and the manuscripts and in this we will be
able to host them all.</p>
            
         <p>For example. If the Work A has four versions 1, 2, 3 and 4, 1 being a
short version of 2 and 3 a later version of 4 while 2 and 4 differ from
one another only in the order in which the content is organized, there
will be 5 records, one for the abstract work, one for each version.
While the abstract work will point to each of the 4 version with
relations and might contain a general description of the work, each of
the version will have clearly defined relations with the others and the
abstract Work.</p>
            
         <p>A further example: a text which is made of parts which can occur in
different orders within different manuscripts. This will have 1 Work
record, describing the ideal or majoritarian, or standard sequence,
while each witness (Manuscript) will contain the specific order of the
parts in it.</p>
            
         <p>Create a new record for every different version, recensions, etc. and
then express the diverse relations between the records with relation
elements. This should be clearer and leave space for more differing
opinions than to try to express the relations within one single
record.</p>
            
         </div>
         
         <div type="level1">
            <head>Title</head>
            <p>A work file will mainly contain the edited text in the
  <gi>body</gi> element. It will not have instead a
  <gi>msDesc</gi>, although the view of the text will show
  manuscript which point to this work.</p>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<titleStmt>
  <title xml:lang="gez" xml:id="t1">
   <date></date>
  </title>
  <title xml:lang="gez" xml:id="t2">
   <date></date>
  </title>

  <title xml:lang="en" corresp="#t1"></title>
  <title xml:lang="gez" type="normalized" corresp="#t1"></title>
  
</titleStmt>
</egXML>
            <p>You can also use <att>type</att> with value <val>main</val> to signal
  which one title is to be used for labels, pointers and headers. the
  <gi>titleStmt</gi> element will have slightly different
  contents. It will contain the title(s) of the work edited and the
  date. If there is a digital edition, a <gi>editor</gi>
  will be added.</p>
            <p>Titles of the same work in another tradition will be reported
  following the same rule and attributing an arbitrary t+digit <att>xml:id</att>
  and the appropriate <att>xml:lang</att>.</p>
            <p>You can also use <tag>title type='short'</tag> for shortened
  titles like citation forms.</p>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">

<title xml:lang="gez" xml:id="t1">ወንጌል፡ ዘዮሐንስ፡</title>
<title xml:lang="gez" corresp="#t1" type="normalized">Wangel za-Yoḥannǝs</title>
<title xml:lang="en" corresp="#t1" type="main">Gospel of John</title>
<title type="short">Jn.</title>
</egXML>
            <list type="unordered">
               <item>
                  <p>if a subpart of a work needs a bibliography this can be given
      in the <tag>div type='textpart'</tag>
                  </p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>if a subpart without independent circulation in the Ethiopic
      tradition needs to reference the work independently in other
      traditions titles will be added and referenced in the appropriate
                     <tag>div type='textpart'</tag>
                  </p>
               </item>
            </list>
  
         </div>
         <div type="level1">
            <head>Edition statement, Source statement, and encoding
  description</head>
            <p>These elements should be provided in the header for texts that we
  provide edition for. The Edition statement should specify the origin
  of the text. The encoding description specifies the principles used
  when encoding, when known (e.g. transcription, specific tag sets,
  etc.)</p>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<editionStmt>
          <p>Digital text based on  <bibl><ptr target="bm:Marrassini1993AmdaSeyon"/></bibl>.</p>
</editionStmt>
</egXML>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Text prepared within the framework of the TraCES project.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <correction>
               <p>The following errors
                  in Marrassini edition have been corrected:
                  <list>
                     <item>...</item>
                     <item>...</item>
                     <item>...</item>
                     
                  </list>
               </p>
               
            </correction>
                       
            <normalization>
               <p>Original spelling and typography is retained.</p>
            </normalization>
         </editorialDecl>
         <tagsDecl>
            <!-- the format for the tagsDecl to be specified -->
         </tagsDecl>
         
      </encodingDesc>
</egXML>
  
         </div>
         <div type="level1">
            <head>Extent</head>
            <p>Extent should be specified for the works wherever possible;
  obligatory for works with digital text provided, after the edition
  statement:</p>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<editionStmt>
          <p>Digital text based on  <bibl><ptr target="bm:Marrassini1993AmdaSeyon"/></bibl>.</p>
</editionStmt>

<extent>10170  words</extent>
</egXML>
  
         </div>
         <div type="level1">
            <head>Other Clavis ids</head>
            <p>inside sourceDesc, there will be a section like this</p>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<listBibl type="clavis">
               <bibl corresp="#t2coptic" type="CC"><ptr target="bm:CC"/><citedRange unit="item">123</citedRange></bibl>
               <bibl  type="CPG"><ptr target="bm:CPG1"/><citedRange unit="item">123</citedRange></bibl>
               <bibl type="BHO"><ptr target="bm:BHO"/><citedRange unit="item">123</citedRange></bibl>
               <bibl  type="CANT"><ptr target="bm:CANT1"/><citedRange unit="item">123</citedRange></bibl>
               <bibl  type="CAVT"><ptr target="bm:CAVT2"/><citedRange unit="item">123</citedRange></bibl>
               <bibl  type="BHL"><ptr target="bm:BHL"/><citedRange unit="item">123</citedRange></bibl>
               <bibl type="syriaca"><ptr target="bm:syriaca"/><citedRange unit="item">123</citedRange></bibl>
               <bibl type="KRZ"><ptr target="bm:KRZ"/><citedRange unit="item">123</citedRange></bibl>
            </listBibl>
</egXML>
            <p>containing ids of the work pointing eventually to the title in
  titleStmt.</p>
  
         </div>
         <div type="level1">
            <head>Witnesses</head>
            <p>We use <gi>witness</gi> for those manuscripts
  which are <hi rendition="simple:bold">actually used</hi> for the
  edition we are going to provide in the
  <tag>div type='edition'</tag>. All catalogued
  manuscripts containing the work are displayed in the app anyway.</p>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<listWit>
     <witness cert="low" corresp="EMML1234"/>
     <witness type="external" facs="http://archivesetmanuscrits.bnf.fr/ead.html?id=FRBNFEAD000091073" corresp="BNFEAD000091073"/>
     <witness type="external" corresp="EMML"/>
  <listWit>
     <witness corresp="ES123"/>
     <witness corresp="BL8910">this manuscript was donated by <persName ref="PRS123124trhas"/>, 
     at <placeName ref="LOC21321asa"/> and is a copy of <ref corresp="EMML2" type="mss"/>
    </witness>
 </listWit>
</listWit>
</egXML>
            <p>
               <gi>listWit</gi>s can be nested if needed for example
  to group them in families. Each <gi>witness</gi> will
  have to take a <att>corresp</att> pointing to the
  manuscript <att>xml:id</att>. If the manuscript is in
  beta mesaheft catalogue that is enough. If the manuscript is into an
  external catalogue, than use @type='external' as in
  listBibl[type='mss'] in the manuscript entity. You can use
  <att>cert</att> to specify a degree of certainty
  regarding the manuscript you are listing. Please, note that each
  witness element can take a fully marked up description in relation to
  the text.</p>
            <p>As information provided by the catalogues we are working with
  should not be lost, whenever a catalogue description contains
  references to other manuscripts containing the same work, mini ms
  records containing the work ID should be created for those
  manuscripts. This assures that all the manuscripts containing the same
  work can be retrieved by the app while reserving
  <gi>listWit</gi> in the work records mainly for the
  manuscripts used for the edition.</p>
  
         </div>
         <div type="level1">
            <head>Bibliography</head>
            <p>At the moment there are no text to be entered. However there will
  be. The body of the Work entity will contain a series of
  <gi>div</gi>s for marked up text</p>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
 <text>
        <body>
        <div type="bibliography">
            <listBibl type="editions">
                <bibl></bibl>
            </listBibl>
            <listBibl type="text">
                <bibl></bibl>
            </listBibl>
            <listBibl type="otherLanguages">
                <bibl></bibl>
            </listBibl>
        </div>
            <div type="edition">
                <ab></ab>
            </div>
            <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                <ab></ab>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</egXML>
            <p>different <gi>listBibl</gi> will be used for separate
  types of entries. within
  <tag>listBibl type='editions'</tag> each bibl will be an
  edition of this work. each of this editions will have used different
  manuscripts.</p>
            <p>References to these witnesses can be done with a link directly to a
  <gi>witness</gi>'s or a <gi>listWit</gi>'s
  @xml:id like in LIT2317Senodo and LIT1709Kebran.</p>
            <p>Secondary bibliographic references given in catalogues about a
  certain work can also be copied here, as they do not belong to the
  manuscript description.</p>
  
         </div>
         <div type="level1">
            <head>Relations</head>
            <p>Each relationship should be listed separately in a
  <gi>relation</gi>, even if the same relationship exists
  between this and more than one other entity.
  <att>name</att> contains the name of the relation.
  Allowed values for relations among works and authors are those in the
  <ref target="http://www.ancientwisdoms.ac.uk/media/ontology/doc/">SAWS
  Ontology</ref> and those used by syriaca.org you can filter them out
  in oXygen typing syriaca: or saws: in the value list.</p>
            <p>
               <att>active</att> should contain the xml:id of the
  current item. <att>passive</att> should contain the ids
  of the related works, people, places, separated by a space</p>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<listRelation>
  <relation name="syriaca:share-a-title" active="LIT1001Homili" passive="LIT1002title">
        <desc>It is always a nice idea to provide a description of this relations with a sentence or two.         
        </desc>
  </relation>
</listRelation>
</egXML>
            <p>The relationship between a work and its subject is expressed in the
  person record:</p>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<relation name="ecrm:P129i_is_subject_of"
active="PRS4585Georgeo"
passive="LIT1455GadlaG"/>
</egXML>
         </div>
         <div type="level1">
            <head>Authors</head>
            <p>Please Note that we will encode
  <hi rendition="simple:bold">AUTHORSHIP</hi> as a relation in the work
  record, to be more specific and explicit about the sort of
  authorship.</p>
            <p>
               <tag>relation name='dcterms:creator' active='LIT1608hoheta' passive='PRS4709Giyorgis'</tag>
            </p>
            <p>This means that the work has this author.</p>
            <p>If a work is traditionally attributed to an author whose authorship
  is not currently considered to be historical, this can be expressed
  verbally with bibliographic references in the description of the
  relation, for example LIT1608hoheta:</p>
            <p>
               <tag>relation name='saws:isAttributedToAuthor' active='LIT1608hoheta' passive="PRS4709Giyorgis'</tag>
            </p>
            <p>
               <tag>relation name='saws:isAttributedToAuthor' active='LIT1608hoheta' passive='PRS3709eleni'</tag>
               <!--descThe traditional attribution to persName ref="PRS3709eleni"/             is considered unlikely by biblptr target="bm:Habtemichael2007Hoheta"//bibl./desc/relation</tag>-->
            </p>
            <p>you can use many of this and also have different types for one
  work. If you come across records which use the author element, please
  correct them.</p>
            <p>You might need to express concept which need more than one
  relation. For example if Person A is author of a translation B of a
  work C in arabic, you will need a relation of authorship between A and
  B (A isAuthorOf B) and the relation stating the fact that B is a
  translation of C (B isLooseTranslationOf C). If a digital edition of
  the translated work exists, please use that as a value in the
  relation. If no such edition exist you might point to the id of the
  title in the language of the original.</p>
  
         </div>
         <div type="level1">
            <head>Versions</head>
            <p>If you have multiple recensions/version of a text, these can be
  linked with a relation with
  <tag>name='saws:isVersionOf'</tag> this will be used to
  pick up these in the text view. The same parallel content in the
  different versions should have the same @corresp to a NAR unit and
  there should always be a @resp in the div[@type='edition'] containing
  this text part with multiple versions with either the initials of the
  editor or the pointer to the xml:id of the bibl element which has a
  pointer to the edition.</p>
  
         </div>
         <div type="level1">
            <head>Dates</head>
            <p>For the date of creation of a work, use the element
  <gi>creation</gi> in <gi>profileDesc</gi>
  as in the following example</p>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<creation when="1555-06-23" corresp="#Pdamot">23 Sane (17 June) 1555 in <placeName ref="LOC2488Damot" xml:id="Pdamot">Damot</placeName></creation>
</egXML>
            <p>any other date relevant to the work elaboration or life could be
  added in a date element, possibly pointing to one of the placeNames in
  the file with a proper id as in the example below.</p>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<date when="1555-06-23" corresp="#Pdamot">23 Sane (17 June) 1555</date> in <placeName ref="LOC2488Damot" xml:id="Pdamot">Damot</placeName>
</egXML>
            <p>It is important that the id of the referred place starts with P
  because there are cases where corresp is already used to point to
  another id, e.g. a work in another tradition title. Look at this
  fictitious example, where I have entered a placeName with Q item id
  from wikidata (Ethiopia) and assigned the second corresp and the id
  with P</p>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
 <creation corresp="#t2arabic #Ptest" when="1238-09" >
<placeName ref="Q115" xml:id="Ptest"></placeName>
</creation>
</egXML>
            <p>this sounds like a dirty hack to get it working... and it is!</p>
         </div>
         <div type="level1">
            <head>Attested placeNames</head>
            <p>The attestations of placeNames should be marked as in the example
  below</p>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<ab> ምዕራፍ፡፱። ወእምዝ፡ ዓደወ፡ ማር፡ ገላውዴዎስ፡ 
ማዕዶተ፡ ክልኤቱ፡ አፍላግ፡ መንገለ፡ ምድረ፡ 
<placeName 
ref="LOC5597Sawa" 
notBefore="1540" 
notAfter="1559">ሼዋ፡</placeName> 
እመንገለ፡ምድረ፡ 
<placeName 
ref="LOC5932Tegray" 
notBefore="1540" 
notAfter="1559">ትግራይ፡</placeName>
 ከመ፡ ይርአይ፡ መርዔቶ፡ bእለ፡ ህየ፡ በጽድቅ፡ ወይዋሄ፡ cሕዝቦ፡ በርትዕ። ወበጽሐ፡</ab>
</egXML>
            <p>to choose which id to use consider the following:</p>
            <list type="unordered">
               <item>
                  <p>if it is a place of interest for ethiopian studies or attested
      in ethiopia, then use one of our internal ids or create a new
      record if none is yet available</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>if it is an ancient place but not in ethiopia, like Jordan,
      Rome, etc. then search pleaides and use a pleiades id prefixed
      with pleaides: e.g. for Jordan River use plaeides:687932</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>if it is an ancient place not of our interest and not relevant
      for pleiades, check in wikidata and enter the item id (starting
      with Q)</p>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>you can also add a @resp with the id of one of our person records
  or editors and a @source with a list of bm:tags from the Zotero
  Ethiostudies group library.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="level1">
            <head>Short Summary of Contents</head>
            <p>To provide a short summary of contents use the element
  <gi>abstract</gi> in as in this example from
  <ref target="https://github.com/BetaMasaheft/Works/blob/master/LIT1252Confes.xml">Confessio
  Claudii</ref>
            </p>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<abstract>
   <p>A theological treatise believed to be a responce of king <persName 
       ref="PRS4428Galawdew">Galāwdewos</persName> to the Jesuit missionaries headed by <persName     
       ref="PRS7691Oviedo">Oviedo</persName>.
   </p>
</abstract>
</egXML>
            <p>The abstract can also mention the total number of words, which
  might be then marked up with a
  <tag>measure type='words'</tag> within the
  <gi>abstract</gi>.</p>
            <p>Summaries given in catalogues can be copied here and edited.</p>
  
         </div>
         <div type="level1">
            <head>divs edition and textparts</head>
            <p>Text is entered in the <gi>body</gi> of a TEI file
  under into a <tag>div type='edition'</tag> . Each text
  part should be contained into a <gi>div</gi>.
  <gi>div</gi>s should always be well nested one into the
  other. These will always take a
  <tag>subtype='textpart'</tag> and a
  <att>subtype</att> with the desired value. There should
  always be also a @n identifying for example chapter 3 as well as a
  <att>corresp</att> pointing to the appropriate
  <gi>msPart</gi> or <gi>msItem</gi>
            </p>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">

<div type="edition">
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="1">
<ab>
<l n="1">
ዝውእቱ ፡ አስማቲሆሙ ፡ ለደቂቀ ፡ እስራኤል ፡ እለ ፡ ቦኡ ፡ ብሔረ ፡ ግብጽ ፡ ምስለ ፡ ያዕቆብ ፡ አቡሆሙ ፡ [ለ]ለአሐዱ ፡ አሐዱ ፡ በበ ፡ አዕጻዲሆሙ ፡ ቦኡ ።
</l>
<l n="2">ሮቤል ፡ ወስምዖን ፡ ወሌዊ ፡ ወይሁዳ ።</l>
<l n="3">ወይ[ሳኮ]ር ፡ ወዛቡሎን ፡ ወብንያም ።</l>
</ab>
  </div>
</div>
</egXML>
            <p>Please be careful in always stating the sources for the description
  of a work, especially for the division of the work into textparts and
  other structural decisions. Ideally this source should be an edition,
  but if none exists, state if the description follows for example the
  EAe or a manuscript.</p>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<div type="edition">
 <note>This division into textparts follows <ref type="mss" corresp="FSUrueppII2"/>.</note>
<div type="textpart" subtype="book" n="1" xml:id="Kefl1" xml:lang="gez"></div></div>
</egXML>
            <p>Note that after each word there should be a separator or
  punctuation without space.</p>
            <p>If the text contains verses we will use <gi>l</gi> as
  in the example above. Also <gi>lb</gi> can be used to
  mark linebreaks, for example in Inscriptions. Be carefull:
  <gi>ab</gi> should be only in the lowest level div
  nesting!</p>
            <p>to identify a div you can use a label</p>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<div type="textpart" xml:id="Athanasius1">
            <label>Homily on the Incarnation by Athanasius of Alexandria</label>
         </div>
</egXML>
            <p>or a corresp pointing to another work</p>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<div type="textpart" xml:id="example" corresp="LIT1234blabla">
            
         </div>
</egXML>
         </div>
         <div type="level1">
            <head>Languages</head>
            <p>within langUsage all languages used in the file should be defined.
  It is not a problem if one of these statements is not relevant to the
  current record, but if another language is used, it should be
  defined.</p>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
 <langUsage>
    <language ident="en">English</language>
    <language ident="it">Italian</language>
    <language ident="gez">Gəˁəz</language>
 </langUsage>
</egXML>
            <p>If you add somewhere e.g.
  <tag>title xml:lang='am'</tag>, there
  should be a language element in langUsage like the following</p>
            <p>
               <!--<gi>language ident="am"Amharic/language</gi>-->
  the values of @ident here are restricted, so you should not be able to
  add e.g. amh as value for @ident and consequently use it in the file
  as value of @xml:lang.</p>
         </div>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
