<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.GitHubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/guidelines/master/schema/out/tei-betamesaheftGL.rng"
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.GitHubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/guidelines/master/schema/out/tei-betamesaheftGL.rng"
type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Workflow</title>
            <author>Pietro Liuzzo</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
          </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Produced by pandoc. Conversion from GIT flavoured markdown to TEI simple.</p>
            <p>transformed to TEI documentation with XSLT by Pietro Liuzzo</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>       <revisionDesc>       <change who="PL" when="2018-04-30">first version of guidelines from Wiki</change>     </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body xml:id="workflow">
        <div type="level2">
<p>In general the workflow for the app can be called GitHub based. The app relies on data which is pushed from GitHub and is validated.</p>
<p>It can happen that a file goes out of sync, but the data is kept in the GitHub repository separated from the code to be available for other implementations and applications.</p>
<p>That is to say, if you do not see your data updated in few seconds, then please see the <ref target="validation">validation</ref> page and if this does not help, open an issue.</p>
        </div>
<div type="level2">
  <p>Once you have <ref target="setup">GitHub installed and the repositories are all up to date</ref> you are ready to start.</p>
  <p>Open on your computer the folder where you have cloned the GitHub repository, for example a BetMas
    folder on your desktop where you have the Manuscripts folder, which is actually the cloned repository.</p>
    <p>Select the file you want to edit, e.g. EMIP00001.xml.
    Open the file with Atom or Oxygen or any other XML editing software you like. <ref target="setup">You find more advice in the setup page for example to create a project, which will allow you to avoid having always to go back and between from your system and the software.</ref></p>
    <p>Following these guidelines, you can edit the file and save it.</p>
    <p>GitHub will see the change and if you open it, you will see that it has recorded the
      changes you made (under the changes tab).
      When you are ready, you can make sure you have <ref target="revisions">recorded your changes</ref>, that your files are <ref target="validation">valid</ref> and then you can commit them,
   leaving a commit message which explains nicely and clearly what you have done (i.e. avoid commit messages like 'upd' or 'changes'...).
      After few seconds, you can eventually check your file in the web application.
  </p>
  <p>Some tasks, like finding the correct ID for a reference or named entity, will need anyway to use the application, unless you prefer to search through the files directly in your editing software.</p>
  <p>In very limited and checked cases you might need to create new entries. You need permission to do so via the application. then you can follow the guidance in the <ref target="newEntry">new record creation</ref> page.</p>
  </div>
         <div type="level2">
            <head>Batch editing files</head>
            <p>You can find and replace strings or regex patterns throughout the
               data in Oxygen for example. Before replacing all, you will be asked if
               you want to preview. This is always wise and gives you one more
               occasion to spot check your changes before performing the action. Please, make sure you untick the option
  to create .bak files - in case you forget, and such files are created,
  please DO NOT commit them. </p>
            <p>In case you have anyway made a mistake, remember that before
  committing data you can review in Git desktop the changes and discard
  them if they are wrong. If you have committed, pushed and you
  realize it was a big mistake, you can still revert your own commit</p>
         </div>
         <div type="level2">
            <head>Keeping track</head>
            <p>To keep track of the workflow we used to refer to a google drive spreadsheet. This workflow is deprecated and discouraged in any way, as the spreadsheet is outdated by two years
               and should not be used to support any statement about entities in the website.
               Its historical purpose, and usage to originate the initial batch of data does not justify the redundancy of going back to look into that.
            </p>
            <p>You can use your user page to see what you have done recently or use the latest function to see what is new in the data.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
