<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/guidelines/master/schema/out/tei-betamesaheftGL.rng"
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/guidelines/master/schema/out/tei-betamesaheftGL.rng"
type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Works Description</title>
            <author>Pietro Liuzzo</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
          </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Produced by pandoc. Conversion from GIT flavoured markdown to TEI simple.</p>
            <p>transformed to TEI documentation with XSLT by Pietro Liuzzo</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>       <revisionDesc>

        <change who="DR" when="2018-04-26">editing of the Work section of the guidelines</change>
          <change who="PL" when="2018-04-30">first version of guidelines from Wiki</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body xml:id="work-teiHeader">

<div type="level2">
   <head>titleStmt</head>

<p>
   The title(s) of the work are encoded in <gi>titleStmt</gi>:

   <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <titleStmt>
         <title xml:lang="gez" xml:id="t1">መጽሐፈ፡ ቅዳሴ፡</title>
         <title xml:lang="gez" corresp="#t1" type="normalized">Maṣḥafa qǝddāse</title>
         <title xml:lang="en" corresp="#t1">Book of the Consecration</title>
         <title xml:lang="en" xml:id="t2">Missal</title>
         <title xml:lang="en" xml:id="t3">Book of Liturgy</title>
         <editor role="generalEditor" key="AB"/>
         <funder>Akademie der Wissenschaften in Hamburg</funder>
      </titleStmt>
   </egXML>

   In general, the normalized version of the Gǝʿz is the one printed on the app to refer to a work. If another title should be printed, because it is the standard title used when
   referring to this work, you can also use <att>type</att> with value <val>main</val> to signal
   the title which is to be used for labels, pointers and headers.
</p>
<p>The title which will be printed on the website will therefore be, in order of priority
   <list>
      <item><tag>title[@type = 'main'][@corresp = '#t1']</tag></item>
      <item><tag>title[@corresp = '#t1'][@xml:lang = 'am']</tag></item>
      <item><tag>title[@corresp = '#t1'][@xml:lang = 'gez']</tag></item>
      <item><tag>title[@corresp = '#t1'][@xml:lang = 'en']</tag></item>
      <item><tag>title[@corresp = '#t1']</tag></item>
      <item>  <tag> title[1]</tag></item>
   </list>
   In the example above, therefore <hi rendition="simple:italic">Maṣḥafa qǝddāse</hi> will be printed.
   Please be as careful in your encoding of titles as everywhere else to correctly encode the facts and not adapt them in order to achieve a certain visualization.
    </p>

   <p>Titles of the same work in another tradition will be reported
      following the same rule and attributing an arbitrary t+digit <att>xml:id</att>
      and the appropriate <att>xml:lang</att>.
   </p>

   <p>You can also use <tag>title type='short'</tag> for shortened
      titles like citation forms:
   <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">

      <title xml:lang="gez" xml:id="t1">ወንጌል፡ ዘዮሐንስ፡</title>
      <title xml:lang="gez" corresp="#t1" type="normalized">Wangel za-Yoḥannǝs</title>
      <title xml:lang="en" corresp="#t1" type="main">Gospel of John</title>
      <title type="short">Jn.</title>
   </egXML>
   </p>

<p>If a subpart of a work, which does not circulate independently  in the Ethiopic
   tradition, does circulate independently in other
   traditions, the relevant titles and references will be added in the appropriate
   <tag>div type='textpart'</tag>, not in <gi>titleStmt</gi>.
</p>

   <!--editor-->
</div>


<div type="level2">
<head>Authors</head>
<p>Please Note that we will encode
<hi rendition="simple:bold">AUTHORSHIP</hi> as a relation in the work
record, to be more specific and explicit about the sort of
authorship.</p>
<p>
   <tag>relation name='dcterms:creator' active='LIT1608hoheta' passive='PRS4709Giyorgis'</tag>
</p>
<p>This means that the work has this author.</p>
<p>If a work is traditionally attributed to an author whose authorship
is not currently considered to be historical, this can be expressed
verbally with bibliographic references in the description of the
relation, for example LIT1608hoheta:</p>
<p>
   <tag>relation name='saws:isAttributedToAuthor' active='LIT1608hoheta' passive="PRS4709Giyorgis'</tag>
</p>
<p>
   <tag>relation name='saws:isAttributedToAuthor' active='LIT1608hoheta' passive='PRS3709eleni'</tag>
   <!--descThe traditional attribution to persName ref="PRS3709eleni"/             is considered unlikely by biblptr target="bm:Habtemichael2007Hoheta"//bibl./desc/relation</tag>-->
</p>
<p>you can use many of this and also have different types for one
work. If you come across records which use the author element, please
correct them.</p>
<p>You might need to express concept which need more than one
relation. For example if Person A is author of a translation B of a
work C in Arabic, you will need a relation of authorship between A and
B (A isAuthorOf B) and the relation stating the fact that B is a
translation of C (B isLooseTranslationOf C). If a digital edition of
the translated work exists, please use that as a value in the
relation. If no such edition exist you might point to the ID of the
title in the language of the original.</p>

</div>

<div type="level2">
<head>Clavis IDs</head>
<p>Inside <gi>sourceDesc</gi>, IDs of the work in different claves can be given in <tag>listBibl type='clavis'</tag>:</p>
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<listBibl type="clavis">
   <bibl corresp="#t2coptic" type="CC"><ptr target="bm:CC"/><citedRange unit="item">123</citedRange></bibl>
   <bibl  type="CPG"><ptr target="bm:CPG1"/><citedRange unit="item">123</citedRange></bibl>
   <bibl type="BHO"><ptr target="bm:BHO"/><citedRange unit="item">123</citedRange></bibl>
   <bibl  type="CANT"><ptr target="bm:CANT1"/><citedRange unit="item">123</citedRange></bibl>
   <bibl  type="CAVT"><ptr target="bm:CAVT2"/><citedRange unit="item">123</citedRange></bibl>
   <bibl  type="BHL"><ptr target="bm:BHL"/><citedRange unit="item">123</citedRange></bibl>
   <bibl type="syriaca"><ptr target="bm:syriaca"/><citedRange unit="item">123</citedRange></bibl>
   <bibl type="KRZ"><ptr target="bm:KRZ"/><citedRange unit="item">123</citedRange></bibl>
</listBibl>
</egXML>
   <p>You cannot have both <gi>p</gi> and <gi>listBibl</gi> in <gi>sourceDesc</gi>, so if you also need paragraphs, add another <gi>sourceDesc</gi>.</p>
   <p>Please use only the clavis IDs given in this example. If there is another clavis you would like to add to this list, please open an issue to discuss it. Other 
      references to works in standardized lists, such as Chaîne's Répertoire or various publications listing the single Miracles of Mary can
      be given as a bibliographic reference in <gi>listBibl</gi>, while references to external sources such as the Umwelttexte  
    by Corpus Coranicum can be given in a <gi>relation</gi> between the record and the external reference in 
   <gi>listRelation</gi>, see below.</p>
</div>

<div type="level2">
<head>Witnesses</head>

<p>We use <gi>witness</gi> for those manuscripts
which are <hi rendition="simple:bold">actually used</hi> for the
edition we are going to provide in the
<tag>div type='edition'</tag>. All
manuscript records containing the work are displayed in the app anyway.</p>
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
   <sourceDesc>
      <listWit>
         <witness corresp="BLorient818" xml:id="L"/>
         <witness corresp="BNFet146" xml:id="P"/>
         <witness corresp="ONBAeth4" xml:id="W"/>
      </listWit>
   </sourceDesc>
</egXML>
<p>

   <gi>listWit</gi>s can be nested if needed, for example
to group them in families. Each <gi>witness</gi> will
have to take a <att>corresp</att> pointing to the
manuscript <att>xml:id</att>. If the manuscript is in already described in
Beta maṣāḥǝft, that is enough. If the manuscript is described in an
external catalogue, then use <tag>@type='external'</tag>  in
<tag>listBibl[type='mss']</tag> in the manuscript entity. You can use
<att>cert</att> to specify a degree of certainty
regarding the manuscript you are listing. Please, note that each
witness element can take a fully marked up description in relation to
the text.</p>
<p>As information provided by the catalogues we are working with
should not be lost, whenever a catalogue description contains
references to other manuscripts containing the same work, mini ms
records containing the work ID should be created for those
manuscripts. This assures that all the manuscripts containing the same
work can be retrieved by the app while reserving
<gi>listWit</gi> in the work records mainly for the
manuscripts used for the edition.</p>

<p>Please note that the list of manuscripts containing a work shown in the application
  and the list of witnesses used for an edition are two different things.
  The first picks up whatever information is available, it might be less or more than we actually know at the moment depending on what has been marked up and linked.
  The <gi>listWit</gi> contains instead a statement about
  the manuscripts used for an edition, which can be nested, and also might contain manuscripts which we do not have yet.</p>
</div>



<div type="level2">
<head>Relations</head>
<p>Each relationship should be listed separately in a
<gi>relation</gi>, even if the same relationship exists
between this and more than one other entity.
<att>name</att> contains the name of the relation.
<!--Allowed values for relations among works and authors are those in the
<ref target="http://www.ancientwisdoms.ac.uk/media/ontology/doc/">SAWS
Ontology</ref> and those used by syriaca.org. You can filter them out
in oXygen typing syriaca: or saws: in the value list.--></p>
<p>
   Usually, <att>active</att> should contain the <att>xml:id</att> of the
current item. <att>passive</att> should contain the ID
of the related work, person or place. In <gi>desc</gi>, the relation can be described with a sentence or two:</p>
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
   <listRelation>
   <relation name="saws:isAttributedToAuthor"
      active="LIT1925Mashaf#t2arabic"
      passive="PRS7509Nasralla">
      <desc>It is not clear whether <persName ref="PRS7509Nasralla"/>, who is otherwise unknown, is the compiler or author.
         <bibl>
            <ptr target="bm:Pietruschka2005EAEFalasfa"/>
         </bibl>
      </desc>
   </relation>
   </listRelation>
</egXML>
<p>The relationship between a work and its subject is expressed in the
person record:</p>
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<relation name="ecrm:P129i_is_subject_of"
active="PRS4585Georgeo"
passive="LIT1455GadlaG"/>
</egXML>
   
   <p>External entries in databases or similar which concern a particular work can also be referenced in a <gi>relation</gi>. If, as in the case of the TUK IDs given by
      Corpus Coranicum, the external entry refers only to a part of a work, it is preferable to add the <gi>relation</gi> in the exact <gi>div</gi> of this textpart in our 
      edition, using <tag>relation name="skos:exactMatch"</tag>. If this is not possible, because we do not yet have the text of the work or because we 
      follow different divisions than the other reference, <tag>relation name="skos:broadMatch"</tag> can be used at the most pertinent place of the record with the 
      most precise pointer to our record possible in <att>passive</att>:</p>
   <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <listRelation>
      <relation name="skos:broadMatch" 
         active="https://corpuscoranicum.de/kontexte/index/sure/6/vers/74/intertext/673"
         passive="LIT1697Jubilees"/>
      </listRelation>
   </egXML>
   <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="47">
         <ab>ወበውእቱ ፡ መዋዕል ፡ ዐርገት ፡ ጸሎተ ፡ ጻድቃን ፡ ወደመ ፡ ጻድቅ ፡ እምነ ፡ ምድር ፡ ቅድመ ፡ እግዚአ ፡ መናፍስት
            ። በእሉ ፡ መዋዕል ፡ የኀብሩ ፡ ቅዱሳን ፡ እለ ፡ ይነብሩ ፡ መልዕልተ ፡ ሰማያት ፡ በ፩ቃል ፡ ወያስተበቊዑ ፡ ወይጼልዩ
            ፡ ወይሴብሑ ፡ ወያአኲቱ ፡ ወይባርኩ ፡ ለስሙ ፡ ለእግዚአ ፡ መናፍስት ፡ በእንተ ፡ ደመ ፡ ጻድቃን ፡ ዘተክዕወ ፡
            ወጸሎቶሙ ፡ ለጻድቃን ፡ ከመ ፡ ኢትፀራእ ፡ በቅድመ ፡ እግዚአ ፡ መናፍስት ፡ ከመ ፡ ይትገበር ፡ ሎሙ ፡ ኲነኔ ፡
            ወትዕግሥት ፡ ኢይኩን ፡ ሎሙ ፡ ለዓለም ። ወበእማንቱ ፡ መዋዕል ፡ ርኢክዎ ፡ ለርእሰ ፡ መዋዕል ፡ ሶበ ፡ ነበረ ፡
            በመንበረ ፡ ስብሐቲሁ ፡ ወመጻሕፍተ ፡ ሕያዋን ፡ በቅድሜሁ ፡ ተከሥቱ ፡ ወኲሉ ፡ ኀይሉ ፡ ዘመልዕልተ ፡ ሰማያት ፡ ወዐውደ
            ፡ ዚአሁ ፡ ይቀውሙ ፡ ቅድሜሁ ። ወልቦሙ ፡ ለቅዱሳን ፡ ትመልእ ፡ ፍሥሐ ፡ እስመ ፡ በጽሐ ፡ ኊልቋ ፡ ለጽድቅ ፡
            ወጸሎቶሙ ፡ ለጻድቃን ፡ ተሰምዐ ፡ ወደሙ ፡ ለጻድቅ ፡ በቅድመ ፡ እግዚአ ፡ መናፍስት ፡ ተፈቅደ ። </ab>
         <listRelation><relation name="skos:broadMatch" 
            active="https://corpuscoranicum.de/kontexte/index/sure/78/vers/38/intertext/913"
            passive="urn:dts:betmas:LIT1340EnochE:2.47"/>
            <relation name="skos:broadMatch" 
               active="https://corpuscoranicum.de/kontexte/index/sure/10/vers/21/intertext/914"
               passive="urn:dts:betmas:LIT1340EnochE:2.47"/></listRelation>
      </div>
   </egXML>
</div>

<div type="level2">
<head>Edition statement, Source statement, and encoding
description</head>
<p>These elements should be provided in the header for texts that we
provide edition for. The Edition statement should specify the origin
of the text. The encoding description specifies the principles used
when encoding, when known (e.g. transcription, specific tag sets,
etc.)</p>
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<editionStmt>
<p>Digital text based on  <bibl><ptr target="bm:Marrassini1993AmdaSeyon"/></bibl>.</p>
</editionStmt>
</egXML>
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Text prepared within the framework of the TraCES project.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<correction>
   <p>The following errors
      in Marrassini edition have been corrected:
      <list>
         <item>...</item>
         <item>...</item>
         <item>...</item>

      </list>
   </p>

</correction>

<normalization>
   <p>Original spelling and typography is retained.</p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
<tagsDecl>
<!-- the format for the tagsDecl to be specified -->
</tagsDecl>

</encodingDesc>
</egXML>

</div>

<div type="level2">
<head>Extent</head>
<p>Extent should be specified for the works wherever possible;
obligatory for works with digital text provided, after the edition
statement:</p>
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<editionStmt>
<p>Digital text based on  <bibl><ptr target="bm:Marrassini1993AmdaSeyon"/></bibl>.</p>
</editionStmt>

<extent>10170  words</extent>
</egXML>

</div>




<div type="level2">
<head>Versions</head>
<p>If you have multiple recensions/version of a text, these can be
linked with a <gi>relation</gi> with
<tag>name='saws:isVersionOf'</tag> this will be used to
pick up these in the text view. The same parallel content in the
different versions should have the same @corresp to a NAR unit and
there should always be a <att>resp</att> in the <tag>div[@type='edition']</tag> containing
this text part with multiple versions with either the initials of the
editor or the pointer to the <att>xml:id</att> of the bibl element which has a
pointer to the edition.</p>

</div>
<div type="level2">
<head>Dates</head>
<p>For the date of creation of a work, use the element
<gi>creation</gi> in <gi>profileDesc</gi>
as in the following example</p>
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<creation when="1555-06-23" corresp="#Pdamot">23 Sane (17 June) 1555 in <placeName ref="LOC2488Damot" xml:id="Pdamot">Damot</placeName></creation>
</egXML>
<p>any other date relevant to the work elaboration or life could be
added in a date element, possibly pointing to one of the placeNames in
the file with a proper ID as in the example below.</p>
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<date when="1555-06-23" corresp="#Pdamot">23 Sane (17 June) 1555</date> in <placeName ref="LOC2488Damot" xml:id="Pdamot">Damot</placeName>
</egXML>
<p>It is important that the ID of the referred place starts with P
because there are cases where <att>corresp</att> is already used to point to
another ID, e.g. a work in another tradition title. Look at this
fictitious example, where I have entered a placeName with Q item ID
from wikidata (Ethiopia) and assigned the second <att>corresp</att> and the ID
with P</p>
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<creation corresp="#t2arabic #Ptest" when="1238-09" >
<placeName ref="Q115" xml:id="Ptest"></placeName>
</creation>
</egXML>
<p>this sounds like a dirty hack to get it working... and it is!</p>
</div>

<div type="level2">
<head>Short Summary of Contents</head>
<p>To provide a short summary of contents use the element
<gi>abstract</gi> in as in this example from
<ref target="https://github.com/BetaMasaheft/Works/blob/master/LIT1252Confes.xml">Confessio
Claudii</ref>
</p>
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<abstract>
<p>A theological treatise believed to be a response of king <persName
ref="PRS4428Galawdew">Galāwdewos</persName> to the Jesuit missionaries headed by <persName
ref="PRS7691Oviedo">Oviedo</persName>.
</p>
</abstract>
</egXML>
<p>The abstract can also mention the total number of words, which
might be then marked up with a
<tag>measure type='words'</tag> within the
<gi>abstract</gi>.</p>
<p>Summaries given in catalogues can be copied here and edited.</p>

</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
