<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/guidelines/master/schema/tei-betamesaheftGL.rng" 
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/guidelines/master/schema/tei-betamesaheftGL.rng" 
type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Workflow</title>
            <author>Pietro Liuzzo</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
          </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Produced by pandoc. Conversion from GIT flavoured markdown to TEI simple.</p>
            <p>transformed to TEI documentation with XSLT by Pietro Liuzzo</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body xml:id="workflow">
         <div type="level1">
            <head>Create a new record</head>
  
  
         </div>
         <div type="level1">
            <head>batch editing files</head>
            <p>You can find and replace strings or regex patterns thourough the
  data in Oxygen for example. Please, make sure you - untick the option
  to create .bak files - in case you forget, and such files are created,
  please DO NOT commit them - before replacing all, you will be asked if
  you want to preview. this is always wise and gives you one more
  occasion to spot check your changes before performing the action</p>
            <p>In case you have anyway made a mistake remember that - before
  committing data you can review in Git desktop the changes and discard
  them if they are wrong. - if you have committed, pushed and you
  realize it was a big mistake, you can still revert your own commit</p>
         </div>
         <div type="level1">
            <head>keeping track</head>
            <p>To keep track of the workflow we use the google drive file linked
  above. PLEASE, note the guidelines for color coding. Use the tabs
  below to switch between categories each line in the file corresponds
  to a file in the corresponding GIThub Repo. https://github.com/SChAth
  * color the text in red if an entry has been added to the spreadsheet,
  but the file still needs to be created * color the text black and the
  cell yellow once the file has been created and is in repo * to submit
  a file for review color it purple * Alessandro should color green
  approved records * Pietro will make blue records already online. This
  will be subject to a different update workflow.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
