<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/guidelines/master/schema/out/tei-betamesaheftGL.rng"
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/guidelines/master/schema/out/tei-betamesaheftGL.rng"
type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Workflow</title>
            <author>Pietro Liuzzo</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
          </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Produced by pandoc. Conversion from GIT flavoured markdown to TEI simple.</p>
            <p>transformed to TEI documentation with XSLT by Pietro Liuzzo</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body xml:id="workflow">
        <div type="level2">
<p>In general the workflow for the app can be called github based. The app relyies on data which is pushed from github and is validated.</p>
<p>It can happen that a file goes out of sync, but the data is kept in the github repository separated from the code to be available for other implementations and applications.</p>
<p>That is to say, if you do not see your data updated in few seconds, then please see the <ref target="validation">validation</ref> page and if this does not help, open an issue.</p>
        </div>

         <div type="level2">
            <head>Batch editing files</head>
            <p>You can find and replace strings or regex patterns thourough the
  data in Oxygen for example. Please, make sure you - untick the option
  to create .bak files - in case you forget, and such files are created,
  please DO NOT commit them - before replacing all, you will be asked if
  you want to preview. this is always wise and gives you one more
  occasion to spot check your changes before performing the action</p>
            <p>In case you have anyway made a mistake remember that - before
  committing data you can review in Git desktop the changes and discard
  them if they are wrong. - if you have committed, pushed and you
  realize it was a big mistake, you can still revert your own commit</p>
         </div>
         <div type="level2">
            <head>Keeping track</head>
            <p>To keep track of the workflow we use to refer to a google drive spreadsheet. This workflow is deprecated and discouraged in any way, as the spreadsheet is outdated by two years and should not be used to support any statement about entities in the website. Its historical purpose, and usage to originate the initial batch of data does not justify the redundancy of going back to look into that.
            </p>
            <p>You can use your user page to </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
