<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/guidelines/master/schema/out/tei-betamesaheftGL.rng"
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/guidelines/master/schema/out/tei-betamesaheftGL.rng"
type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Zotero Bibliography Guidelines</title>
            <author>Pietro Liuzzo</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
          </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Produced by pandoc. Conversion from GIT flavoured markdown to TEI simple.</p>
            <p>transformed to TEI documentation with XSLT by Pietro Liuzzo</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>       <revisionDesc>       <change who="PL" when="2018-04-30">first version of guidelines from Wiki</change>     </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body xml:id="zotero">
         <div type="level2">
            <head>Zotero data entry guidelines (valid for all HLCES projects)</head>
            <p>General guidance on bibliography can be found <ref target="https://betamasaheft.github.io/bibliography/">here</ref>.
            This page is about entering data in the <ref target="https://www.zotero.org/groups/ethiostudies/items">Zotero Group Library.</ref></p>
            <p>When adding titles to the EthioStudies Group bibliography please
  make sure you follow the rules:</p>
            <list type="ordered:arabic">
               <item>
                  <p>Make sure that the entry is not there already. And make sure
      that you choose the correct publication type (Journal article,
      Encyclopedia article, etc.). For papers in Conference proceedings
      - use "Book section" in Zotero, do not use
      "Conference paper" as the publication type as then you
      cannot enter series number and some other things in the mask.</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>The titles must be quoted in full (not abbreviated), in the way
      they appear on the frontispiece. All diacritics must be
      preserved.</p>
<list type="ordered:loweralpha">
  <item>
     <p>Titles in English should use maximal capitalization (i.e.
capitalize every words apart from articles and conjunctions),
unless the title is not originally in upper case, then follow the
capitalization as it appears on the book cover. Titles in
languages other than English should use minimal capitalization
(i.e. capitalize only the words which must be capitalized
according to the rules of the language in question, e.g. nouns in
German).</p>
  </item>
  <item>
     <p>The first word of subtitles should always be capitalized.</p>
  </item>
  <item>
     <p>The following punctuation should be used in titles:</p>

  <list>
    <item>
       <p>The punctuation of the original title must be preserved.</p>
    </item>
    <item>
       <p>A colon (:) should be used between the main title and a
  subtitle.</p>
    </item>
    <item>
       <p>If more subtitles are present, they should be divided by a
  comma and capitalized.</p>
    </item>
    <item>
       <p>Use a full stop between titles in different languages in
  publications with a double title. e.g.: Raineri, O. 1996.
  <hi rendition="simple:italic">Santi e guerrieri a cavallo: Tele
  etiopiche, Tele di Qēs Adamu Tesfaw. Warriors Saints on Horseback:
  Ethiopian Paintings, Paintings by Qēs Adamu Tesfaw</hi> (Clusone:
  Ferrari Edizioni, 1996)</p>
    </item>
  </list></item>
  <item>
     <p>For titles in Ethiopic provide the original in fidäl, the
scientific transcription in brackets and the translation into
English.</p>
  </item>
  <item>
     <p>For titles in scripts other than Ethiopic (Arabic, Cyrillic,
etc.), provide the scientific transcription and translation only
(i.e. not the title in the original script).</p>
  </item>
  <item>
     <p>A translation in English is necessary for titles in any
language apart from the three in which Aethiopica accepts
publications (Italian, French and German).</p>
  </item>
  <item>
     <p>Pay attention not to incorporate in the title elements that do
not belong to it, e.g. information such as ‘edited and translated
by’.</p>
  </item>
  <item>
     <p>Journal names are quoted using only the 'main' name, i.e.
Aethiopica, not Aethiopica. International Journal of Ethiopian and
Eritrean Studies.</p>
  </item>
</list>
               </item>


               <item>
                  <p>The names of all authors, editors and translators must be
      provided - in full and as they appear on the book. Make sure that
      you enter editors as editors and authors as authors, not e.g.
      editors as authors in the mask.</p>
      <p>NOTE: Because of the HLCE style, if the SAME person is editor,
author and translator you need to insert their name in the Zotero mask
under EACH of their roles, otherwise the record will not appear
correctly once extracted. For instance: Colin, G. 1986.
<hi rendition="simple:italic">Le Synaxaire éthiopien, Mois de
maskaram</hi>, ed., tr. G. Colin, Patrologia Orientalis, 43/3 (195)
(Turnhout: Brepols, 1986). In Zotero, Colin's name needs to be
inserted in the fields: author, editor and translator.</p>
               </item>

               <item n="4">
                  <p>For the names of the authors/editors, Zotero has the option to
      choose between the “Surname, First name” and simply “Name” (one
      field) form. Make sure that you use 2 fields for occidental names,
      and the 1-field mode for oriental (Ethiopian) names. You can
      switch between the options clicking on the field to the right of
      the name.</p>
                 <list type="ordered:loweralpha">
                    <item>
                       <p>If the name of the authors is not given and not known, use
           Anon. instead of the author's name.</p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                       <p>If the name of the authors is not given on the publication but
           is known through other sources, the name may be given in square
           brackets.</p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                       <p>Author's names in Zotero should be given in full as they appear
           on the publication, but if the full first name is not available
           please provide the initials as given on the book with full points
           AND divided by a space (e.g. 'Mudimbe, V. Y.' and NOT 'Mudimbe, V
           Y' OR 'Mudimbe, V.Y.' Titular prefixes (Sir, Revd, Dr, Captain,
           etc.) are not needed unless their removal would mislead the
           reader.</p>
                    </item>
                 </list>
                 <p>NOTE: The name of the person(s) appearing on the book should be
       treated consistently with what was the author's and publisher's
       intention: a person should be marked as an editor or a translator only
       if this is explicitly written on the book cover and not because the
       text is in our opinion an edition.</p>
               </item>
               <item n="5">
                  <p>In a multi-volume publication, each volume is a separate entry,
      DO NOT merge volumes in one entry. Same is valid for article
      series. Each separately printed piece is a separate Zotero entry.
      Each volume gets a SEPARATE TAG.</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>Each discrete printed entity that potentially may be quotable
      separately is a separate Zotero entry. Meaning a collection
      (Festschrift, Conference proceedings etc etc) get separate entries
      as "Books", and each article in the collection gets its
      own entry as "Book section". In electronic publications,
      both the book and each chapter get independent DOIs.</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>Same applies to articles consisting of sub-articles written by
      different authors: the group article is an entry, but also each
      sub-article by a different author is an entry of its own.</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>In case of multiple reprints: always provide and primarily
      quote the first version. Note that e.g. with CSCO the older series
      volumes are not printed with Peeters in Louvain, and have
      different series numbers – the original series numbers (Ser. II,
      **), publication place (most often Parisiis), publisher and year
      must be provided. All later reprints (Louvain, in the 1960s, with
      the usual CSCO/SAe numbers) are separate, additional, Zotero
      entries.</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>If you import citations from an online source (e.g.
      worldcat.org or JSTOR) make sure that they are correctly imported
      and complete, <hi rendition="simple:bold">Never</hi> import from
      specific library catalogues as you may inherit too many mistakes
      and you risk to import a compilation created only in that specific
      library and actually not existing elsewhere. Do not import any
      library-specific data like shelfmarks, buildings, etc.</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>Always provide the series (full title) and the series number
      when they exist. For series+subseries combinations, the subseries
      has to go with the series number (e.g. Series: Corpus Scriptorium
      Christianorum Orientalium, Series Number: 552, Scriptores
      Aethiopici, 101).</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>Always provide the place of the publisher – in the FORM THEY
      APPEAR ON THE COVER – i.e. for old books e.g. “Lugduni Batavorum”
      and NOT “Leiden”</p>
      <list><item>
         <p>When no place of publication is given, use n.p. instead (it
means 'no place')</p>
      </item>
      <item>
         <p>Abbreviations in city’s and states name are written without
full point and without space in British English, e.g. Washington
DC not Washington D.C. or Washington D. C. or Washington, DC USA
not U.S.A or U. S. A.</p>
      </item></list>
               </item>

               <item n="12">
                  <p>Always provide the publisher in the form he appears on the
      cover (e.g. “Ex officina Danielis &amp; Abrahami à Gaesbeeck” and
      not simply “Daniel &amp; Abraham” as modern catalogues may
      list)</p>
      <list><item>
         <p>If the name of the publisher is in another script, e.g. fidäl
or Arabic, provide the name using the scientific transcription and
not the name in the original script or an English translation
(e.g. Täsfa Gäbrä Śǝllase mattämiya bet and NOT በተስፋ ገብረ ሥላሴ ማተሚያ
ቤት or Täsfa Gäbrä Śǝllase Press).</p>
      </item>
      <item>
         <p>If the name of the publisher is not given on the publication,
use n.pub. instead (it means 'no publisher')</p>
      </item></list>
               </item>

               <item n="13">
                  <p>If the publication date is not given, please use n.d. (no
      date).</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>Most books can be found in HLCES/AAI/Stabi – check the physical
      books. Some older books can be found on Googlebooks and/or
      Archives, and articles on JSTOR and other repositories. In cases
      when the publication is available online add URL/DOI in Zotero
      mask.</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>For related publications (translations, reprints, etc): you can
      establish relations with Zotero.</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>Use Roman numbers for specific volume number for
      "Books" and Arabic numbers for volumes/issues for
      Journals. Filling out the "# of Volume" field is not
      requested, if you fill it out use Arabic number. Also "# of
      pages".</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>In case of 2nd/3rd etc edition: use the "Edition"
      field, write in English only in this field, also for the books in
      other languages (i.e. if the book says "Zweite Auflage"
      you write "2nd edition).</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>Manuscripts should be cited by city (in English), library (name
      in the original language), collection (in the original language),
      shelfmark. Examples: Milan, Biblioteca Ambrosiana, B. 21 inf
      Vercelli, Biblioteca Capitolare, MS 117</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>Do not use any abbreviations for journals, series, libraries,
      etc.</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>If the publisher cites more cities of publication, these can be
      included in the bibliographic record separated by an n rule, e.g.
      'Urbana–Chicago: University of Illinois Press'</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>If there are more than one publisher involved and operating in
      the same city, then the publishers’ name should be divided by an n
      rule, e.g. 'Addis Ababa: CFEE–Institute of Ethiopian Studies'.</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>If more publishers and more places of publication are involved,
      these are separated by , (comma). E.g. 'London: James Currey,
      Athens: Ohio University Press, Addis Ababa: Addis Ababa University
      Press'.</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>When the printing year on the book is expressed in a non-Common
      Era calendar, then both years should be recorded: for instance,
      for a book published in Ethiopia in 1982 EC = 1989/1990 CE write
      in the field date '1989/1990' and in extra '1982 EC'</p>
      <list><item>
         <p>Please note that Zotero extraction of this type of records is
not perfect, but the bibliography tool will fix this for you.</p>
      </item>
      <item>
         <p>The abbreviations to be used are EC for Ethiopian Calendar and
H for Hegira.</p>
      </item></list>
               </item>

               <item n="24">
                  <p>For bibliographic records in which the editorial and publishing
      years are different, the editorial year is used as the point of
      reference, as easier to define. E.g. Löfgren, O. 1962.
      ‘Äthiopische Wandamulette’, Orientalia Suecana, 11 (1962, pub.
      1963), 95–120. Both sets of information need to be input in
      Zotero, with the editorial year (1962) given under 'Date' and the
      publishing year given under 'Extra' as 'pub. 1963'.</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>If you have a date across two years like 2011-2012, please
      enter it both in the date filed as is and in extra with the
      following syntax: "issued: 2011/2012" This will ensure
      that both results printed with the HLZ styles from standalone and
      API will be correct.</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>Do not forget to test via the "export" function that
      the titles appear the way you would want to see them in a
      publishable bibliography. For quoting in publications of the
      HLCES: use the Hiob Ludolf Centre for Ethiopian Studies style
      provided in Zotero repository
      (https://www.zotero.org/styles?q=hiob%20) – when you export your
      bibliography with this style make sure it corresponds to the
      appearance foreseen by the guidelines (e.g. here:
      https://www.aai.uni-hamburg.de/en/comst/publications/bulletin.html)
      - if not, maybe something is entered wrongly.</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>NB: when creating tags note that these may be only ASCII
      alphanumeric combinations, do not use diacritical symbols (umlauts
      etc.)</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>superscripts and subscripts should use
      <gi>sup</gi> and
      <gi>sub</gi>, as described here.
      https://www.zotero.org/support/kb/rich_text_bibliography these can
      be used also for cases in which the title contains formatting</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>EACH Encyclopaedia entry must have volume and short title
      indicated if you want to get the correct citation style for
      Aethiopica. eg. ‘Mikaʾel Sǝḥul’, EAe, III (2007), 962b–964b (J.
      Abbink)</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>Do not upload PDFs in the group bibliography. If they are
      necessary to substantiate your bibliographic entry, then please
      add a note to explain what is in the pdf which provides evidence
      for the decisions taken in entering the data in the record and
      perhaps inform on the PDF availability.</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>If your entry is to be used in BetaMasaheft or Dillmann Online,
      then you need to add a tag with this format and using only latin
      alphabet letters</p>
      <p>bm:AuthorYYYYkeyword</p>
      <p>Please make sure <hi rendition="simple:bold">this contains no
special characters, umlaut, underdots and other combining
diacritics</hi>, only digits and latin characters. To check that this
is unique, after saving the record in Zotero, click on the tag and
check that only one item has this tag. If not, change the keyword of
the tag just assigned.</p>
                  <p><hi rendition="simple:bold">Please do not change existing tags</hi>, as they probably already have been used in Beta maṣāḥǝft or Dillmann.
                     Small inconsistencies and typos in tags can be ignored. Adjusting their cosmetics to feet your taste is only going to harm.</p>
                     <p>In case double bm: tags have been assigned, please proceede immediately to check which one is actually in use. Update the occurrences of the minority attestation and remove the unneeded tag.</p>
                     <p>In case of double entries each with a bm: tag, the guidelines have not been followed for the one created the latest. You are welcome to blame them and move to the author of the
                       mistake the need to immediately clean the Zotero database from the wrongly created record AND update all occurrences of the tag assigned to it with the correct tag of the correct entry.</p>
                       <p>Please always be very careful. If you think it is a double but you are not sure, ASK. For example sometimes two records seem the same
but they are not as for instance the publisher is different. In that case
they are not double records and should not be removed.</p>
               </item>
            </list>

         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
